<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0001" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Chile swine flu cases jump to 276
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Santiago, May 31, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Chilean health authorities confirmed 26 new cases of swine flu on Sunday,
raising the number of patients with A(H1N1) virus in the country to 276, the
highest number on the continent.
</P>
<P>
The sometimes-deadly disease continued its rise across Latin America meanwhile
with Argentina, Brazil, Bolivia, Peru and the Dominican Republic all reporting
new cases.
</P>
<P>
Officials here said that most of the victims were in the capital, and that most
cases were mild and being treated at home. Three people remain in serious
condition in hospital, however.
</P>
<P>
Swine flu has killed nearly a hundred and infected over 15,500 worldwide,
according to World Health Organization (WHO) figures, since it emerged in North
America in late April.
</P>
<P>
According to figures released by individual governments, the virus has actually
now killed more than 110 people around the world.
</P>
<P>
In the southern hemisphere, health experts fear the new virus could take hold,
as winter sets in and the regular flu season gets underway.
</P>
<P>
Argentine health authorities meanwhile reported 15 new cases on Sunday, a day
after reporting 20 new cases, raising the country's total patient count to 115.
</P>
<P>
Officials in Buenos Aires said those with new swine flu infections were
recovering well and that most of them were found at several private schools in
the capital, where students had recently returned from the United States.
</P>
<P>
The outbreak has prompted officials to close the schools for two weeks in a bid
to contain the virus.
</P>
<P>
In the Dominican Republic officials confirmed nine cases of the disease, raising
the country's total to 11, a day after Santo Domingo rebuffed a Russian claim
that the Caribbean island was underreporting its cases in a bid to boost
tourism.
</P>
<P>
"We fear that in reality, the situation is very different," Gennady Onishchenko,
Russia's chief sanitary inspector, had told the Interfax news agency in response
to the island reporting only two cases.
</P>
<P>
On Sunday the island's Ministry of Public Health reported that of the nine new
cases one had been hospitalized.
</P>
<P>
In Peru health authorities said they had confirmed two more cases of the virus,
bringing the country's total to 40.
</P>
<P>
Both cases were found in Lima and are recovering well on medication at home,
officials said.
</P>
<P>
Brazil also confirmed four new cases, which brought the country's total number
to 20.
</P>
<P>
At its last count at the end of last week Mexican authorities said 97 people had
died from the disease and that 4,932 had been infected. Officials however
maintained that the epidemic was on the wane there.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0002" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Basketball: Despite sting of defeat, James says Cavs on right track
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
CLEVELAND, Ohio, May 31, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
National Basketball Association Most Valuable Player LeBron James insisted
Sunday that Cleveland were on the right track, despite their painful failure to
reach the NBA finals.
</P>
<P>
James couldn't bring himself to address the media or congratulate the players of
the Orlando Magic on Saturday night, after the Magic defeated the Cavs in game
six of the Eastern Conference finals to reach the league's championship series.
</P>
<P>
But as he and teammates gathered for the last team meeting of the season here on
Sunday, James tried to put a positive spin on the Cavaliers season.
</P>
<P>
Cleveland notched the best record in the regular season with 66 victories, won
their division and swept to victory in four games in each of their first two
playoff series.
</P>
<P>
Then they ran into the surprising Magic, who had already ousted reigning
champions Boston in seven games, and even "King" James's heroics couldn't save
them.
</P>
<P>
"You want to continue to get better, that's all you can ask," said James, whose
team lost to Boston in the conference finals last year.
</P>
<P>
"We got better this season and I feel this team will be better next season. You
don't want to take a step backward. I thought we went forward from the Boston
series to this year and hopefully we can go forward one more time next year."
</P>
<P>
James certainly did all he could to take his team one step further.
</P>
<P>
His buzzer-beating 3-pointer saved Cleveland in game two against Orlando. He had
21 points, 17 in the second half, in game five, a contest that saw him finish
with 37 points, 14 rebounds and 12 assists.
</P>
<P>
Now the big question exercising Cleveland - the club's management, his teammates
and Cavs fans - is how this defeat will influence his future with the team.
</P>
<P>
The Cavaliers can offer him a contract extension in July. He can extend the
contract up to four years, or play out his current contract that ends after next
season and make a move via free agency. He could also exercise a player option
for the 2010-11 season.
</P>
<P>
"I haven't thought about it just yet," James said. "I'm just going to take time
off from basketball and not think about contracts or the game, period, and relax
with my family."
</P>
<P>
James defended his actions in Orlando on Saturday, when he strode off the court
- to a smattering of taunts from Magic fans - without congratulating his
opponents.
</P>
<P>
"I just didn't have much to say," said James, who said he had since e-mailed
Orlando star Dwight Howard. "One thing about me you've got to understand - it is
hard for me to congratulate somebody after just losing to him.
</P>
<P>
"I'm a winner. That's not being a poor sport or anything like that. If somebody
beats you up, you are not going to congratulate them (for) beating you up. That
doesn't make sense to me."
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0003" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
US pleased with new talks with Cuba: Clinton
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
San Salvador, May 31, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
US Secretary of State Hillary Clinton said here Sunday the United States is
pleased that Cuba has agreed to resume talks on migration issues and to start
discussions on direct mail service.
</P>
<P>
"We're very pleased that the Cuban government has agreed to talks on migration
and direct mail links," Clinton told reporters after US officials announced the
new discussions that continue a US-Cuban thaw in ties.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0004" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
URGENT еее US pleased with migration, mail service talks with Cuba: Clinton
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
San Salvador, May 31, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Secretary of State Hillary Clinton said here Sunday the United States is pleased
that Cuba has agreed to resume talks on migration issues and to start
discussions on direct mail service.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0005" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Business says British politicians distracted by expenses row
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
LONDON, June 1, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The row over MPs' expenses is distracting Britain's politicians from confronting
the serious economic issues facing the country, a prominent business leader said
Monday.
</P>
<P>
Richard Lambert, director-general of the CBI, told the Financial Times that all
the main parties should be focusing on their plans to deal with the recession
ahead of European and local elections later this week.
</P>
<P>
"I've just been talking to business people in Brussels and the sense of
bewilderment about what's happening and what it means for the UK and Europe is
palpable," Lambert told the FT.
</P>
<P>
"We've got important elections and they are being completely overshadowed by
these disclosures."
</P>
<P>
He added: "Clearly there's an enormous, understandable public outrage... but
we've got big decisions to be taken by all the big political parties about the
future shape and role of the state, and these have been completely brushed to
one side."
</P>
<P>
Polls over the weekend suggested British Prime Minister Gordon Brown's Labour
party is in danger of coming third in the elections for the European Parliament
on Thursday, largely because of disillusionment over the expenses row.
</P>
<P>
The main opposition Conservatives have also suffered from the scandal and
analysts expect fringe parties such as the anti-EU UK Independence Party (Ukip)
and the far-right British National Party to benefit.
</P>
<P>
Brown insisted Sunday that he was focused on the recession, brushing aside calls
for him to quit in favour of a more popular leader and saying: "I am dealing
with the economy every day."
</P>
<P>
In an article in the Daily Mirror, he also launched a strong attack on the BNP,
describing them as a "nasty extreme party" made up of "Nazi thugs" and urging
voters not to back them when they go to the polls this week.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0006" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
ALERT е
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
US pleased Cuba agrees to talks on migration, direct mail: Clinton
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0007" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Golf: Stricker claims Colonial crown at second hole of sudden death
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
FORT WORTH, Texas, May 31, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Steve Stricker birdied the second playoff hole to win the 6.2 million-dollar
Colonial on Sunday, leaving South African Tim Clark still in search of his first
USPGA tour title.
</P>
<P>
Stricker defeated Clark and Steve Marino in the playoff to claim his first title
of 2009 to go with his runner-up, third-place, fourth-place, sixth- and seventh-
place finishes this year.
</P>
<P>
For Clark it was yet another near miss. His 12.7 million dollars in US earnings
are the most of any player without a victory in PGA Tour history.
</P>
<P>
He squandered a two-shot lead with five holes left, including a bogey on the
72nd hole that forced the playoff.
</P>
<P>
He also missed a putt that would have given him the victory at the first playoff
hole.
</P>
<P>
On the second, Stricker stuck his approach within a few feet and Clark almost
followed suit.
</P>
<P>
But Clark's hit the stick and rolled more than 20 feet away. The South African
missed his birdie attempt and Stricker made his for a fifth career crown.
</P>
<P>
Clark, meanwhile, settled for a seventh second-place finish, including at this
tournament behind Phil Mickelson last year.
</P>
<P>
Clark, who started the day with a two-stroke lead, carded a 70 to finish
regulation on 263. Stricker and Marino both shot 68 to join him in the playoff.
</P>
<P>
Australian Jason Day carded a 69 to finish alone in fourth on 264, one shot in
front of England's Paul Casey.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0008" type="advis" >
<HEADLINE>
AFP sports schedule for Monday, June 1
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Paris, June 1, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
AFP sports schedule for Monday, June 1:

TENNIS

Day nine of the French Open sees men's number two seed Roger Federer playing
Tommy Haas, and women's number two seed Serena Williams playing Canadian
Aleksandra Wozniak.

Coverage by Dave James and Tom Williams

Slug: Tennis-FRA-Open

ATHLETICS

Ethiopian Haile Gebrselassie is targeting a fifth world record at the Hengelo
Grand Prix, that of the one-hour run.

Slug: Athletics-NED

CRICKET

Build-up to ICC World Twenty20 in England which starts on Friday.

See separate advisory.

Slug: Cricket-ICC-T20
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0009" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
2,000 to leave Australian flu ship after all-clear: officials
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Sydney, June 1, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
About 2,000 passengers were given the all-clear to leave the Pacific Dawn cruise
ship here on Monday after Australian officials found none was carrying swine
flu.
</P>
<P>
The ship has been at the centre of an outcry after infected passengers were
allowed to disembark last week, prompting an explosion in Australia's swine flu
cases.
</P>
<P>
"No evidence of any additional cases of human swine influenza has been found on
board the Pacific Dawn, and most importantly, there has been no person-to-person
transmission on board the ship," New South Wales' top health official, Kerry
Chant, said in a statement.
</P>
<P>
Three crew members who caught the disease have now recovered and remain in
quarantine, P&amp;O Cruises said in a statement.
</P>
<P>
Infected passengers were among 2,000 who disembarked here last Monday following
an earlier cruise on the ship. Australia's swine flu cases, then fewer than 20,
had shot up to 303 by Sunday.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0010" type="other" >
<HEADLINE>
Golf: Colonial final round scores
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
FORT WORTH, Texas, May 31, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
Leading final-round scores here on Sunday in the 6.2 million-dollar Colonial
(x-won at 2nd playoff hole; USA unless noted):

263 - x-Steve Stricker 63-63-69-68, Tim Clark (RSA) 63-64-66-70, Stephen Marino
66-67-62-68

264 - Jason Day (AUS) 65-65-65-69

265 - Paul Casey (GBR) 66-67-66-66

266 - Woody Austin 63-68-67-68, Vijay Singh (FIJ) 64-64-69-69

268 - Ian Poulter (GBR) 66-69-65-68

269 - Jim Furyk 68-69-67-65, Zach Johnson 69-67-64-69, Kevin Na 66-68-66-69,
Kevin Sutherland 66-67-68-68

270 - Luke Donald (GBR) 68-65-67-70, Tom Lehman 68-69-66-67, Justin Leonard
66-68-64-72, Jeff Overton 69-67-65-69, Charlie Wi (KOR) 67-70-66-67

...

271 - John Senden (AUS) 68-67-67-69

272 - Nick O'Hern (AUS) 69-69-66-68

273 - Stephen Ames (CAN) 68-68-67-70

274 - Brian Davis (GBR) 69-68-70-67, Justin Rose (GBR) 69-69-70-66, Rory
Sabbatini (RSA) 71-69-69-65

276 - Fredrik Jacobson (SWE) 68-70-66-72, Danny Lee (NZL) 69-67-71-69

277 - James Nitties (AUS) 67-68-70-72

278 - Geoff Ogilvy (AUS) 70-67-67-74, Greg Owen (GBR) 68-69-69-72

279 - Carl Pettersson (SWE) 71-68-69-71, Adam Scott (AUS) 68-71-69-71, Mike Weir
(CAN) 69-67-72-71

280 - Richard S. Johnson (SWE) 71-69-70-70, Rod Pampling (AUS) 73-66-67-74

281 - Ryuji Imada (JPN) 69-68-73-71

Made cut/Did not finish (MDF)

212 - Aron Price (AUS) 67-72-73
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0011" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Rugby Union: International result - USA 10 Ireland 27
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
SANTA CLARA, California, May 31, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Result from Sunday's United States-Ireland rugby union international match:
</P>
<P>
United States 10 Ireland 27
</P>
<P>
H-t: 0-13
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0012" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Britain's Prince Harry admits finding army training tough
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
LONDON, June 1, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Britain's Prince Harry admitted Monday that he sometimes questions whether he
will succeed in his army training -- but said his brother Prince William helps
take the pressure off by cooking for him.
</P>
<P>
The 24-year-old, the youngest son of Prince Charles and the late princess Diana,
is currently training to be a pilot with the Army Air Corps.
</P>
<P>
Based at RAF Shawbury in the West Midlands, he lives with William, who is
training to become a search and rescue pilot with the Royal Air Force (RAF).
</P>
<P>
"We hardly ever see each other. And now we are living together and it's
fantastic," Harry said in a syndicated interview.
</P>
<P>
"(William) does most of the cooking. I spend time just lying around, watching TV
and doing my work," he said, and joked: "The RAF don't have to work as hard as
the army."
</P>
<P>
William is reportedly giving his brother advice ahead of his first helicopter
flight in the coming weeks, and Harry admitted that he had found the training
difficult.
</P>
<P>
"The flying courses are so intense," he said, adding: "It's surprised me."
</P>
<P>
He said: "There's times when I thought, you know, I'm really not cut out for
this, mentally. I hope I've got the physical skills to fly a helicopter.
</P>
<P>
"But mentally, there are the exams and everything. I mean, I can't do maths, I
gave that up when I left school, as anyone does at that age. But I've been
throwing myself back in the deep end."
</P>
<P>
Harry has recently returned from a two-day visit to New York, which he described
as a "nice break" from the training. It was his first trip abroad as official
representative of Buckingham Palace.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0013" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Football: Perez to take reins at Real Madrid again
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
MADRID, June 1, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Spanish construction magnate Florentino Perez will be sworn in as president of
Real Madrid again later on Monday as no other candidate stood against him before
the deadline, the club said.
</P>
<P>
The 62-year-old will be sworn in at the Real's Santiago Bernabeu stadium at 1 pm
(1100 GMT), the club said in a statement posted on its website shortly after the
deadline of midnight (2200 GMT) on Sunday had expired.
</P>
<P>
Several challengers who had been expected to oppose him pulled out or were not
able to lodge a bank guarantee of 57.4 million euros (81.1 million dollars)
required by the club to be able to run for president.
</P>
<P>
Perez last led Real, Spain's historically most successful team and the world's
richest football club by revenues, from 2000 to 2006.
</P>
<P>
Under his rein Real earned the nickname "Los Galacticos", winning the Primera
Liga twice and the European Champions League with such stars as Zinedine Zidane,
Ronaldo, Luis Figo and David Beckham.
</P>
<P>
He officially presented his candidacy on Thursday under the slogan "the dream is
back" and said the team he would help build would be world beaters.
</P>
<P>
"We will build a spectacular team with top notch players. We have set up a
strong and stable sporting project which will be able to call upon footballers
who will turn each Real Madrid match into a fascinating rendez-vous," he said.
</P>
<P>
Perez has not mentioned any names regarding top signings but Spanish media has
reported that Chilean Manuel Pellegrini, currently at Villarreal, would become
coach in place of Juande Ramos and the club would also land AC Milan's Brazilian
playmaker Kaka.
</P>
<P>
Media reports also constantly speculate that Cristiano Ronaldo, Liverpool's
Spanish star Xabi Alonso and Bayern Munich's French star Franck Ribery will don
the all-white strip next term.
</P>
<P>
Real has been led on an interim basis by Vicente Boluda, who took the reins of
the club after Ramon Calderon stepped down in January following allegations that
he rigged voting at the club's last annual general assembly in December.
</P>
<P>
Had another candidate stood against Perez, elections for president -- normally
held every four years -- would have taken place on June 14.
</P>
<P>
Real's arch-rivals Barcelona won the Champions League, the Spanish title and the
Spanish Cup this season under debutante coach Pep Guardiola.
</P>
<P>
But in an interview published Sunday in daily newspaper El Pais, Perez said
Barcelona's success this season "motivates me even more".
</P>
<P>
"I do not place any limit on myself," he told the newspaper, adding the club
"needs a revolution".
</P>
<P>
Real ended the season on Sunday with a 2-1 loss to lowly Osasuna.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="AFP_ENG_20090531.0014" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Football: FIFA 'in compliance' with world anti-doping code - Blatter
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
NASSAU, May 31, 2009 (AFP)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
World football's governing body has been notified that its policies are "totally
in compliance" with those of the World Anti-Doping Agency, apart from the issue
of reintegrating players after a suspension, FIFA president Joseph Blatter said
Sunday.
</P>
<P>
Blatter, speaking at the conclusion of FIFA executive committee meetings here,
said WADA had confirmed that "FIFA's disciplinary code and FIFA's anti-doping
code, is totally in compliance with the WADA code".
</P>
<P>
The lone exception, he said had to do with when suspended players can resume
training with their clubs.
</P>
<P>
FIFA secretary general Jerome Valcke said that FIFA's position is that a player
suspended for 12 months should be allowed to resume training after nine months.
</P>
<P>
FIFA and WADA had been at odds recently over WADA requirements on availablity of
players for out-of-competition drugs testing.
</P>
<P>
Since the beginning of January, the world anti-doping code requires elite
athletes to give notice of their location at a chosen one-hour period each day,
seven days a week.
</P>
<P>
FIFA had contended that players should be subject to testing when with their
teams, but not when on holiday.
</P>
<P>
World anti-doping chief John Fahey said FIFA's stance "ignores the reality of
doping in sport."
</P>
<P>
"There is no problem between the WADA organization and FIFA," Blatter said.
</P>
<P>
"The only problem that we had, which has now been put away ... is the question,
'Is WADA a service organization for the world of sport?' The answer is yes. WADA
is not a police organization."
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0001" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Philippines president remembers Aquino
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
WASHINGTON 2009-08-01 00:03:06 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Philippines President Gloria Macapagal Arroyo is remembering former President Corazon Aquino as a "national treasure" who led the country at a time of great peril.
</P>
<P>
Arroyo, on an official visit to Washington, says the Philippines will observe 10 days of official mourning following Aquino's death early Saturday in Manila.
</P>
<P>
She says Aquino "picked up the standard" after her husband, Benigno "Ninoy" Aquino Jr., was assassinated on the tarmac of Manila's international airport in 1983 as he returned from exile in the United States to challenge longtime leader Ferdinand Marcos.
</P>
<P>
Arroyo says Aquino "helped lead a revolution to restore democracy and the rule of law to our nation at a time of great peril."
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0002" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Islamist sect leader in Nigeria killed in custody
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
MAIDUGURI, Nigeria 2009-08-01 00:06:03 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The leader of the Islamist sect blamed for days of violence in northern Nigeria has been shot and killed while in police custody, officials said.
</P>
<P>
The police commander of Borno state announced on state radio Thursday that Mohammed Yusuf, the leader of the sect some call the Nigerian Taliban, has "died in police custody."
</P>
<P>
He gave no further explanation, but the state governor's spokesman Usman Ciroma told The Associated Press: "I saw his body at police headquarters. I believe he was shot while he was trying to escape."
</P>
<P>
Yusuf's death could provoke more violence, though his followers in the Boko Haram sect may be in disarray after troops shelled his compound in the northern city of Maiduguri on Wednesday. Yusuf, 39, managed to escape with about 300 followers, some of them armed. His deputy, Bukar Shekau, was killed in the attack, according to Army commander Maj. Gen. Saleh Maina.
</P>
<P>
Troops killed about 100 militants by an AP reporter's count, half of them inside the sect's mosque. Soldiers then launched a manhunt, and Yusuf was reportedly found in a goat's pen at the home of his in-laws.
</P>
<P>
Human Rights Watch called reports of Yusuf's killing "extremely worrying."
</P>
<P>
"The Nigerian authorities must act immediately to investigate and hold to account all those responsible for this unlawful killing and any others associated with the recent violence in northern Nigeria," said Corinne Dufka, the group's senior West Africa researcher.
</P>
<P>
"The local commissioner of police should be immediately removed pending an investigation into Mr. Yusuf's killing," she said in a statement.
</P>
<P>
Leading Nigerian rights groups accuse security forces of killing bystanders and other civilians. A military spokesman denied the charge and said it was impossible for rights workers to tell who was a civilian and who was a member of Boko Haram, which means "Western education is sin" in the local Hausa language.
</P>
<P>
The government warned people to evacuate the area before the attack on the compound Wednesday, then shelled the compound and stormed the group's mosque inside, setting off a raging firefight with retreating militants armed with homemade hunting rifles and firebombs, bows and arrows, machetes and scimitars.
</P>
<P>
An AP reporter saw soldiers shoot their way into the mosque under fire and then raked those inside with gunshots.
</P>
<P>
The bodies of barefoot young men littered the streets of Maiduguri, the capital of Borno state, on Thursday morning as the army pursued the manhunt on the outskirts of the city. Police said most of the dead were fighters with Boko Haram. Army Col. Ben Anahotu said three police officers were killed.
</P>
<P>
Seeking to impose Islamic Shariah law throughout this multi-religious country, the militants attacked police stations, churches, prisons and government buildings in a wave of violence that began Sunday in Borno and quickly spread to three other northern states.
</P>
<P>
Officials said at least 4,000 people have been forced from their homes by Wednesday afternoon, but it was not known how many have been killed, wounded and arrested.
</P>
<P>
President Umaru Yar'Adua said that security agents had been ordered to attack when the movement started gathering fighters from nearby states at its sprawling Maiduguri compound in preparation for "the holy war."
</P>
<P>
The militants are also known as Al-Sunna wal Jamma, or "Followers of Mohammed's Teachings," and some Nigerian officials have referred to them as Taliban. Analyst Nnamdi K. Obasi of the International Crisis Group said a few have fought with that radical movement in Afghanistan.
</P>
<P>
League for Human Rights director Shamaki Gad Peter said that after the siege rights workers saw the bodies of up to 20 people who were unarmed and appeared to have been shot from behind, possibly trying to escape the mayhem, he said.
</P>
<P>
Military spokesman Col. Mohammed Yerima initially denied allegations that the military intentionally killed civilians but said that the militants were indistinguishable from civilians.
</P>
<P>
"All the civilians that were living in that place were evacuated, to our knowledge," he said. "And those that remained in that enclave are loyalists and members of the group. So the issue of whether we have killed innocent civilians is not true."
</P>
<P>
He added, "The issue of identifying who is the Taliban or not, the human rights groups are not fair to security agencies because they don't have any marks on their faces. There is no way to know if this is Taliban or this is not."
</P>
<P>
Maiduguri resident Linda Dukwa said she had seen police execute two men Monday, frightening her and her family so badly that they did not venture out of their house, even for food, for days afterward.
</P>
<P>
The men "were dressed in white robes," she said, indicating they were sect members. "They were held by policemen. Then they shot their feet. After they fell on the ground, they (police) shot their heads."
</P>
<P>
National police spokesman Emmanuel Ojukwu denied such allegations of executions.
</P>
<P>
"We respect the rules of combat," he said.
</P>
<P>
Nigeria's 140 million people are roughly divided between Christians in the south and northern-based Muslims. Shariah was implemented in 12 northern states after Nigeria returned to civilian rule in 1999 following years of oppressive military regimes. More than 10,000 Nigerians have died in sectarian violence since then.
</P>
<P>
Dire poverty is at the heart of the violence, which analysts say reflects decades-old grievances of Nigerians whose governments are so corrupt and ineffective they do not deliver even basic services like running water and electricity.
</P>
<P>
Boko Haram members are particularly angry that full Shariah has not been implemented, especially the law's demand for a social welfare system helping poor people.
</P>
<P>
In recent months, police have been raiding Boko Haram hideouts and finding explosives and arms. The house at the compound in Maiduguri included a laboratory the military said was used to make bombs.
</P>
<P>
----------
</P>
<P>
Associated Press writers Muhammad Wahab in Bauchi, Bashir Adigun in Abuja and Michelle Faul and Anita Powell in Johannesburg contributed to this report.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0004" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Pakistan court rules Musharraf ' s emergency illegal
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
ISLAMABAD 2009-08-01 00:07:23 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Pakistan's Supreme Court has ruled that the state of emergency former President Pervez Musharraf imposed in 2007 was unconstitutional and declared invalid the appointments of judges he made during that period.
</P>
<P>
The decision Friday could lay the groundwork for treason charges against the ex-army chief, and some fear it could cause political turmoil at a time when Pakistan is battling a Taliban insurgency. But the court said the ruling -- the most severe against a former military leader -- would strengthen democracy in a country plagued by repeated military dictatorships.
</P>
<P>
The 14-member bench that delivered the ruling was headed by Chief Justice Iftikhar Mohammed Chaudhry, whose attempted ouster by Musharraf spurred much of the unrest that led to the strongman's downfall.
</P>
<P>
"The constitution is supreme, and this decision will strengthen democracy and democratic institutions," Chaudhry said.
</P>
<P>
The court added that rulings made by the judges who were improperly appointed could still stand, and told Parliament to decide which of the laws that Musharraf pushed through during the unconstitutional emergency could remain on the books.
</P>
<P>
Musharraf declared the emergency when it appeared the Supreme Court might challenge his eligibility for office. Eventually, under domestic and international pressure, Musharraf allowed elections that brought his foes to power in February 2008. Under threat of impeachment, he stepped down in August 2008.
</P>
<P>
Ever since, many opponents have demanded that he be held accountable.
</P>
<P>
Musharraf, who is living in London, ignored a summons to appear before the court or send a lawyer this week to explain his actions.
</P>
<P>
A man who answered the phone at a number for Musharraf in Britain said the retired general had no comment.
</P>
<P>
The court decision was eagerly awaited by many Pakistanis, especially lawyers who led a movement that helped push Musharraf from office.
</P>
<P>
Prime Minister Yousuf Raza Gilani welcomed the decision, describing it as a good omen for the future of democracy in Pakistan, which has been run by the army for about half of its nearly 62-year existence.
</P>
<P>
Farahnaz Ispahani, a spokeswoman for President Asif Ali Zardari, also hailed the ruling, describing it as "the last nail in the coffin of dictatorship."
</P>
<P>
Because of a legal twist, one measure that could come up for review is an ordinance -- signed by Musharraf before the emergency -- that granted amnesty in corruption cases to Zardari and his wife, slain former Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto.
</P>
<P>
Zardari succeeded Bhutto as leader of the Pakistan People's Party after she was assassinated in December 2007. As president, he enjoys broad legal immunity for the duration of his term, even if Parliament overturns the amnesty deal.
</P>
<P>
But prominent lawyer Athar MinAllah said the case paved the way for trying Musharraf on treason charges, which could carry the death penalty, but noted that such charges can only be filed by the federal government.
</P>
<P>
Musharraf seized power in a 1999 military coup and became a key ally in the U.S.-led war against al-Qaida following the Sept. 11, 2001, attacks that sparked the American-led invasion of neighboring Afghanistan.
</P>
<P>
In early 2007, he dismissed Chaudhry as the court was about to rule on the validity of Musharraf's holding two offices -- that of president and chief of army staff. Chaudhry's removal triggered mass lawyer-led protests that damaged Musharraf's popularity.
</P>
<P>
The court managed to bring Chaudhry back, but faced with growing rancor and fearing he could be ousted, Musharraf declared the emergency, tossing out Chaudhry again along with around 60 other judges.
</P>
<P>
The move deepened anger against Musharraf, who eventually lifted the emergency. He stepped down as army chief and allowed parliamentary elections the following February that brought his political foes to power. But even after his resignation, the fate of the judges caused fissures among those who came to power.
</P>
<P>
------
</P>
<P>
Associated Press writers Raphael G. Satter in London and Munir Ahmad and Elena Becatoros in Islamabad contributed to this report.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0006" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
TVA raises coal ash tab to $1.2B
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
KNOXVILLE, Tennessee 2009-08-01 00:10:15 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Tennessee Valley Authority raised its estimates for cleaning up a massive coal ash spill to $1.2 billion on Friday, and partly blamed its third-quarter loss of $167 million on that cleanup.
</P>
<P>
America's largest public utility said in a filing to the Securities and Exchange Commission that the tab could reach $933 million to $1.2 billion to restore the Kingston, Tennessee, community after 5.4 million cubic yards (4.13 million cubic meters) of toxic ash breached a holding pond at a coal-fired power plant on Dec. 22.
</P>
<P>
No one was injured, but the spill of millions of tons of ash and sludge swept into a river, damaged two-dozen homes, covered 300 acres (121 hectares), raised health concerns throughout the community and brought congressional attention to the lack of regulation of similar sites around the country.
</P>
<P>
TVA's latest cleanup estimate is at least $200 million higher than previous calculations and still doesn't include potential fines, penalties, or the outcome of seven federal lawsuits filed by residents.
</P>
<P>
"This range could change significantly depending on whether new coal ash laws and regulations are implemented at the state or federal level," said the report from TVA Chief Financial Officer Kim Greene.
</P>
<P>
The cleanup cost also "is in large part dependent on the final disposal plan, which is still in development by TVA and by regulatory authorities," the report said.
</P>
<P>
Knoxville-based TVA is a self-financing government corporation that issues bonds to raise capital but does not sell stock. Its ratepayers in Tennessee and six surrounding states feel the consequences of its financial decisions in their power bills.
</P>
<P>
In its SEC filing, TVA reported a $167 million loss on $2.5 billion in revenue for the quarter ending June 30, compared with a $100 million gain on similar revenue for the same period a year ago. The utility is running $339 million in the red on $8.6 billion in revenues through the first nine months of the year.
</P>
<P>
TVA blamed the poor performance on the ash spill and a drop in electric sales because of the economy. Power sales are down 7 percent for the year, notably among major industrial customers served by TVA directly.
</P>
<P>
Greene noted that TVA would need to invest in cleaner energy resources, and said some of the utility's expenses may need to be covered by power rate increases.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0008" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Criminal charges in Colombia spy scandal
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
BOGOTA 2009-08-01 00:10:49 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
At least eight former officials of Colombia's domestic intelligence agency surrendered on Friday to face criminal charges for allegedly spying illegally on opponents of President Alvaro Uribe including judges, journalists and human rights workers.
</P>
<P>
They are among 10 former officials whose arrests were ordered Thursday night and include ex-intelligence and counterintelligence chiefs in the DAS security agency, which reports directly to the president.
</P>
<P>
One of the former officials still at large, former DAS deputy director Jose Miguel Narvaez, is also under investigation for murders committed by far-right death squads.
</P>
<P>
If convicted of criminal conspiracy, the 10 face prison terms of up to six years.
</P>
<P>
In its arrest warrant, the chief prosecutor's office said the accused "under the guise of protecting national security ended up persecuting people who were fulfilling constitutional duties" such as Supreme Court justices and lawmakers.
</P>
<P>
It said the accused intercepted phone calls and e-mails and followed targeted individuals "to satisfy dark interests that have not yet been determined."
</P>
<P>
Uribe and officials in his inner circle have denied any illegal activity in connection with the scandal, which broke in February after a new DAS director was installed.
</P>
<P>
The president's first DAS chief after he took office in 2002, Jorge Noguera, is currently in prison awaiting trial on charges including murder for allegedly helping right-wing death squads target union leaders.
</P>
<P>
Analysts and targets of the DAS illegal wiretaps expressed doubts that Uribe could not have known about the extensive spying by the DAS on government opponents.
</P>
<P>
Political analyst Leon Valencia, a former leftist guerrilla, said Uribe "is a president of minute details who knows everything, with an impressive memory."
</P>
<P>
"Nothing happens without his authorization," Valencia said.
</P>
<P>
"An illegal espionage network isn't something run by midlevel officials," said Rafael Pardo, a former defense minister and candidate for president next year.
</P>
<P>
Asked about the accusations, Uribe spokesman Cesar Mauricio Velasquez said "this government has been and is honorable and dignified. As such, it never ordered the illegal monitoring of anyone."
</P>
<P>
The chief prosecutor's office, which is independent of the executive branch, determined that DAS employees working for those arrested compiled dossiers on judges, journalists and human rights workers. The files included family photos, bank statements and personal profiles on details such as the subjects' preferred alcoholic beverages and whether they had mistresses.
</P>
<P>
It based the arrest warrants on documents found at DAS headquarters and the testimony of midlevel agency workers who said they were ordered to do the spying, according to court documents obtained by The Associated Press and interviews with prosecutors.
</P>
<P>
They said the illegal espionage began in 2004 and continued until early this year.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0010" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Myanmar court delays Suu Kyi verdict until Aug. 11
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
YANGON, Myanmar 2009-08-01 00:13:55 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Judges in Myanmar have postponed the verdict in pro-democracy leader Aung San Suu Kyi's trial until Aug. 11 -- a sign, activists say, that the ruling junta is hesitating in the face of outrage abroad and fears of unrest at home.
</P>
<P>
The 64-year-old Nobel Peace laureate is accused of violating the terms of her house arrest when she harbored an American man who swam to her lakeside house and secretly entered the compound. Critics say the military has seized upon the bizarre intrusion as an excuse to keep Suu Kyi jailed through next year's scheduled elections -- the country's first free vote in nearly two decades.
</P>
<P>
But the charges against Suu Kyi -- who has been detained for 14 of the last 20 years and was under house arrest at the time of the incident -- have refocused international outrage on Myanmar.
</P>
<P>
Activists and other supporters of Suu Kyi said it was difficult to determine the reason behind the delay, announced Friday, though the regime may be struggling with how to present the verdict -- which Suu Kyi herself has said is already "painfully obvious" -- to the world.
</P>
<P>
"The postponement may show they are having a difficult time. In other words, this may show they are feeling the heat especially from outside the country," said Soe Aung, a spokesman for Forum for Democracy in Burma, a Thai-based, pro-democracy coalition.
</P>
<P>
Others noted the ruling generals may worry the announcement would set off protests -- and so have pushed it to after the sensitive Aug. 8 anniversary of the failed 1988 uprisings.
</P>
<P>
"The announcement of a guilty verdict will instigate public anger and will be easier for underground activists to organize mass demonstration," said Aung Din, executive director of the U.S. Campaign for Burma.
</P>
<P>
Authorities were clearly anxious ahead of the trial, detaining 10 members of Suu Kyi's opposition party, the National League for Democracy.
</P>
<P>
Thus far, however, neither outside pressure nor the possibility of better economic and political ties with the West has deterred the ruling junta, which appears determined to keep Suu Kyi out of the public eye.
</P>
<P>
Jared Genser, Suu Kyi's international counsel, said the junta may simply be hoping the delay will do just that -- bury the news item in the height of summer.
</P>
<P>
"It is in some ways a smart move -- push off the verdict until the middle of August when numerous government and U.N. officials around the world will be on vacation," Genser said in an e-mail statement.
</P>
<P>
International criticism of the trial has been building since it began May 18, and outrage appeared to peak this month during ASEAN's Regional Forum, when Southeast Asian countries took the unusual step of joining reliable critics like the United States in condemning the regime and calling for Suu Kyi's release. The members of the Association of Southeast Asian Nations generally refrain from criticizing one another.
</P>
<P>
Minutes after the proceedings began Friday, the judges indicated they were not prepared to rule.
</P>
<P>
"Judge Thun Nyunt said the trial is adjourned until Aug. 11 to consider some legal issues concerning the case," defense lawyer Nyan Win told reporters.
</P>
<P>
Verdicts were also postponed for the 53-year-old American, John Yettaw, and two women who lived with Suu Kyi -- Khin Khin Win and her daughter Win Ma Ma. The women face similar charges to Suu Kyi, and Yettaw is accused of abetting in violating the house arrest and faces up to five years in prison.
</P>
<P>
Suu Kyi's party won national elections in 1990, but Myanmar's generals, who have ruled the country since 1962, refused to relinquish power.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0012" type="story" >
<DATELINE>
CARACAS, Venezuela 2009-08-01 00:14:12 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Venezuelan lawmakers approve election law that foes say favors President Hugo Chavez's party.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0013" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Indicted US mayor resigns after 3 weeks on job
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
HOBOKEN, New Jersey 2009-08-01 00:17:10 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The city's mayor resigned Friday just three weeks after taking office, a casualty of a sweeping federal corruption probe that resulted in the arrests of 44 people, including rabbis and dozens of public officials in the New York City area.
</P>
<P>
Mayor Peter Cammarano III, 32, who won a June runoff election to become Hoboken's youngest mayor, is accused of accepting $25,000 in bribes in exchange for help on a purported high-rise building project in the city. He was the second elected official to resign in the wake of the arrests. Later Friday, a Republican state assemblyman also facing corruption charges related to his salary and benefits became the third to step down.
</P>
<P>
Dennis Elwell, the mayor of Secaucus, New Jersey, who was among those arrested in the corruption sweep, resigned earlier this week.
</P>
<P>
"I apologize to the residents of Hoboken for the disruption and disappointment this case has caused," Cammarano, an election-law attorney, said in his resignation letter. He reiterated his innocence and said he still intends to fight the charges.
</P>
<P>
New Jersey, the setting for the television mob drama "The Sopranos" and the 1954 Marlon Brando classic "On the Waterfront," about crookedness on the docks, has long been known for government corruption. But over the last five years, hundreds of government officials from both major parties have been charged with crimes involving betrayal of public trust: taking bribes, getting no-show jobs to boost state pension benefits or lavishly spending public money on themselves.
</P>
<P>
This month's arrests snared 44, including three mayors, two state assemblymen, five rabbis and many other public officials. It also brought fresh attention to Hoboken -- a 1-square-mile (2.59-square-kilometer) city known as Frank Sinatra's hometown, one of America's earliest settlements and more recently a nightlife mecca for the young and hip.
</P>
<P>
Cammarano's arrest comes at a tough time for Hoboken, which sits across the Hudson River from Manhattan and is home to many professionals who work in New York. Financial industry layoffs have hit the New Jersey city hard, flooding the real-estate market with homes for sale or rent.
</P>
<P>
New Jersey Gov. Jon Corzine had praised Cammarano as a rising star in the Democratic Party. But that turned to disgust after Cammarano's arrest and Corzine announced on Thursday that the mayor would resign.
</P>
<P>
Cammarano was replaced by City Council President Dawn Zimmer, who was sworn Friday as the city's first female acting mayor.
</P>
<P>
Assemblyman Daniel Van Pelt announced Friday he was stepping down because his continued service would be "a distraction." He said he was advised not to take reporters' questions.
</P>
<P>
------
</P>
<P>
Beth DeFalco reported from Trenton, New Jersey.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0015" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
US city eyes UN Climate Center at old shipyard
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
SAN FRANCISCO 2009-08-01 00:17:32 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
San Francisco's mayor and the United Nations are eyeing a former naval shipyard contaminated by radiation, heavy metals and other industrial toxins as the future site of a sprawling new green technology complex and climate change think tank.
</P>
<P>
The proposal would turn a section of the Hunters Point Shipyard, one of the most polluted places in the nation according to the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, into a UN "Global Compact Center" meant to help solve the world's pollution dilemmas and foster clean tech business.
</P>
<P>
The city hopes to start construction on the center in 2011 and open its doors in 2012. But the project faces many hurdles before it can be realized, including the completion of a complex environmental cleanup, the approval of the city's Board of Supervisors and finding investors.
</P>
<P>
The U.S. Navy, EPA and state regulators have been working to clean up toxins from the site since the early 1990s and have spent more than $500 million so far. Once finished, the land would be transferred to the city.
</P>
<P>
"Our current schedule is that the land will be ready to transfer to the city of San Francisco in the middle of 2012," said Mark Ripperda, EPA's project manager for the site. "Timelines can always be changed, but that schedule is pretty solid."
</P>
<P>
That makes the city's planned 2012 opening unlikely, but officials said the Navy could allow some construction to start before regulators finish their work.
</P>
<P>
The parcel of land the UN center would occupy would have more than 2 million square feet (190,000 square meters) of commercial space in a campus-like setting, with views across the bay and to downtown San Francisco. The site would feature a conference center, UN office buildings and have an estimated cost of at least $20 million.
</P>
<P>
"California, in general, and San Francisco, in particular, has been at the forefront of environmental sustainability and justice for many years and all of the right ingredients are here," said Gavin Power, deputy director of the UN Global Compact.
</P>
<P>
The shipyard is located next to Candlestick Point, the current home of the San Francisco 49ers NFL football team, who are planning to leave the city for a new stadium being planned down the peninsula, in the city of Santa Clara.
</P>
<P>
On Thursday, the same day Mayor Gavin Newsom mayor announced the proposed UN center, Santa Clara released an environmental impact report for the 49ers' new stadium, moving the team one step closer to leaving.
</P>
<P>
Newsom has been clear in his desire to keep the 49ers in San Francisco, and the timing of his proposal for a new, high-profile tenant at the site made clear the city is planning to move on with or without the team.
</P>
<P>
"If the Niners come, they are perfectly compatible," said Michael Cohen, the mayor's director of economic and work force development. "If not, the 25 acres dedicated to the stadium site can be used for a range of alternative purposes."
</P>
<P>
The UN Center and a future stadium would be key parts of San Francisco's plan to redevelop the Bayview-Hunters Point neighborhoods, a project Cohen called "the most important development project in city history."
</P>
<P>
Voters have approved the redevelopment plan, which is expected to create more than 10,000 new homes, parks and retail space.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0016" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Family believed baby cut from womb was theirs
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
WORCESTER, Massachusetts 2009-08-01 00:18:41 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Little things nagged at Cindy Dion while her son's girlfriend, Julie Corey, was pregnant: One month Corey said she was four months' pregnant -- the next it was eight. Her due date pushed back drastically as it neared. And Corey suddenly refused to let Dion's son, Alex, accompany her to the doctor
</P>
<P>
But Dion put her questions aside when her granddaughter was born last week, and her son couldn't stop smiling. The family even held a cookout to welcome the child, whom he and his girlfriend planned to name Alida Nevaeh.
</P>
<P>
Now, the baby is in state custody and Julie Corey -- Alex Dion's on-and-off girlfriend of two years -- is in jail on $2 million bail, accused Thursday of kidnapping an infant that was cut out of her mother's womb. The mother, Darlene Haynes, was found dead Monday in Worcester. Police have not yet charged anyone in her death.
</P>
<P>
Cindy Dion said Friday it's devastating that she got a chance to hold and love the baby when Haynes never did. She struggles to speak when she considers she might never see the baby she thought was her granddaughter again.
</P>
<P>
"It's killing me. I've got a hole in my heart," Dion said before breaking down and weeping.
</P>
<P>
Dion said Corey was clearly expecting when the family held a shower for her in May. But looking back, Dion said, Corey's behavior during the pregnancy was odd.
</P>
<P>
She told the family she was four months' pregnant in April but said she was eight months' pregnant by the shower a month later. She wouldn't let Alex Dion accompany her on doctor's visits after a test indicated the baby might have developmental problems. The baby was originally due in mid-June, but Corey, 35, told the family she was going to have a cesarean section in late July.
</P>
<P>
Dion said she was set to go the hospital July 24 to be with Corey after the procedure, but Corey called her the night before to say she was about to give birth. Then, Corey called Friday morning to ask her to visit the baby at her home, not a hospital.
</P>
<P>
The blood in the baby's ear and the neck was odd -- she thought hospitals cleaned newborns much better than that.
</P>
<P>
Still, Cindy Dion believed the baby was Corey's until her distraught son called from New Hampshire on Wednesday, the day police arrested Corey. He told her, "The baby's not ours."
</P>
<P>
Dion said her biggest question is what happened to Corey's pregnancy. Did she miscarry? If so, what happened to the child's body? "I want to know where my grandbaby is," she said.
</P>
<P>
Alex Dion couldn't immediately be reached for comment Friday, but he told the Boston Herald he never doubted the child was his. "I thought I had a brand-new daughter," he said.
</P>
<P>
His mother said her 27-year-old son was racked with grief on the ride home from New Hampshire.
</P>
<P>
"He cried so hard he couldn't catch his breath," she said. "I had to climb over the front seat and sit with him. And he hugged me like he was a little kid."
</P>
<P>
Donna Scoville, a neighbor who drove the mother and son back from New Hampshire, said she turned to Alex Dion and said, "I'm sorry." Scoville said his response to her was: "I don't want you to be sorry for me. Be sorry for that baby's mother."
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="APW_ENG_20090801.0017" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Venezuela OKs election law, foes say favors Chavez
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
CARACAS, Venezuela 2009-08-01 00:22:52 UTC
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Venezuelan lawmakers have approved a new election law that opponents say favors President Hugo Chavez's party.
</P>
<P>
The law lets the National Election Council, widely perceived as pro-Chavez, redraw the boundaries of voting districts.
</P>
<P>
It passed Friday in the National Assembly, which is dominated by the president's allies.
</P>
<P>
Opposition politicians fear the council may gerrymander districts to favor Chavez's party in next year's congressional vote.
</P>
<P>
Chavez allies deny the bill is designed to favor the ruling party.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0001" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
CNA daybook for May 31, 2009
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
05/31/09  00:12:59
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Disclaimer:
</P>
<P>
The CNA provides this listing of some of tomorrow's events in Taipei and some
other cities as part of our daily English-language service.
</P>
<P>
Reporters interested in covering the events listed in the Daybook are advised to
contact the organizers for additional information.
</P>
<P>
The CNA is not responsible for any cancellations or last-minute changes made in
the scheduling of these events.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0002" type="multi" >
<HEADLINE>
Today in history
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taipei,  May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  11:03:58
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
Today is Sunday, May 31, or the eighth day of the fifth month of the Year of the
Ox according to the lunar calendar. Following is a list of important events that
have occurred on this date in the past:

1594: Tintoretto, originally Jacopo Robusti, Italian painter of religious,
mythological and historical subjects as well as portraits, dies at the age of
76. His works include "Saint George and the Dragon," "The Last Judgment" and
"The Last Supper."

1859: Big Ben, the clock tower of the House of Parliament in London, goes into
operation.

1923: Rainier III, Prince of Monaco, is born. He married the American actress
Grace Kelly in 1956 and transformed Monaco from a gambling paradise into a
booming international business center.

1924: The Republic of China signs the Peking agreement with the Soviet Union,
recognizing the Soviet government.

1930: Clint Eastwood, American actor and director, is born. He hit the big time
in movies known as spaghetti westerns, such as "The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly"
and "High Plains Drifter," before turning to detective roles in the "Dirty
Harry" series.

1933: The Sino-Japanese Tangku Armistice Agreement is signed, ending hostilities
in Northern China.

1940: U.S. President Franklin D. Roosevelt asks Congress for a US$1.3 billion
defense spending program.

1945: Generalissimo Chiang Kai-shek, who remains as president of the Republic of
China, resigns as premier and is succeeded by Dr. T. V. Soong.

1958: The Soviet Union agrees to talk with the United States on an atmospheric
test ban treaty.

1961: South Africa declares itself a republic independent of the British
Commonwealth.

1970: A strong earthquake rocks northern Peru, killing more than 60,000 people
and injuring at least 200,000 others.

1973: The China Youth Corps elects Lee Huan as its director.

1973: Vice Foreign Minister H. K. Yang leaves on a 45-day tour of Africa as the
special envoy of President Chiang Kai-shek.

1973: The Council for International Economic Cooperation and Development under
the Executive Yuan is reorganized into the Council for Economic Planning and
Development, with Chang Chi-cheng serving as its chairman.

1974: The Republic of China severs diplomatic relations with Malaysia.

1976: The provisional government of East Timor declares the country's merger
with Indonesia.

1976: ROC Economic Affairs Minister Y.S. Sun and Colombian Agriculture Minister
Rafael Pardo Buelvas sign an agreement to strengthen economic and technical
cooperation.

1984: The ruling Kuomintang approves the nomination of Chang Chi-cheng as
governor of the Central Bank of China, Wang Chang-ching as secretary-general of
the Executive Yuan, and Chen Li-an as chairman of the National Science Council.

1989: Jim Wright, speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives, resigns
following investigations by the House Ethics Committee into financial
improprieties, becoming the first speaker in U.S. history to be forced to
resign.

1989: One million students participate in the "Hand in Hand, Heart to Heart"
rally in support of the mainland democracy movement.

1992: The Mainland Affairs Council allows Chinese mainlanders to come to Taiwan
to care for elderly or sick relatives.

1997: The Legislative Yuan passes the third reading of the Public Television
Bill, which enables the nation's public television station to begin broadcasting
in 1998.

1999: ROC Education Minister Lin Chin-jiang says that he has tendered his
resignation so that he can concentrate on undergoing treatment for a brain
tumor.

2000: The Council of Labor Affairs announces that a temporary ban on the
importation of workers from the Philippines will become effective on June 1.

2001: Senior presidential adviser K.T. Li, who is credited as laying the
foundation for Taiwan's econo;mic development in the 1970s and 980s and later
helping foster the island's hi-tech industry, dies at the age of 92.

Confucius' lesson of the day: "Friendship with insincere men, with men of
insinuating manners, and with glib-tongued men: such friendships are injurious."
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0003" type="multi" >
<HEADLINE>
Taiwan headline news
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taipei,  May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  15:20:21
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The lead stories in major Taiwan dailies on Sunday are as follows:

@The China Times:

Cocaine-laced Red Bull Energy Drink confiscated.

@The United Daily News:

Old man stays in NTU Hospital emergency room for 5 days without being diagnosed
as a TB case.

@The Liberty Times:

Cocaine-laced Red Bull Energy Drink has been sold in Taiwan for four years.

@Central Daily News online:

KMT Chairman Wo Po-hsiung conferred with honorary doctorate by Nanjing
University, visits Dr. Sun Yat-sen mausoleum.

@Economic Daily News:

TAIEX poised to rally toward 7,000 as computer expo approaches.

@Commercial Times:

22 stocks seen to lead next round of TAIEX rally.

@The China Post:

Red Bull 'coke' pulled.

@The Taiwan News:

Taiwan, Guatemala agree on cooperation path.

@The Taipei Times:

Thousands of cases of Red Bull seized.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0004" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Taiwan wants to help preserve Guatemalan relics: president
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Guatemala  City,  May 30 (CNA)
05/31/09  16:07:47
(By Huang Juei-hung and Deborah Kuo)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Republic of China President Ma Ying-jeou  told his host,  Guatemalan  President
Alvaro Colom Caballeros, Saturday that Taiwan would like to help Guatemala
conserve its historic relics.
</P>
<P>
"Conserving historic relics or sites is a mammoth engineering task that takes a
long time to complete, " Ma said during a dinner party held in Guatemala City,
adding that the ROC government would like to extend a helping hand if necessary.
</P>
<P>
Ma and his wife Chow Mei-ching hosted the dinner party to thank Colom for his
nation's hospitality during their three-day visit to Guatemala -- one of
Taiwan's 23 diplomatic allies.
</P>
<P>
Earlier in the day, the Taiwan first couple visited the Tikal area, where they
viewed the country's most prominent Mayan ruins, which are a living testimony to
a culture that flourished there between 700 BC and 900 AD.
</P>
<P>
Ma and Colom released a joint statement the previous day reiterating that they
will continue efforts to promote bilateral ties and cooperation in a wide range
of fields.
</P>
<P>
Ma and his 158-member entourage will depart Sunday for El Salvador,  where they
will attend the June 1 inauguration of President-elect Mauricia Funes.
</P>
<P>
El Salvador is the last leg of Ma's 10-day, three-nation diplomatic tour of
Central America that also has taken him to Belize.
</P>
<P>
Ma and his entourage are scheduled to return to Taiwan June 4.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0005" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Bird strike at Taoyuan airport in April caused by eagle: report
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taipei,  May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  16:25:17
(By Han Nai-kuo)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The bird strike incident involving a China Airlines flight at Taiwan Taoyuan
International Airport April 16 was caused by a crested serpent eagle, according
to a report released last week by the Flight Safety Foundation-Taiwan.
</P>
<P>
The report said that an examination of a small amount of flesh and feathers from
what was left of the shredded bird showed that the CAL flight collided with the
medium-large raptor known scientifically as Spilornis cheela, a reptile eater
that hunts over woodland mainly for snakes and lizards.
</P>
<P>
Flight safety experts at the foundation noted that the airport authorities had
launched a drive to eliminate rodents around the airport shortly before the
incident. They said in the report that the eagle was probably attracted by rat
carcasses or slow-moving rodents under the influence of rat poison.
</P>
<P>
A bird strike at the Taoyuan airport caused by a bird of prey of such a large
size is a rare occurrence, as previous incidents involved only small birds, the
report said.
</P>
<P>
The CAL jetliner involved in the strike was taxiing on the runway at the time
and did not suffer serious damage, it added.
</P>
<P>
Bird strikes are a perennial problem for aircraft at Taiwan's 27 airports for
civilian and military aircraft.
</P>
<P>
The Flight Safety Foundation recorded six such incidents in April and May at
airports in Taoyuan, Taipei, Tainan, Chiayi, Gangshan and Hualien -- caused by a
variety of birds, including red turtle doves, barn swallows and large Indian
pratincoles.
</P>
<P>
The air force has lost four expensive jet fighters to bird strikes since 1991,
but there have been not crashes of civilian aircraft attributed to bird strikes.
</P>
<P>
According to statistics compiled by the foundation, there were 841 bird strike
incidents involving military and civilian aircraft in Taiwan between 2002 and
2005, 108 of which resulted in damage and causing 22 planes to abandon their
scheduled takeoffs.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0006" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Medical students protest against academic credentials policy
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taipei, May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  16:59:02
(By Deborah Kuo)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
More than 1,000 students from Taiwan's major medical schools took it to the
streets Sunday to protest a policy they claim favors Taiwanese doctors who have
received medical education abroad.
</P>
<P>
The policy  against  which  they  were  protesting  allows foreign-trained
Taiwanese doctors to practice in Taiwan once they pass a two-stage national
medical exam, which is generally considered not very difficult.
</P>
<P>
Liu Tzu-hung, a senior at National Taiwan University School of Medicine who co-
organized the protest, said they hope foreign-trained medical school graduates
should also have to do internships at local hospitals before being allowed to
sit national medical exams.
</P>
<P>
Liu said these people, some of whom received their medical education in eastern
European countries such as Poland and Romania, may have received diplomas from
abroad, but lack on-the-spot clinical experience in Taiwanese hospitals.
</P>
<P>
"Because they have not done internships and because of their lack of clinical
experience in Taiwanese hospitals, critical conditions and emergencies occur as
a result of their practices, often requiring their locally educated peers to
scramble to correct their errors, " Liu elaborated.
</P>
<P>
The protesters  also demanded  that foreign medical school graduates should have
their academic credentials certified by the Ministry of Education before being
allowed to sit national exams.
</P>
<P>
The protesting students also opposed a "sunset bill" proposal that would exempt
those who are now studying at medical schools in Eastern European countries from
being subject to the new regulations.
</P>
<P>
The students said they want relevant draft amendments to be included on the
agenda of the present legislative session.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0007" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
12th swine flu case confirmed in Taiwan
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taipei,  May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  17:30:35
(By Deborah Kuo)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Central Epidemics Command Center (CECC) confirmed another imported case of
swine flu Sunday, bringing to 12 the number of people infected with the
influenza A(H1N1) virus in the country.
</P>
<P>
"The 12th case is a 33-year-old Taiwanese businessman who flew back to Taiwan
from the United States via Hong Kong May 27, " said CECC spokesman Shih Wen-yi.
</P>
<P>
The man suffered a fever aboard the flight that departed from New York,
according to Shih.
</P>
<P>
"Since the businessman was traveling first class to Hong Kong, no other
passengers came into close contact with him during the flight," Shih said.
</P>
<P>
However, he then boarded another flight from Hong Kong to Taiwan on which he
traveled economy class. A total of 40 people were seated in the three rows in
front of and behind him during that flight, Shih noted.
</P>
<P>
Once back in Taiwan, he went to a movie with his wife and two friends in Taipei
City.
</P>
<P>
As a consequence, a total of 44 people have come into close contact with him
over the past three days, all of whom have been notified and told to closely
monitor their health and contact the CECC if any flu symptoms develop.
</P>
<P>
In order to avoid causing public panic, the CECC decided last week that it will
no longer identify the flights taken by swine flu patients unless there is
evidence to show that the virus was contracted during the flight.
</P>
<P>
Moreover, Shih said that as Taiwan has not reported any more indigenous case for
seven days, the country's swine flu alert was downgraded to the second level
Sunday as previously scheduled.
</P>
<P>
To date, 12 swine flu cases have been confirmed in Taiwan, with no deaths.
</P>
<P>
The CECC raised the level of the country's swine flu alert to the third stage of
yellow May 25 -- which denotes a situation in which imported cases have already
caused a second wave of infections -- after the first case of domestic infection
was confirmed that same day.
</P>
<P>
As of 2 p.m. Friday, 53 countries had officially reported 15,510 cases of
A(H1N1) infection, including 99 deaths, according to the latest World Health
Organization report.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0008" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Couple tie the knot again after six decades of separation
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taipei,  May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  18:47:30
(By Deborah Kuo)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A 92-year-old veteran and his "former" wife tied the knot again Sunday, after
being separated for decades with one in Taiwan and the other in China as a
result of the Chinese civil war more than 60 years ago.
</P>
<P>
Lee Fu-tang, dressed in a trim business suit, arrived in a limousine to marry
Kuan Wen-ying, 85, at his home in Yuanlin township in the central county of
Changhua that morning.
</P>
<P>
A wedding ceremony was held at the courtyard of Lee's home, where the couple has
lived since 2007 after Kuan came to Taiwan from their hometown in China's
northern province of Shandong, followed by a wedding banquet, also held in the
courtyard.
</P>
<P>
The wedding was organized with the assistance of the Taichung City-based Hondao
Senior Citizen's Welfare Foundation.
</P>
<P>
The foundation decided to help organize the wedding after hearing of Lee's long-
held hope of being able to remarry his wife in a "more formal wedding ceremony."
</P>
<P>
Lee said that he and Kuan used to play together as children when they were
neighbors back in Shandong. They were later wed through a marriage arranged by
their parents, but only over a table at a small restaurant with just their
parents attending.
</P>
<P>
Lee said he left home three years later to join the Nationalist army and fight
against Japanese invading troops and the emerging Chinese communists. Their son
was also born at around that time, he went on, adding that he did not see Kuan
and their only son again until 1993, when he got in contact with them and they
began exchanging photos.
</P>
<P>
He traveled to Shandong to bring Kuan to Taiwan to live with him in 2007 --
after nearly 60 years of separation across the strait, during which they both
remarried and had families of their own. Both Lee's Taiwanese wife and Kuan's
Chinese husband had died by the time Lee made the trip to Shandong.
</P>
<P>
Lee kissed a shy Kuan on the cheek during the wedding ceremony, in which the
couple vowed to keep each other company for the rest of their lives.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0009" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
NT$20 surcharge on cigarettes from June 1: DOH
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taipei,  May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  18:55:49
(By Han Nai-kuo)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The health and welfare surcharge on tobacco products will be increased from the
present NT$10 per pack to NT$20 per pack from June 1, a senior health official
said Sunday.
</P>
<P>
Chao Kun-yu, director of the Bureau of Health Promotion under the Cabinet-level
Department of Health (DOH), said retail stores are allowed to sell off their
existing cigarette stocks without asking their customers to pay the extra NT$10
surcharge.
</P>
<P>
He urged consumers to examine the cigarettes they buy to make sure the pack
carries a sticker certifying the imposition of a NT$20 health and welfare
surcharge.
</P>
<P>
The 100 percent surcharge increase will raise the average per-pack price for
cigarettes to between NT$55 and NT$70 (US$2.15) per pack, depending on the
brand.
</P>
<P>
According to an estimate by Chao, the new measure is expected to boost annual
revenues from the health and welfare surcharge from NT$20 billion to between
NT$32 billion and NT$36 billion.
</P>
<P>
In accordance with the Tobacco Hazards Prevention Act and the regulations
governing the distribution of the tobacco health and welfare surcharge, the DOH
will use 4 percent, or NT$1.39 billion, of the revenues from the surcharge as
subsidies to help 470,000 less privileged people obtain national health
insurance, Chao said.
</P>
<P>
The Bureau of National Health Insurance will receive 70 percent of the surcharge
revenues and will spend NT$10 billion to meet its financial shortfall and the
rest in various areas, including 6 percent for cancer prevention, 5 percent on
raising the standards of medical services, 3 percent in areas lacking medical
resources, another 3 percent on tobacco hazards prevention and 2 percent on
treatment of rare diseases.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0010" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
`Reading replacing smoking' drive launched on World No Tobacco Day
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taipei,  May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  20:02:48
(By Sofia Wu)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Nantou county government in central Taiwan launched a new publicity campaign
Sunday to encourage smokers to replace smoking with reading as part of the
observance of the May 31 World No Tobacco Day.
</P>
<P>
Magistrate Lee Chao-ching and Nantou County Council Speaker Wu Chi-hsiang
stubbed out a giant-size burning cigarette in a ceremony held on the county
government plaza to signify their determination to prevent the hazards caused by
tobacco and promote a smoke-free society.
</P>
<P>
Noting that the drugs and chemicals found in cigarettes are detrimental to
health, Lee said he looks forward to seeing local smokers quit as soon as
possible for the sake of public health.
</P>
<P>
"Smoking not only threatens the health of the smoker but also harms non-smokers
through second-hand smoke," Lee said.
</P>
<P>
He urged smokers to take up reading as a replacement for their smoking habits,
saying that reading benefits both physical and mental health and contributes to
national development in the long run.
</P>
<P>
Similar ceremonies were also held in the county's 13 major townships and
villages to inspire local smokers.
</P>
<P>
As of Friday, 101 infractions had been reported throughout the county since the
newly revised Tobacco Hazards Prevention Act came into effect in January that
bars smoking in indoor public areas and workplaces, a local public health
official said.
</P>
<P>
Among the violators, 65 cases involved students younger than 18, the official
said.
</P>
<P>
He further said that anti-smoking patrols will be intensified at the county's
major scenic spots and recreational areas, as the county government frequently
receives complaints about illegal smoking in such areas.
</P>
<P>
With beautiful mountain scenery, Nantou -- the only land-locked county in Taiwan
-- has long played a significant role in Taiwan's tourism industry.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0011" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Chinese deckhand on Taiwanese fishing boat bitten by shark
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taitung County,  May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  20:39:06
(By Han Nai-kuo)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A Chinese deckhand on a Taiwanese fishing boat suffered serious shark bite
injuries aboard the boat Sunday while trying to move the seemingly unconscious
fish to a freezer.
</P>
<P>
Officials from the Coast Guard Administration's 15th flotilla said they received
a radio request for help from the skipper of the Chin Sheng Fa 13 to help Zhang
Sanqian, 46, a native from Fujian province who was bleeding profusely because of
the shark bites.
</P>
<P>
Zhang was given first aid treatment by health workers at a clinic on Green
Island to stop bleeding before a helicopter from the National Airborne Services
Corps lifted him to the Taitung branch of Macay Memorial Hospital in
southeastern Taiwan for further treatment.
</P>
<P>
CGA officials quoted other crew members of Chin Sheng Fa 13 as saying that the
crew caught the 80-kilogram shark in waters near Green Island during an
operation to catch hake.
</P>
<P>
After Zhang and five other deckhands pulled the shark onto the deck, they had
the fish electrocuted. As Zhang tried to pull the seemingly unconscious shark
toward the freezer, it suddenly attacked him twice with its razor-sharp teeth,
wounding his knee and tearing off large chunks of flesh from the back of his
left lower leg.
</P>
<P>
Doctors at Macay Hospital said that Zhang needed 54 stitches to close the
wounds, and that he was "out of danger" by noon. However, the doctors decided
that Zhang should remain in an intensive care unit for a few days to prevent
wound infection.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="CNA_ENG_20090601.0012" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Chinese trade delegation arrives for procurement mission
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
Taipei,  May 31 (CNA)
05/31/09  21:43:02
(By Sofia Wu)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A 77-member trade delegation from China arrived in Taipei Sunday to procure a
variety of products ranging from high-tech devices to traditional craftworks.
</P>
<P>
The delegation,  headed by Li Shuilin,  president  of the Association for Trade
and Economic Exchange Across the Taiwan Straits (ATEEATS) , is composed of
senior executives of five major Chinese export-import  trade  associations  and
six  leading  industry associations.
</P>
<P>
Among the members are also top management officers from more than 40 flagship
companies in China, including Haier Group and Hasee Computer Co. Most of them
have won bids to provide products under China's "home appliances to the
countryside" project as part of its massive economic stimulus package.
</P>
<P>
Noting that Taiwan is the ATEEATS' main engagement target, Li said many of
Taiwan-produced goods are badly needed in China. Therefore, he added, his
association plans to send more procurement missions to Taiwan later this year.
</P>
<P>
The cross-strait trade and economic exchange association is set up by China's
Ministry of Commerce to handle cross-strait trade deals and promote commercial
exchanges.
</P>
<P>
Chao Yung-chuan, secretary-general of the Taiwan External Trade Development
Council (TAITRA) who greeted the Chinese delegation at Taiwan Taoyuan
International Airport, said the group will procure electric home appliances,
information technology (IT) products, chemicals, craftworks, textiles,
foodstuffs and many other items.
</P>
<P>
TAITRA will organize a presentation at the Taipei International Convention
Center Monday for Chinese buyers to meet their potential Taiwanese suppliers,
Chao said, adding that the council will help local manufacturers to grasp
business opportunities generated by China's "home appliances going to the
countryside" project.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0001" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Freedom on the Defensive
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The following editorial appeared in Sunday's Washington Post:
</P>
<P>
"The peoples of the Americas have a right to democracy and their
governments have an obligation to promote and defend it." So reads the first
sentence of the Inter-American Democratic Charter, which was adopted on
Sept. 11, 2001, by the Organization of American States and signed by all 34
active member countries. Founded in 1948, the OAS defines its two top
purposes as "to strengthen peace and security on the continent" and "to
promote and consolidate representative democracy." So with the
organization's annual assembly set to open Tuesday in Honduras, you'd think
a principal item of business would be the rapidly deteriorating political
situation in Venezuela, where would-be strongman Hugo Chavez has ordered up
criminal investigations against most of his leading opponents -- jailing one
and driving another into exile -- and is threatening to shut down the last
opposition broadcast television network.
</P>
<P>
Not a chance. Far from facing the sanctions that the democratic charter
authorizes, Chavez will be helping to lead a charge aimed at lifting the
1962 suspension of Cuba's OAS membership -- a campaign that enjoys the
support of almost every government in the region. No, Cuba doesn't come
close to meeting the requirements of the democratic charter -- in fact, its
totalitarian domestic regime has remained essentially unaltered during the
last 47 years. Nor do Raul and Fidel Castro wish to rejoin the OAS; like
Chavez, the Castros would prefer to form a new regional organization that
excludes the United States.
</P>
<P>
Nonetheless, Latin American governments from Mexico to Argentina have
chosen to make Cuba's readmission the centerpiece of this year's assembly.
It's a cheap and popular way to please leftist constituencies at home -- and
to pressure the Obama administration, which has unilaterally lifted several
sanctions against Cuba but not what remains of the economic embargo. Sadly,
even democratic governments such as Brazil and Chile are unwilling to stand
by the pledge they made just eight years ago -- they, too, are clamoring to
restore Cuba's membership while remaining silent about Venezuela.
</P>
<P>
Obama has proclaimed his wish to set U.S.-Latin relations on a new
footing; he shook Chavez's hand at a recent hemispheric summit and has
refrained from criticizing the crackdown in Venezuela. That seems to have
emboldened leftist leaders to press their own agenda at the OAS. The
administration has been trying to finesse the issue: Last week it proposed
that the suspension be lifted but that Cuba's reinstatement be linked to
steps toward democracy. When that proposal failed to gain traction, U.S.
diplomats joined a working group trying to hammer out a compromise. But most
likely the administration is fighting an unwinnable battle. By signaling
that it cares more about "partnership" with Latin American governments than
defending democracy and human rights, it has allowed support for those
principles to crumble at the very institution founded to defend
them.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0002" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Textbook for Failure
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The following editorial appeared in Sunday's Washington Post:
</P>
<P>
Whether New York York Mayor Michael Bloomberg will retain control of
the city's public schools will soon be decided by state lawmakers in Albany.
This is an issue about which there should be no debate. By any measure, the
city's schools are better off today than under the byzantine system that
preceded mayoral control. Too much is at stake -- for New York's 1.1 million
students as well as for education reform efforts nationwide -- for the
legislature to turn back the clock. If the vested interests of the education
establishment succeed in their bid to kill off mayoral control in the
nation's largest school system, it will make it harder for other cities to
sustain the oversight of schools by mayors. Places such as Washington, D.C.,
are likely to become the next targets.
</P>
<P>
The 2002 law that gave Bloomberg direct authority over the schools,
replacing a system of local control overseen by a central Board of
Education, expires at the end of June. Lawmakers must decide if mayoral
control should be maintained, abolished or modified; the lobbying is
ferocious. Critics -- including the United Federation of Teachers -- want to
curb the mayor's influence, saying that he and Chancellor Joel Klein have
ruled like dictators. Among the suggested changes, presented under the
specious guise of "checks and balances," are proposals for reconfiguring the
education panel that replaced the old school board so that it would be able
to overrule the mayor and giving broad new powers to local community
councils. So much for accountability and responsibility; apparently the fact
that Bloomberg was overwhelmingly returned to office in 2005 after staking
his political future on running the schools isn't enough.
</P>
<P>
It's important to recall the grim reality prior to mayoral control:
struggling and unsafe schools, failing students, inequities in funding,
corrupt politics and patronage. Bloomberg and Klein instituted such reforms
as ending social promotion and standardizing curriculum. They closed
chronically low-performing schools and innovated with new and charter
schools. No less an authority than U.S. Education Secretary Arne Duncan
hailed the undisputed progress of these seven years. "I'm looking at the
data here in front of me," Duncan told the New York Post. "Graduation rates
are up. Test scores are up. Teacher salaries are up . ..." Indeed, test
scores announced this month showed 68.9 percent of students in fourth grade
and 57 percent of students in eighth grade met or exceeded grade-level
readings standards, up from 46.5 percent and 29.5 percent, respectively, in
2002.
</P>
<P>
Why sacrifice progress and momentum when there are so many students yet
to be helped? One answer is in the clear dislike by teachers union officials
of the hard-charging Klein, who, much like his D.C. counterpart, Michelle
Rhee, is absolutely fearless in putting the interests of children ahead of
job protection, seniority or being liked by city pols. Unions talk a good
game about wanting to be change agents, but here, when real reform is on the
table, they opt for sabotage. Easier to criticize a style of governing than
the benefits of real leadership. Easier to look out for your own
institutional interests than what's good for pupils.
</P>
<P>
A lot is riding on the outcome in New York; Washington, where the same
union leaders have inserted themselves into the fight over education, should
pay particular attention.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0003" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Difficult Decisions Over What Not to Disclose
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In the 1952 movie classic "Deadline-U.S.A.," a crusading editor played
by Humphrey Bogart is on the phone with a gangster who warns him: "Print
that story, and you're a dead man."
</P>
<P>
A defiant Bogart, holding the receiver so the presses can be heard in
the background, tells the bad guy: "That's the press, baby. The press. And
there's nothing you can do about it. Nothing!" For many, that's the enduring
perception of those of us in the press. Plead all you want, but we're going
to give readers the news, and there's nothing you can do about
it.
</P>
<P>
In truth, sometimes you can do something.
</P>
<P>
Post readers -- from presidents to peons -- routinely make appeals for
information to be withheld. Most are denied. But a few are granted.
</P>
<P>
If you want to block publication of the sale price of your home or a
DUI arrest, forget it. Those are public records. But if there's a threat to
personal safety, you've got a chance.
</P>
<P>
Virginia Editor Mike Semel recalls a case in which federal authorities
expressed fear that a planned Post story would elevate death threats against
a law enforcement figure. The story ran, but only after it was edited with a
special sensitivity to language that might heighten the threats.
</P>
<P>
On other occasions, The Post has agreed to delay publication of stories
that might jeopardize a criminal investigation.
</P>
<P>
The names of witnesses to crimes have been withheld after The Post
agreed that disclosure would endanger their lives. Likewise, The Post
deleted the name of a purchaser from its weekly home sales listings after
she expressed fear that it might be noticed by a man who was stalking
her.
</P>
<P>
When fancy homes are featured in photo spreads, editors routinely mask
the precise location -- often without being asked -- so burglars won't have a
road map. Post policy is to print a street address only when it's essential
to the story.
</P>
<P>
But obituaries editor Adam Bernstein denies requests from relatives of
the deceased who don't want references to previous marriages or the cause of
death. Likewise, The Post's Web site denies requests to delete archival
stories of those whose convictions have been expunged by a court.
</P>
<P>
But The Post has on occasion agreed to help those who faced criminal
charges that were later dropped. The Web site has been willing to "redirect"
search rankings so that the first archived story to appear will include the
dismissal, not the arrest.
</P>
<P>
The stakes are high when the government asks The Post not to publish
material that it thinks will harm national security.
</P>
<P>
Longtime executive editor Leonard Downie Jr. said The Post agreed a
"very few" times to scrap entire stories during his quarter century as a top
editor at the paper. Last fall he handed the reins to Marcus Brauchli, who
said he has not received a government request to withhold national security
information. "We killed a story of mine after CIA officials made their
case," said national security reporter Dana Priest. "It was a very easy
decision once we understood their rationale."
</P>
<P>
In 2005, the Bush administration sought to limit disclosures in another
Priest story revealing secret CIA interrogation sites in Eastern Europe.
Before publication, Downie was summoned to the White House, where the
president, Vice President Dick Cheney and Director of National Intelligence
John Negroponte made their case.
</P>
<P>
The story, which won a Pulitzer Prize, was published. But it noted that
The Post had agreed not to identify the countries participating in the
covert program because "senior U.S. officials" had "argued that the
disclosure might disrupt counterterrorism efforts in those countries and
elsewhere and could make them targets of possible terrorist retaliation."
</P>
<P>
Government leaders often assert that disclosures would damage national
security.
</P>
<P>
But University of Chicago legal scholar Geoffrey Stone, an authority on
the subject, said, "There is no clear example of any instance in which the
press has published classified information where the publication has caused
direct, immediate and grave harm to the United States."
</P>
<P>
Downie said his meetings with top-level officials about sensitive
national security information were civil and rarely "melodramatic."
</P>
<P>
"We always listened carefully" to the appeals, he said, "but that
doesn't mean we agreed all the time."
</P>
<P>
"We take these decisions very seriously. We lose sleep over them," he
said, adding that the decision on whether to publish is seldom
clear-cut.
</P>
<P>
"These are not 90-10 decisions," he said. "Sometimes, they're
51-49."
</P>
<P>
Alexander is ombudsman for The Washington Post.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0004" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Russia's Iconic Nesting Dolls on Endangered Industry List
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Inna Kashnikova found her calling during a fourth-grade trip to a
factory in this picturesque town that produces matryoshki, the wooden
nesting dolls that are synonymous with Russian folk art.
</P>
<P>
"I really liked it here, with the smell of the paint and all the
colors," recalled Kashnikova, 40, as she sat at a workbench in the Aofis
factory and used a cotton swab to dab white flowers across the apron of an
unfinished matryoshka. "Ever since then, I wanted to paint the
dolls."
</P>
<P>
But matryoshki -- those gourd-shaped figures that can be pulled apart to
reveal ever-smaller dolls -- are in trouble, and so is Kashnikova's
job.
</P>
<P>
Here in Sergiyev Posad, a historic town 50 miles north of Moscow that
is considered the birthplace of the matryoshka, factories that have produced
the dolls for decades are struggling to stay in business. Souvenir shops
have slashed orders, tourists have stopped coming, and artisans such as
Kashnikova are worried that their way of life -- and a distinctly Russian
tradition -- may soon be lost.
</P>
<P>
With the country enduring its worst economic downturn in a decade,
matryoshka manufacturers are pleading with the government for aid, and
warning that their survival could depend on it because sales have already
fallen by at least a third.
</P>
<P>
The Kremlin has agreed to add the matryoshka to its bailout budget,
pledging to buy nearly $30 million worth of the dolls and other souvenirs
for officials to give away as gifts. Sales of the dolls account for less
than 1 percent of the country's $1.2 billion souvenir industry, but
officials say more is at stake than money and jobs.
</P>
<P>
"The matryoshka is our face" to the world, said Galina Subbota, a
deputy mayor of Sergiyev Posad, where the government commissioned a hot-air
balloon shaped like the doll to promote tourism. "Even if it is not
economically profitable, we can't allow it to disappear from our
lives."
</P>
<P>
The first matryoshka is said to have been made here in the 1890s, after
a local craftsman saw a set of Japanese stacking dolls in the likeness of a
Buddhist deity and created a Russian version in the form of a matronly
peasant woman. Today, tourists can buy dolls painted to represent anything
from "Simpsons" characters to communist leaders and American
presidents.
</P>
<P>
Built around a 14th-century monastery, Sergiyev Posad remains an
important source of matryoshki, and a century-old toy museum here displays
dolls from each of the past 10 decades. But the lime tree that
matryoshka-makers favor for its soft wood has all but disappeared from the
region. Production has shifted to the Volga River outside Nizhny Novgorod,
where artisans make the dolls extra curvy, with bright red peasant dresses
and yellow scarves.
</P>
<P>
Most matryoshki are made in small factories or workshops by artisans
who craft them one at a time and often have spent years training on the
lathe. Painting the dolls is easier, and during the economic turmoil after
the fall of the Soviet Union, laid-off state employees across the country
earned a living by doing it in their homes.
</P>
<P>
"In the 1990s, the matryoshka helped people to survive," Subbota said.
"There wasn't a house in Sergiyev Posad where you couldn't find someone
painting a matryoshka."
</P>
<P>
A beloved children's toy in the Soviet era, when the state economy
provided consumers with few choices, the matryoshka became less popular in
Russia after the economy opened up.
</P>
<P>
"It's difficult to compete with the Chinese and these plastic toys,"
complained Aleksander Kurennoy, director of the Aofis factory, which has
been making matryoshki since 1947 but relies largely on visits from tourists
for income.
</P>
<P>
Now, some say the financial crisis could be the final blow to the
industry.
</P>
<P>
Alexei Polikarpov, director of the Dyuna Nesting Doll Co., said he used
to sell about $35,000 worth of dolls a month to shops in Russia and abroad
but hasn't received an order since November. The company, located outside
Nizhny Novgorod, has been late paying suppliers and employees, he said. It
has begun making other wooden toys in an attempt to stay in business. "I'm
sure this will help us live through the crisis," Polikarpov said.
</P>
<P>
Others say they will need the government's help to survive. In March,
Russia's largest matryoshka-maker, Khokhloma Painting, met with officials in
Moscow to plead for tax breaks and subsidies. Representatives of the
crystal, lace and porcelain industries also sought help.
</P>
<P>
The businessmen said that their warehouses were overflowing, that they
were unable to repay bank loans, and that the souvenir industry was in
critical condition, state media reported. Two days later, the government
announced that next year it would buy $28.4 million in nesting dolls,
painted wooden spoons and lacquer boxes.
</P>
<P>
Matryoshka manufacturers expressed skepticism about whether the
government would follow through and said they would prefer that the Kremlin
cut taxes on exports and make it easier to obtain existing subsidies.
</P>
<P>
"For 12 years, I've heard the government talking about support for folk
crafts," said Oleg Korotkov, director of Semyonovskaya Painting, a
matryoshka-maker whose sales have fallen more than 90 percent.
"Unfortunately, there's never any real help."
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0005" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Same-Sex Marriage Ruling Invokes Oddities of Constitution
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Whereas the U.S. Constitution has been amended only 27 times,
California's top legal document has been altered more than 500 times, often
by voter initiative. The state's Constitution is the third longest in the
world, exceeded only by those of India and Alabama.
</P>
<P>
Inscribed within its venerable pages are a ban on gill net fishing, a
statement that English is the state's official language and an assortment of
requirements involving liquor and criminal defendants.
</P>
<P>
Californians can amend their Constitution more easily than voters in
most other states, and without calling for tighter restrictions, California
Chief Justice Ronald M. George observed in Tuesday's ruling that they were
possible and maybe even proper.
</P>
<P>
As in other states  that allow initiatives, California's ballot measures
sometimes have been used to take away rights from minorities.
</P>
<P>
"We have seen a whole bunch of law review articles saying that in
general the initiative process has been used more against minority groups
than to help them," said Jon W. Davidson, legal director of the gay-rights
group Lambda Legal.
</P>
<P>
California ballots have carried initiatives to ban gays and lesbians
from teaching and quarantine people with HIV -- both rejected -- and to
permit race discrimination in housing, require English literacy and repeal
affirmative action, which passed. The state Supreme Court later overturned
the housing law on federal constitutional grounds.
</P>
<P>
In upholding Proposition 8, George disputed the challengers' contention
that the measure was unprecedented in taking away a fundamental right from a
minority.
</P>
<P>
He cited a voter-approved 1894 amendment that withdrew the right to vote
from anyone not literate "in the English language." The provision remained
in effect until 1970, when the state Supreme Court struck it down as a
violation of the federal Constitution.
</P>
<P>
"People don't understand that the people of California can change their
Constitution," Justice Kathryn Mickle Werdegar said in an interview. The
Proposition 8 case "was about procedure," she said.
</P>
<P>
Despite the anger over Proposition 8 by gay rights activists, voters are
unlikely to restrict their power to tinker with the state's most important
legal document, experts said, which could be accomplished by voter
initiative.
</P>
<P>
At least five commissions have been formed during the last 20 years to
look at the initiative process, and not one measure to change it has made it
to the ballot, said Fred Silva, senior fiscal policy adviser at California
Forward, a nonpartisan, nonprofit group  concerned with fiscal reform and
state governance.
</P>
<P>
"There are people on both sides who don't want anything done -- both
liberals and conservatives," said Bob Stern, president of the Los
Angeles-based Center for Governmental Studies.
</P>
<P>
Still, the state budget fiasco has made constitutional reform a more
pressing issue, and even if voters refuse to change the initiative process,
Stern believes, "The public is ready for an examination of the
Constitution."
</P>
<P>
An initiative expected to qualify for next year's ballot would authorize
a constitutional convention, where delegates could take a red pencil to the
state's massive tome.
</P>
<P>
Stern cited a daylong conference on constitutional reform held in
Sacramento, the state capital, in February. Attendees paid $89, he said.
More than 400 people showed up and some had to be turned away.
</P>
<P>
"I was stunned," he said.
</P>
<P>
When voters amend the Constitution, the state Supreme Court  can
overturn the amendment only if it decides it was a "revision," which is a
more sweeping alteration that must be put on the ballot by a constitutional
convention or two-thirds vote of the Legislature, or because it violated the
federal Constitution.
</P>
<P>
The court concluded that Proposition 8 was not an impermissible revision
because it did not alter the governmental plan or framework.
</P>
<P>
But given the court's historic May 15, 2008, ruling affirming the right
of gays and lesbians to wed, the court might well have found the measure
violated federal constitutional equal protection guarantees.
</P>
<P>
Anti-Proposition 8 lawyers did not pursue that argument, however,
fearing that a reversal in the U.S. Supreme Court would set the marriage
movement back decades.
</P>
<P>
Same-sex marriage activists looked askance when two high-profile
lawyers, Theodore Olson and David Boies, announced Wednesday they are
challenging Proposition 8 in federal court. For the U.S. Supreme Court to
rule in favor of a federal constitutional right to marry, it would have to
reject the views of 44 states, 30 of which have constitutional amendments
banning gay and lesbian nuptials, Davidson said.
</P>
<P>
Olson and Boies "believe they know a lot about the Supreme Court, but
the reality is they have never done any lesbian and gay rights litigation
nor even really any civil rights litigation from the plaintiffs' side,"
Davidson said.
</P>
<P>
Civil rights groups have tended to choose litigation carefully, starting
with issues they think they can win to establish building blocks for matters
of more consequence later on. The National Association for the Advancement
of Colored People first attacked school segregation with a case against law
schools, Davidson noted. They have tried to avoid cases that could set an
unfavorable precedent.
</P>
<P>
For now, most activists would prefer to overturn Proposition 8 at the
ballot box in 2010 -- a repeal measure could appear alongside the initiative
to hold a constitutional convention.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0006" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Group Pushes Census Boycott by Illegal Immigrants
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Washington-based National Coalition of Latino Clergy &amp; Christian
Leaders, which says it represents 20,000 Hispanic churches in 34 states,
recently announced that a quarter of its 4 million members were prepared to
join the boycott as a way to intensify pressure for legalization and to
protect themselves from government scrutiny.
</P>
<P>
"Before being counted, we need to be legalized," said the Rev. Miguel
Rivera, the coalition's chairman and founder.
</P>
<P>
But the boycott call has infuriated many Hispanic organizations. La
Opinion, in a recent editorial, denounced it as a "dangerous mistake" that
"verges on political suicide," and an official with the National Association
of Latino Elected and Appointed Officials called it "wildly irresponsible."
</P>
<P>
"This is a phenomenal step backward in the strides we have made to make
sure we are equal," said Arturo Vargas, executive director of the Hispanic
officials group.
</P>
<P>
The decennial Census, which counts all people regardless of immigration
status, is used to allocate federal funds for education, housing, health
care, transportation and other local needs. By some estimates, every person
counted results in $1,000 in federal funds.
</P>
<P>
The Census is also used to apportion the 435 seats in the U.S. House of
Representatives, which are based on a state's population.
</P>
<P>
According to a study in 2003, California's sizable illegal immigrant
population allowed it to gain three House seats it might otherwise not have
received. The illegal immigrant population also caused Indiana, Michigan and
Mississippi to each lose one of their seats and prevented Montana from
gaining a seat.
</P>
<P>
The study by the Center for Immigration Studies, a Washington,
D.C.-based research group that promotes immigration restrictions, also
argued that the illegal immigrant population skewed the "one man, one vote"
principle in elections. In 2002, the study found, it took almost 100,000
votes to win the typical congressional race in the four states that lost or
failed to gain a seat, compared with 35,000 votes to win in immigrant-rich
districts in California.
</P>
<P>
Back in 1988, the effect on apportionment, which also affects the
Electoral College, prompted a lawsuit by 40 members of Congress,
Pennsylvania and the Federation for American Immigration Reform to prevent
the Census Bureau from counting illegal immigrants. The complaint was
dismissed by the U.S. Supreme Court for lack of standing.
</P>
<P>
"People who have no right to be in this country should not be counted,"
said federation President Dan Stein. "It's awfully hard to explain to U.S.
citizens why they keep losing political representation to states like
California because of people who broke immigration laws."
</P>
<P>
Vargas and others questioned the boycott organizers' political
motivations, noting that most of them were conservative.
</P>
<P>
Rivera acknowledged that his coalition endorsed George W. Bush for
president in 2004 and slightly favored Republican presidential nominee John
McCain over Democrat Barack Obama by a vote of 52 percent to 48 percent last
year. But he denied that the boycott was aimed at aiding Republicans.
</P>
<P>
He said his group was concerned that federal funds obtained in part
through the counting of illegal immigrants would be used against them to
increase arrests and harassment by local law enforcement.
</P>
<P>
Rivera also said he wanted to use the boycott as a way to pressure
Congress to pass legislation offering legalization to illegal
immigrants.
</P>
<P>
So far, his group appears to have made little traction in California. A
group of affiliated Hispanic pastors plans to meet soon to discuss the
boycott idea, according to Jose Caballero, a Camarillo, Calif.,
minister.
</P>
<P>
But other Hispanic leaders say they are nervous about the
boycott.
</P>
<P>
"The fact that they are getting a lot of media attention concerns us
that they could do a lot of damage," said Brent Wilkes, executive director
of the League of United Latin American Citizens in Washington,
D.C.
</P>
<P>
Using the same slogan as their successful citizenship campaigns -- "Ya
es Hora," or "It's Time" -- Spanish-language media, community groups, labor
unions and churches plan to launch a far-reaching campaign urging mass
participation in the Census.
</P>
<P>
(Optional add end)
</P>
<P>
Boycott or not, they have their work cut out for them. Although the
Census Bureau by law must keep the information confidential, that message
has not entirely gotten through.
</P>
<P>
At Our Lady Queen of Angels Roman Catholic Church in Los Angeles,
migrant farm worker Juan Garcia said he would not participate because of
fears about how the information might be used.
</P>
<P>
Another illegal immigrant, Julian Chavez, also voiced concern that
census workers would contact him at work, go to his home and ask nosy
questions. Asked if he would participate, Chavez hedged his answer.
</P>
<P>
"Will there be consequences?" he asked. "I have my family to think
about."
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0007" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Iranian Campaign Veers Into Previously Off-Limit Topics
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
With campaigns in full swing ahead of the June 12 vote, none of the
three major challengers has shied away from publicly criticizing Ahmadinejad
on topics long considered off-limits for debate in Iran, such as his stance
on the country's nuclear program and his vitriol about Israel.
</P>
<P>
Reformist challenger Mir-Hossein Mousavi accused the president of so
sullying the nation that Iranian passports are now on par with those of
Somalia, the African state that has become a hub of poverty, piracy and
terrorism.
</P>
<P>
"Our people have not given you the right to disgrace them," he told
supporters during a campaign stop in the city of Isfahan.
</P>
<P>
Mehdi Karroubi, another liberal challenger, took on the president's
handling of the nuclear program, which the West believes is meant to
eventually produce weapons, saying Iran needs to be more transparent and
rational in pursuing its goals abroad. "We have to deal with the world
differently," he said in a television appearance.
</P>
<P>
And even conservative presidential contender Mohsen Rezai, a former
commander of the Revolutionary Guard, slammed Ahmadinejad for going
overboard with his rhetoric on the Arab-Israeli conflict. Iran strongly
opposes the Jewish state and supports the Palestinian cause through militant
allies such as Hamas and Islamic Jihad.
</P>
<P>
"When we say we are revolutionary, it does not mean that we are seeking
adventures," he said in a television interview Wednesday. "It means we have
wisdom and discretion."
</P>
<P>
The criticism is startling given the call last month by the country's
highest political and spiritual authority, Ayatollah Ali Khamenei, for a
hard-line stance that many saw as an implicit endorsement of the shape and
tenor of Ahmadinejad's foreign policy.
</P>
<P>
"The supreme leader endorses all elected governments, but that does not
imply that he dictates foreign policy," said Mojtaba Bigdeli, a political
analyst close to Ahmadinejad.
</P>
<P>
Ahmadinejad has responded to the criticism by accusing his rivals of
serving the interests of the West.
</P>
<P>
"Certain people bring up tomatoes as the country's leading issue at a
time when the enemy is trying to spread the idea that sanctions have been
effective in crippling Iran's economy," he said recently.
</P>
<P>
Iran's political system combines elements of a democratic republic with
a structure dominated by Khamenei, who sets the parameters of the country's
policies.
</P>
<P>
The president has limited but palpable leeway on foreign affairs.
Mohammad Khatami, Ahmadinejad's predecessor, charmed the world by calling
for a "Dialogue of Civilizations" to overcome tensions between Islam and the
West. Ahmadinejad outraged the international community by convening a
conference of those who doubt that the Holocaust took place.
</P>
<P>
"The constitution says that Iran should have good relations with Islamic
countries and support the Palestinian cause, but the details and methods are
not stipulated," said Ali Kadkhodazadeh, a Middle East analyst at Hamshahri,
a daily newspaper that is the mouthpiece of Tehran's mayor, a rival of
Ahmadinejad.
</P>
<P>
"The constitution does not say Iran should host a Holocaust-denial
conference," he said. "If the president is changed, the methods will change,
not the outlines and pillars of foreign policies."
</P>
<P>
Analysts say Ahmadinejad's opponents are tapping into deep-seated
feelings of Iranian national pride to recast his policies on the nuclear
issue and relations with the U.S., and even on the Arab-Israeli conflict, as
out of sync with the country's values and interests.
</P>
<P>
In the process, they are publicly leveling condemnations that would be
highly sensitive if voiced by, say, a dissident or a reformist
newspaper.
</P>
<P>
For example, Esmail Gerami-Moqaddam, a spokesman for Karroubi's
campaign, told reporters recently that Ahmadinejad had naively dismissed
U.N. Security Council resolutions imposing sanctions as "trash papers" while
they were hurting ordinary people.
</P>
<P>
Authorities for months strongly discouraged newspapers from mentioning
or examining how international sanctions affect Iranians.
</P>
<P>
The Karroubi camp also has snidely urged the president to focus on
"stabilizing the price of tomatoes" rather than managing world
affairs.
</P>
<P>
To his critics, the president has created the opening by running a
campaign that stresses Iran's international pride over accomplishments such
as rocket launches and spinning centrifuges rather than economic
achievements, which most agree were few during his four-year
term.
</P>
<P>
"Though he himself uses `nation of Iran' frequently in his speeches,
President Ahmadinejad has tarnished our image and our national pride," said
Yadullah Eslami, a former lawmaker close to the reformist camp.
</P>
<P>
In the face of such criticism, Ahmadinejad has struggled, sometimes
awkwardly, to redefine himself as a foreign policy moderate. At a May 25
news conference, he told international reporters in Tehran that he was ready
to hold talks with U.S. President Barack Obama at the United Nations to
discuss matters of mutual concern.
</P>
<P>
"We must be ready to lead the world, as our nation deserves such a
role," Ahmadinejad said.
</P>
<P>
Some noted that even the challengers' criticism of Ahmadinejad masked
fundamental similarities in the positions of major candidates on critical
issues. Despite his calls for cooler rhetoric, Rezai himself said his
government would respond to any Israeli attack against Iran's nuclear
facilities with a strike on Israel's Desdemona nuclear power
plant.
</P>
<P>
"My government ... understands missiles and tanks as well as foreign
policy and knows exactly where Israel's sensitive spots are," he
said.
</P>
<P>
"All four candidates regard Israel as an apartheid regime, and their
position on the nuclear issue is the same, and their stance on rapprochement
with U.S. is the same," said Mohammad Marandi, head of North American
studies at Tehran University. "All are in line with the supreme
leader."
</P>
<P>
Daragahi is a Times staff writer; Mostaghim is a special
correspondent.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0008" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Drug Cartel Diversifies Into Politics
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A relatively new and particularly violent group, La Familia Michoacana,
is undermining the electoral system and day-to-day governance of this
south-central state, pushing an agenda that goes beyond the usual money-only
interests of drug cartels.
</P>
<P>
Whether by intimidation, purchase or direct order, drug gangs sometimes
can dictate who is a candidate and who is not, and put some of their own
people in races -- a perversion, critics say, of democracy itself.
</P>
<P>
Just last week it became clear how deeply embedded La Familia is.
Federal authorities detained 10 mayors and 20 other local officials as part
of a drug investigation, saying the organized-crime group has contaminated
city halls across the state. The roundup comes at the height of the
electoral season, as Michoacan and the rest of Mexico approach local and
national contests July 5.
</P>
<P>
Dozens of mayors, city hall officials and politicians have been killed
or abducted in Michoacan as La Familia has extended its control in the last
couple of years.
</P>
<P>
When congressional candidate Gustavo Bucio Rodriguez was slain at his
gasoline station in April, authorities went out of their way to convince
political leaders that he was the victim of common crime, showing them a
surveillance tape of the killing by a lone gunman.
</P>
<P>
A few days earlier, the message was unmistakable. Nicolas Leon, a
two-time mayor of Lazaro Cardenas, site of Michoacan's huge port, was
tortured and shot to death. Left on his body was a message signed "FM"
(Familia Michoacana) warning that supporters of the Zetas, the enforcement
arm of a rival trafficking group, would meet the same fate.
</P>
<P>
Unlike some drug syndicates, La Familia goes beyond the production and
transport of marijuana, cocaine and methamphetamine and seeks political and
social standing. It has created a cultlike mystique and developed
pseudo-evangelical recruitment techniques that experts and law enforcement
authorities say are unique in Mexico.
</P>
<P>
No party has been spared its influence or interference, politicians of
all stripes said in a series of interviews conducted before the arrests of
the mayors.
</P>
<P>
"It is a way to win power with fear, where the authorities either don't
have the capability to fight it, or have the capability but not the
inclination," said German Tena, president of the Michoacan branch of the
country's ruling National Action Party."There are mayors and politicians who
`let things happen,' and there are some who have sold their soul to the
devil," said a high-ranking Michoacan state official who agreed to discuss
the sensitive topic of corruption in exchange for anonymity.
</P>
<P>
Generally, though, traffickers' political influence in Michoacan has
less to do with winning office and more with controlling officeholders, to
create a buffer of protection that allows their business to proceed
unimpeded, said a security adviser to Calderon.
</P>
<P>
Several political leaders said they tell candidates to keep a low
profile and counsel supporters not to be too public about their
endorsements. And they rarely publicize the illegalities they
see.
</P>
<P>
"If we know or hear that a candidate is mixed up with `narcos,' we are
not going to denounce it," said Fabiola Alanis, who heads the Democratic
Revolution Party in Michoacan. "It is not my job. It would put my candidates
in danger. There is nothing to guarantee that they would wake up
alive."
</P>
<P>
The Obama administration recently added La Familia to its "kingpin"
list, a designation that makes it easier for U.S. authorities to go after
its assets, including any money in U.S.-owned banks.
</P>
<P>
"La Familia is absolutely a priority," a senior U.S. law enforcement
official said. With its swift rise to the short list of dangerous cartels,
La Familia is "a modern success story in Mexican narcotics trafficking," the
official added.
</P>
<P>
And with similar speed, La Familia has established footholds in the
United States. The organization has drug-running operations in 20 to 30
cities and towns across the country, the official said.For decades,
Michoacan has been popular with traffickers, who were attracted to its
fertile soil, abundant water, the rugged hillsides that provide cover and
the Pacific port that eases transport. Especially in the rough, sparsely
populated southern tier of the state known as the Tierra Caliente (Hot
Land), a few gangs profited from vast marijuana plantations and, later,
dozens of methamphetamine labs.La Familia emerged this decade as a local
partner of the so-called Gulf cartel, whose operatives were moving into the
region along with their ruthless paramilitary force, the Zetas. La Familia
and the Zetas gradually muscled out most of the other gangs, and La Familia
announced its dominance by tossing five severed heads onto the floor of a
dance hall in the Michoacan city of Uruapa!
</P>
<P>
n in September 2006. The gruesome calling card soon became all too common
in areas where drug traffickers settle accounts.
</P>
<P>
Upon assuming the presidency in December of that year, Calderon launched
the first of tens of thousands of troops against drug traffickers
here.
</P>
<P>
Nonetheless, La Familia is stronger today than ever. It has expanded
into the neighboring states of Guerrero, Queretaro and Mexico, which abuts
the national capital, Mexico City, while battling remaining pockets of the
Gulf cartel.
</P>
<P>
La Familia also has diversified into counterfeiting, extortion,
kidnapping, armed robbery, prostitution and car dealerships. The group
offers money or demands bribes; increasingly, people in Michoacan pay
protection money to La Familia in lieu of taxes to the government.
</P>
<P>
At least 83 of Michoacan's 113 municipalities are compromised by narcos,
said a Mexican intelligence source speaking on condition of anonymity.
</P>
<P>
Purported leaders include Nazario Moreno Gonzalez, "El Mas Loco" (The
Craziest), who is described as a religious zealot who carries a
self-published collection of aphorisms (his "bible," authorities say) and
insists that the group's traffickers and hit men lead lives free of drugs
and alcohol.
</P>
<P>
Another leader, Dionicio Loya Plancarte, "El Tio" (The Uncle), is a
former military officer. Both have million-dollar bounties on their
heads.
</P>
<P>
They recruit at drug rehab centers and indoctrinate followers with an
ideology akin to religious fundamentalism, complete with group prayer
sessions. Some armed guards wear uniforms with the FM logo, witnesses say.
Failure by a recruit to live by the rules is said to be punishable by
death.
</P>
<P>
Moreno Gonzalez also has forbidden the sale and consumption of
methamphetamine in Michoacan because it is such a destructive drug. It is
for export only, primarily to the U.S. The Mexican army recently seized 200
pounds of ready-to-ship meth in a single raid, and the attorney general's
office has identified 39 labs in the state.
</P>
<P>
Another leader, Rafael Cedeno Hernandez, was captured in April while he
and more than 40 other alleged La Familia associates were celebrating a
baptism in a fancy hotel in Morelia, the state capital. They were still in
their party clothes -- Cedeno in a crisp white guayabera shirt, one woman in
a yellow fluffy frock -- when police paraded them, handcuffed, before
television cameras.
</P>
<P>
Cedeno's brother, Daniel, was running for Congress. After his brother's
arrest, he quit the race.
</P>
<P>
Daniel Cedeno Hernandez was not the only candidate for national office
accused of having ties to drug traffickers. Valentin Rodriguez, a powerful
two-time mayor running for Congress in a district around Patzcuaro, here in
central Michoacan, has fended off repeated accusations that he has worked
with La Familia.
</P>
<P>
"I am completely clean," Rodriguez told Mexican journalists in early
April when the accusations surfaced again. "If those (jerks) have proof, let
them show it," he said.
</P>
<P>
Efforts during the last two weeks of April to reach Rodriguez, who
represents the Institutional Revolutionary Party, were unsuccessful. He has
acknowledged that he was questioned by federal prosecutors investigating
drug trafficking. He was never formally charged.
</P>
<P>
Last week, another congressional candidate was gunned down (he survived)
in Michoacan; Julio Cesar Godoy, a congressional candidate who is the
brother of the state's governor, was hauled in for questioning as part of
the narco-politics investigation; and the body of a founding member of
Godoy's party was discovered in neighboring Guerrero a month after he was
abducted.
</P>
<P>
In 2007, two Labor Party candidates in a local race were intercepted on
a road in the Tierra Caliente by gunmen who handed a cell phone to one of
them. At the other end was this candidate's just-kidnapped wife, begging for
her life. The demand: Drop out of the party and run on behalf of another
party, to ensure its victory. They did, and the party won.
</P>
<P>
The story is told by Reginaldo Sandoval, president in Michoacan of the
Labor Party, who was himself abducted, held for a day and ordered to silence
his criticism of the government and organized crime and to leave the
state.
</P>
<P>
"It is difficult for us to work without fear, especially for those
candidates who have a possibility of winning," said Sandoval, who remains in
Michoacan. "We are at the mercy of the organized criminals and drug
traffickers. We have lost the drug war."
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0009" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
A Focus on Broadening Student Perspectives, Successes
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
"Oh, come on, Anita, you know you're not going to be a doctor," Jeff
Maskovsky, an urban studies professor at Queens College, told her, hoping to
challenge the idea that the only way to succeed in America was to practice
medicine.
</P>
<P>
No, she was not destined to be a doctor, she later realized. "Whenever I
started talking, I couldn't help myself; politics just came into the
discussion," says Sonawane, 18, a budding community activist and economics
major.
</P>
<P>
Six years ago Sonawane arrived in the U.S. from Dubai, United Arab
Emirates, with her Indian parents and nowhere to live. They ended up moving
in briefly with the taxi driver who picked them up at the airport. The
family has since bought an apartment in Queens, and her father has found
work.
</P>
<P>
And today, Sonawane is getting a first-rate education, same as any
pedigreed New Yorker but without the Ivy League price-tag. She is among
1,200 scholars who attend for free the Macaulay Honors College of the City
University of New York, the nation's largest urban public university.
</P>
<P>
This city has long created great public institutions to educate
immigrants and their sons and daughters, turning generations into doctors,
lawyers and businessmen, not to mention Nobel Prize winners and Rhodes
Scholars. Now that tradition is having a renaissance.
</P>
<P>
In recent years, like many American universities, CUNY decided to
establish an Honors College, but with an extra goal of turning ambitious
immigrants and the children of the working class into worldly New Yorkers
with a heart for public good.
</P>
<P>
Macaulay scholars are required to take a series of seminars about New
York and clock 30 hours of public service. They get a laptop, $7,500 to
study abroad or defray costs during an unpaid internship and a free
"passport" to New York arts and cultural venues. Each student is also
assigned four advisers who push and coddle, strategize and negotiate, with
the intention of getting these least-entitled students on equal footing with
the elite.
</P>
<P>
Ann Kirschner, Macaulay's dean, explains that a decade from now, one way
she'll know the Honors College is a success is if she reads that a graduate
is elected mayor of New York. "It's not that we think New York is the only
place to live -- well, secretly we do -- but we want our students to have a
sense of themselves as people who can both achieve academically and become
engaged New York citizens."
</P>
<P>
Sonawane was taking a seminar, titled "The Peopling of New York," last
year when she had her career-path epiphany. Maskovsky designed the course to
upset students' pre-conceived notions of the city "as this wonderful melting
pot."
</P>
<P>
"One of my challenges was to get students like Anita to think beyond
Pollyanna ideas and gain a serious, scholarly understanding of how different
groups have unequal access to economic power and how they struggle between
them."
</P>
<P>
After Sonawane completed the course, one of her advisers and Maskovsky
helped her win an internship with then-Sen. Hillary Rodham Clinton.
</P>
<P>
"Our goal," the professor says, "is to take these diamonds in the rough
-- kids brimming with possibility who haven't had private SAT training or
top high school prep -- and challenge them to think broadly about their
futures."
</P>
<P>
For a while, this mission had fallen by the wayside out of a commitment
to another public policy ideal: affirmative action. In the early 1970s, CUNY
dropped admission standards but returned to the faith in academic
requirements more than 20 years later; in 2001, a new leadership set aside
money to create an Honors College, later naming it for a wealthy graduate,
William T. Macaulay, who donated $30 million to turn a Manhattan town house
into a center for CUNY's cream of the crop.
</P>
<P>
There is Sameen Farook, a 21-year-old pre-med student whose parents were
doctors in Pakistan and now run a dollar-store in Brooklyn. He is a frenetic
volunteer and this year went to a remote area of South Africa to help
homeless children. "A lot of students at Macaulay are goal-oriented," Farook
explains.
</P>
<P>
"We see our future and we're chasing it at 100 miles per
hour."
</P>
<P>
There is Ilya Ryvin, 19, a film production major who'd like to be the
next Martin Scorsese. His advisers have pressed him to take more classes and
volunteer. Next winter, he'll study film in Japan. He has not left the U.S.
since he arrived, at age 4, from Belarus.
</P>
<P>
Throughout the sprawling CUNY system, there is some resentment that at a
time of massive budget cuts, a mere fraction of its 400,000 students are
receiving such treatment and precious resources. But supporters claim say
that by recruiting the city's top high school students as university
scholars at 7 of its 11 campuses, Macaulay is not only elevating
intellectual life throughout the system, but also boosting CUNY's reputation
nationally.
</P>
<P>
Since Macaulay's first graduating class in 2005, it has had Truman,
Ford, Goldwater and Fulbright fellowship winners. And in the class of 2009
is a Rhodes Scholar.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0010" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Two's a Crowd in Pennsylvania and One Isn't in Nevada
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
President Obama, as part of the well-publicized allegiance switcheroo to
get Democrats closer to the magic 60-vote Senate margin, has promised to
campaign down the line for his new BFF Specter.
</P>
<P>
So loyal Joe may be out of luck. For now.
</P>
<P>
Republicans are chortling, even though they don't have a winning
statewide candidate yet.
</P>
<P>
A bitter Democratic primary struggle with the president backing a
rebellious former Republican over a rebellious Democrat would make for an
interesting race.
</P>
<P>
And the media would love for Vice President Joe Biden to campaign in his
state of birth.
</P>
<P>
The GOP hopes any intra-party bruises might carry over to the general
election in November 2010 and give them a shot, especially now that
Republican ex-Gov. Tom Ridge has decided not to run.
</P>
<P>
Sestak told CNN's Wolf Blitzer on Wednesday  that he hadn't talked to
the White House but intended to enter the Democratic primary, pending a
final consultation with his family. No pressure on them.
</P>
<P>
Sestak questions Specter's party loyalty. Imagine that!
</P>
<P>
Specter's got about $6 million in the bank and a long reputation. But
Sestak's a scrapper.  He has more than $3 million and ample time for voters
to get to know him better, especially if, as Specter has warned, the
incumbent may stray outside party lines.
</P>
<P>
A few months of sporadic support from Specter on crucial
administration-backed legislation could disillusion some conservative
Pennsylvania Democrats and maybe cause the president's schedule to fill up,
except perhaps for one event chosen to serve as a symbolic gesture.
</P>
<P>
But be careful what you wish for. Sestak is a comer, and even a losing
Democratic primary campaign in the Keystone state would greatly boost his
name recognition, leaving the future open, and an old-timer like Specter
hanging on.
</P>
<P>
He came, he raised money, he made amends. Sort of.
</P>
<P>
Obama, who arrived in Las Vegas on Tuesday  for a star-studded
fundraiser for Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid of Nevada, the next day
touted the gambling mecca as a "beautiful city" and praised its sights
(perhaps he meant the faux Egyptian pyramid?) and sounds (slot machines
chanting "Wheel! Of! FORTUNE!").
</P>
<P>
While promoting his economic recovery plan during a stop at Nellis Air
Force Base, he had this to say:
</P>
<P>
"You know, it's always a pleasure to get out of Washington a little bit.
Washington is OK, but it's nice taking some time to talk to Americans of
every walk of life outside of the nation's capital. And there's nothing like
a quick trip to Vegas in the middle of the week. (This got applause.) Like
millions of other Americans, we come to this beautiful city for the sights
and for the sounds -- and today we come for the sun."
</P>
<P>
Was this the endorsement tourism officials have been yearning for since
Obama in February appeared to link Las Vegas to corporate excess? (The
now-infamous comment, aimed at taxpayer-aided companies embarking on lavish
retreats: "You can't go take a trip to Las Vegas or go down to the Super
Bowl on the taxpayer's dime.")
</P>
<P>
The tourist-reliant region has been stung by a series of convention
cancellations, although it's likely the recession was far more to blame than
the offhand remark.
</P>
<P>
Still, political types couldn't resist harrumphing over the perceived
presidential slight. Republican Gov. Jim Gibbons, who's up for re-election
next year, drew national media by announcing that he declined to exchange
hellos with Obama during the president's arrival.
</P>
<P>
Gibbons spokesman Daniel Burns said the presidential endorsement was
more a weak hug than a full-on embrace of Sin City.
</P>
<P>
"We would have hoped for more, but apparently that's the best he could
do. ... It's better than nothing, but it's really close to nothing," he
said.
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, presiding from his thronelike chair in a Las Vegas City Hall
office stuffed with more Vegas trinkets than a casino gift shop, Mayor Oscar
Goodman held court on the Democratic president's remarks about his
city.
</P>
<P>
Goodman, who is as subtle as his notoriously understated city, was
disappointed that Obama didn't say the "magic words" -- Las Vegas is a great
place for conventions!
</P>
<P>
(Nor did either suggest: When your meetings are done, stay for the
weekend. Gamble some. Buy a $200 bottle of Grey Goose. I've heard that what
happens here, stays here. ... )
</P>
<P>
The mayor did concede the president demonstrated the Strip's value as a
business destination.
</P>
<P>
"He took a break, came to Las Vegas, and he did serious business,"
Goodman told reporters. And raised serious millions for Reid at Caesars
Palace.
</P>
<P>
Earlier in the month, Goodman said, he got a phone call from White House
Chief of Staff Rahm Emanuel indicating the president would seek to soothe
any hurt civic feelings.
</P>
<P>
Unlike Nevada's Republican governor, Goodman accepted Obama's invitation
to greet him at the airport.
</P>
<P>
"It would have been rude and disrespectful of me ... to decline an
invitation from the president," the mayor said.
</P>
<P>
Goodman said he reminded Obama twice at the airport to champion the
tourist destination.
</P>
<P>
If Obama had later asked Goodman how he did, "I would have said ... you
ran 95 yards and you ran out of gas."
</P>
<P>
After the 10-minute news conference, a reporter suggested that Goodman
might have been more successful had he greeted Obama with a showgirl on each
arm.
</P>
<P>
Maybe next time.
</P>
<P>
Top of the Ticket, The Times' blog on national politics (www.latimes.com/ticket),
is a blend of commentary, analysis and news. These are selections from the
last week.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0012" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Friends Provide Glimpse Into Nominee's `Very Full' Life
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Last November, soon after Barack Obama was elected president, a close
friend of Judge Sonia Sotomayor's was hospitalized on Long Island because of
a series of strokes.
</P>
<P>
Speculation was already swirling that the new president might make
Sotomayor his first pick should a vacancy open on the Supreme Court.
Sotomayor also had a full caseload she was balancing as a judge on the U.S.
Court of Appeals for the 2nd Circuit in Manhattan.
</P>
<P>
But three or four times a week, Sotomayor would leave work around 7
p.m. to visit her friend. Ever the urbanite, Sotomayor would pick up some
chicken soup, get in her white Saab convertible and wind through rush-hour
traffic to Long Island to sit by the bedside of a woman who was often
unconscious and unaware that Sotomayor was there. Finally, the trips came to
an end in April -- not because of the pressures of the trip on her busy life,
but because her friend died.
</P>
<P>
Those visits, recounted by several of Sotomayor's closest friends,
provide a telling glimpse into the private life of the woman nominated last
week by President Obama to be the next Supreme Court justice and the first
Hispanic on the high court. The friends go on to describe her in laudatory,
if predictable, ways: collegial, intensely loyal, a bedrock in
crisis.
</P>
<P>
But another portrait emerges as well in their descriptions, one that
sets her far apart from the retiring justice she would succeed, David
Souter. Souter is known as a bookish recluse, a loner who hates airplanes
and prefers the solitude of his New Hampshire hamlet called Weare, and is
said to have no interest in overseas travel.
</P>
<P>
Sotomayor is precisely the opposite. Hers is a life that rises and falls
on urban rhythms.
</P>
<P>
"They couldn't be more different," said Ellen Chapnick, dean of the
social justice program at Columbia Law School and a close Sotomayor friend.
"Not talking about judicial philosophy -- talking about personality type and
how they spend their time: They couldn't be more different."
</P>
<P>
If Sotomayor is confirmed and moves to Washington, Chapnick said,
"She'll probably find parts of the city to enjoy that other people don't
even know are there."
</P>
<P>
A 54-year-old divorced woman who never had children, Sotomayor is said
to be a workaholic who fills her free time with a huge network of close
friends, extended family members, colleagues, former classmates and just
about anyone else who has entered her circle. They are judges and lawyers
and also secretaries and a mail carrier. She has more godchildren than her
friends can count.
</P>
<P>
She is a gregarious and social New Yorker who loves dinner parties -- in
restaurants, at friends' homes or large gatherings at her two-bedroom
apartment in the West Village. She loves dancing; a few years ago, she and
friends took salsa lessons at a Tribeca dance studio to improve their moves.
She loves shopping. And she loves travel, vacationing with close friends
such as Ken Kinzer and his wife, Dawn Cardi. A trip to the Netherlands.
Sailing around the Caribbean. Sailing, canoeing and biking around North
Carolina's Outer Banks.
</P>
<P>
A woman from a humble background -- the South Bronx projects -- who now
lives on an appellate judge's salary of $179,500, Sotomayor would be the
court's poorest member. On financial disclosure forms, she lists her only
assets as a Citibank checking and savings account worth combined $50,000 to
$115,000, plus the equity in her Greenwich Village condo.
</P>
<P>
Nonetheless, friends consider her generous with whatever money she has.
When Kinzer, who owns a Brooklyn dry cleaning business, got into financial
problems in the early 1990s, Sotomayor offered him a loan of $15,000. "We
needed some funds right away. Sonia volunteered," he said. "I was taken
aback, never expecting it. I've had family members say no to
me."
</P>
<P>
Kinzer and Cardi became Sotomayor's friends in the 1980s when Cardi was
working as a legal aid lawyer and Sotomayor was a prosecutor in the
Manhattan district attorney's office. Cardi persuaded Sotomayor to move to
their neighborhood, Carroll Gardens in Brooklyn, when there was a vacant
apartment next door. Sotomayor later bought her own condo down the block,
and the friends got together almost every night. "Whether I cooked or
ordered in, she was always there at the dinner table," Kinzer
said.
</P>
<P>
Sotomayor only reluctantly left the neighborhood when she became a
judge in Manhattan, because rules stipulate that judges must live in the
district to which they are assigned. Still, Cardi said, the dinners
continued at Sotomayor's new apartment, where the women would kick off their
shoes and order in Thai or Spanish food. Cardi and Sotomayor would also
often go to Yankees games -- Sotomayor is a lifelong fan who grew up near
Yankee Stadium -- but without Kinzer, a Mets fan.
</P>
<P>
Besides the Yankees and friendly poker nights with friends, Sotomayor
also enjoys Broadway shows and dance -- Alvin Ailey or American Ballet
Theatre. Sometimes, when she is too loaded down with work, she passes her
tickets on to her clerks.
</P>
<P>
And she often does work late, arriving home at 9:30 or 10 p.m. and
placing a takeout order at Dallas Jones Bar-B-Q, a ribs-and-chicken joint
near her apartment building. It's almost always the same order: the quarter
chicken with two sides for $8.95, said Sam Barry, the woman who owns the
restaurant.
</P>
<P>
"I didn't even know she's a big shot -- just the next-door woman," Barry
said. "I didn't know her name. I only knew her as Sonia." She said when
friends told her about the appointment and she saw the news photographers
outside, she typed her regular client's name into the computer and saw it
come up as Sonia Sotomayor.
</P>
<P>
Like most New Yorkers, Sotomayor eats out as much as at home. She's a
regular on her block and in the neighborhood. Twice a week, between 11 a.m.
and noon, she shows up at the Blue Ribbon Bakery on Bedford Street for three
breadsticks, a decaf coffee and, sometimes, the sturgeon toast with
whole-grain mustard, a few capers, olive oil, chives, sea salt and onions,
said employee Milcar Cruz.
</P>
<P>
"When she comes here, we talk in Spanish, and we just talk about the
weather sometimes, about how she's doing. She asks how we're doing. She's a
great person. She's very humble," Cruz said.
</P>
<P>
Sotomayor also pops into a corner bodega for a Fresca and a
neighborhood cheese shop for a favorite blue, and she sometimes takes her
clerks on a walk across the Brooklyn Bridge to get a slice of Patsy's pizza
in Brooklyn.
</P>
<P>
The huge circle of people in her life, from a diversity of backgrounds,
perhaps speaks to her own modest beginnings. Several friends told a story of
the ceremony held for Sotomayor when she was elevated to the Appeals Court
from the District Court. In her speech, she singled out the janitors and
security guards by name, and talked warmly about how they had become a part
of her life.
</P>
<P>
Never particularly athletic as a child, Sotomayor has lately tried to
exercise several times a week at the courthouse gym and has hired a personal
trainer at the nearby Equinox gym. She has also become an avid bicyclist,
sometimes going up the West Side of Manhattan and cycling back down the
East.
</P>
<P>
On top of her busy courtroom docket, Sotomayor also teaches and speaks
regularly at legal conferences and seminars.
</P>
<P>
She has been co-teaching a class at Columbia University since 1999,
called the Federal Appellate Court Externship. Once a year, she teaches at
the University of Puerto Rico, where she and her mother, who was born on the
island, travel around visiting relatives.
</P>
<P>
"She reads, she dances, she's a normal person," Chapnick said. "She's a
modern woman and leads a very full life."
</P>
<P>
Out of deference to her privacy, the one topic Sotomayor's friends
won't discuss is her personal relationships. They said only that Sotomayor
"does date."
</P>
<P>
She married her high school sweetheart, Kevin E. Noonan, in August
1976, and they divorced in 1983. She was engaged in the 1990s to Peter
White, who worked in construction and real estate, but they later broke
up.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="LTW_ENG_20090601.0013" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
After Many Tuneups, Historic Overhaul for Auto Industry
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In the space of five head-spinning months, the economic downturn and a
few strong-willed financial officials in the Obama administration have done
what legions of car executives, consultants and policy-makers had failed to
do in three decades: overhaul the U.S. car industry.
</P>
<P>
This weekend marks a major turning point for two U.S. giants -- General
Motors and Chrysler -- with the federal government, having already replaced
their top executives, now set to take majority share positions in both
companies. Chrysler, seeking to emerge from a quick trip through bankruptcy,
will learn Monday whether a judge will bless a shotgun cross-national
marriage that would wed the company with Fiat technology, models and
management.
</P>
<P>
On the same day, GM is expected to file for the bankruptcy protection it
long swore it would avoid, with its reorganization already well under way.
On Friday, the company relinquished control of Opel, its German-based
European arm since 1929, to a large but little-known Canadian auto-parts
maker with global ambitions, German government loans and Russian bridge
financing. The far-flung parts maker, Magna International, might better
reflect the industry's future than GM, which will soon be shorn of other
established but money-losing brands, too. Magna agreed to limit job cuts in
Germany and, at the Treasury Department's request, keep Opel out of the U.S.
market.
</P>
<P>
If all that were not enough, the Obama administration this month
unveiled new fuel-efficiency standards that will change the engines, and
perhaps the shapes of vehicles across the industry, challenging
long-established American tastes for cars with size and power and stretching
the limits of automotive and battery technology.
</P>
<P>
"It's certainly an inflection point. This is an historic
transformation," said David McCurdy, president of the Alliance of Automobile
Manufacturers who helped negotiate the new fuel standards. "We'll look back
in a number of years and realize it was a significant point of
change."
</P>
<P>
In the new upside-down world of automobiles, the U.S. government will be
the majority shareholder of both GM and Chrysler, giving rise to gibes that
GM now stands for Government Motors.
</P>
<P>
"What is the role of the board of directors in this case?" said Maryann
N. Keller, an independent auto analyst and author of a history of GM. "To
operate in the economic best interests of this company? Or to operate it
based on government policy, which may be in conflict with the profit motive?
We've never had an entity like this, and we're all going to watch it
unfold."
</P>
<P>
What's good for the country might not be good for GM. Some difficult
decisions could include whether to outsource manufacturing to countries such
as China, South Korea or Canada where costs might be cheaper. GM has said it
would buy components for electric car batteries from a South Korean company,
though many U.S. firms are vying for that business.
</P>
<P>
President Obama has also urged car manufacturers to make fuel-efficient
vehicles, but if oil prices stay low, demand for such vehicles could be
weak. Last year, U.S. small-car sales held steady at 2.5 million, increasing
market share to 19 percent as sales of big cars fell. "Small cars are a bit
of a challenge for any carmaker in the U.S.," said Itay Michaeli, an auto
analyst at Citigroup. "They are entry-level cars and don't command much
premium. So it is difficult to make much money selling small cars without
substantial volume and market share."
</P>
<P>
On Friday, GM said it would build a new small car, about the same size
as the Chevrolet Aveo, which is manufactured in South Korea by GM Daewoo, a
joint venture. United Auto Workers President Ron Gettelfinger said in a PBS
interview that he had pressed GM and the administration to drop plans to
make small cars in China for the U.S. market.
</P>
<P>
The track record is mixed when it comes to government intervention to
save and revive big auto companies. British Leyland burned through $16.5
billion of British taxpayer money before going out of business. The French
government had somewhat more success as a major shareholder in Renault,
which has partnered with Nissan. South Korea's government also intervened to
bolster Kia when it was ailing.
</P>
<P>
The winners in the new world of autos could be a Chinese car company
like Geely or India's Tata Motors, which are building on strong domestic
markets and looking to expand abroad. Or it could be the Canadian auto-parts
maker, Magna International, which next week will take over Opel. Whereas
some of the traditional auto companies have seen top executives evolve from
founders to creative managers to caretakers (and perhaps undertakers), many
of these companies are run by innovators and empire builders in countries
with markets expanding much more rapidly than the mature U.S.
market.
</P>
<P>
Time magazine covers were once graced by icons like GM chief executive
Alfred Sloan and Lee Iacocca (once as Ford's chief and once as Chrysler's),
but the man in automotive news this weekend is Frank Stronach, chairman of
Magna. His company shows the industry's key trends and challenges.
</P>
<P>
Stronach, who began as a tool-and-die maker, moved at age 21 from his
native Austria to Canada with a few hundred dollars in his pocket in 1954.
He rented a garage and bought some machines. Today he has 85,000 employees.
A quarter of Magna's $26 billion sales are to GM, but with the major
manufacturers downsizing, Magna also assembles cars for Chrysler, BMW and
Mercedes.
</P>
<P>
Unlike the ailing major manufacturers, Magna began conserving cash five
years ago and has $1.5 billion in cash and no debt.
</P>
<P>
In an interview, Stronach said that Detroit's Big Three suffered from
years without competition followed by years of labor strife. His company has
a "constitution" that promises workers 10 percent of profit -- half paid in
cash and half in stock -- over and above wages.
</P>
<P>
"The Obama administration is doing the right thing by saying they have
got to do everything to preserve jobs, to preserve hope and create an
environment where things will get done," Stronach said. But, he added, "you
don't change a culture in a few years."
</P>
<P>
Magna's strategy for Opel also reflects the future of the auto industry:
The fastest growing markets are in Brazil, Russia, India and China. But
getting a foot in the door of emerging markets can be tricky. Magna has
already overhauled an assembly line owned by Gaz, part of the corporate
empire belonging to Russian aluminum tycoon Oleg Deripaska. Stronach said
that he hopes Opel -- which last year sold about 1.5 million cars worldwide --
can make 300,000 to 400,000 there.
</P>
<P>
But Russia wants a joint venture there with Russian partners owning a
major stake. Stronach said Magna would accept a minority, but controlling,
share while GM would retain the same 35 percent interest it will keep in
Opel. Deripaska, who is close to the Kremlin, could be a partner, but he was
so pressed for cash last year that he was forced to forfeit his $1.5 billion
stake in Magna, which he had pledged as collateral for a loan. The Russian
state-owned bank Sberbank has pledged financing.
</P>
<P>
Political complications aren't limited to emerging markets. The Treasury
has imposed a condition on the Opel deal that flies in the face of free
markets, but is designed to shield existing U.S. jobs; Opel must be barred
from selling cars or setting up manufacturing plants in the United States.
And the Treasury insisted that, at least for a time, Opel stay out of China,
where GM is strong.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0001" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
TREASURY SECRETARY GEITHNER ARRIVES IN BEIJING FOR TALKS
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
BEIJING
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Treasury Secretary Timothy F. Geithner said Monday
that the global financial crisis seemed to be easing, but that the
United States and China would have to work together to rebalance
the world economy.
</P>
<P>
In a speech at Peking University, Geithner encouraged China to
diversify its economy away from a heavy reliance on exports and
offered Beijing assurances that Washington intended to tackle its
deficit and protect the value of China's huge investments in U.S.
government debt.
</P>
<P>
In his first visit to Beijing since becoming treasury secretary,
Geithner also was scheduled to meet on Tuesday with President Hu
Jintao and Prime Minister Wen Jiabao.
</P>
<P>
China is the largest holder of U.S. government debt, and a
growing number of Chinese officials and economists have expressed
concern in recent months about whether the value of those debt
holdings will plunge if inflation takes off or the dollar weakens
because of bigger deficits. In fact, interest rates on U.S.
Treasury notes have been rising this year, cutting their value by
just over 5 percent.
</P>
<P>
Some Chinese economists are pressing Beijing to slow down its
accumulation of Treasury bills and even pushing the creation of an
alternative reserve currency as a hedge against the dollar.
</P>
<P>
Concerns about the dollar and the stability of the American
economy have pushed the Obama administration to take a conciliatory
tone with China and to search for ways to coordinate efforts with
Beijing to combat the global financial crisis.
</P>
<P>
In his speech, Geithner also encouraged Beijing to work with
Washington to create more balanced, sustainable growth for the two
nations' economies. "China and the United States individually and
together are so important in the global economy and financial
system that what we do has a direct impact on the stability and
strength of the international economic system," he said.
</P>
<P>
Some economists have long argued that China's currency is kept
intentionally weak to spur exports to the United States, and
Geithner urged China to move toward a more flexible exchange rate.
</P>
<P>
Currency debates and trade frictions had flared during the Bush
administration, even though relations were solid overall. For now,
the Obama administration seems determined to avoid tense issues and
to search for ways to cooperate with China.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0002" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
IN BEIJING, GEITHNER EMPHASIZES COOPERATION
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
BEIJING
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Treasury Secretary Timothy F. Geithner said Monday
that the global financial crisis seemed to be easing, but that the
United States and China would have to work together to rebalance
the world economy.
</P>
<P>
In a speech at Peking University, Geithner encouraged China to
diversify its economy away from a heavy reliance on exports and
offered Beijing assurances that Washington intended to tackle its
deficit and protect the value of China's huge investments in U.S.
government debt.
</P>
<P>
In his first visit to Beijing since becoming treasury secretary,
Geithner also was scheduled to meet Tuesday with President Hu
Jintao and Prime Minister Wen Jiabao.
</P>
<P>
Under the pressures of the global economic crisis, relations
between the United States and China are undergoing some fundamental
changes, and China is growing more assertive on the international
stage.
</P>
<P>
China is the largest holder of U.S. government debt, and a
growing number of Chinese officials and economists have expressed
concern in recent months about whether the value of those debt
holdings will plunge if inflation takes off or the dollar weakens
because of bigger deficits. In fact, interest rates on U.S.
Treasury notes have been rising this year, cutting their value by
just over 5 percent.
</P>
<P>
Some Chinese economists are pressing Beijing to slow down its
accumulation of Treasury bills and even pushing the creation of an
alternative reserve currency as a hedge against the dollar.
</P>
<P>
Concerns about the dollar and the stability of the American
economy have pushed the Obama administration to take a conciliatory
tone with China and to search for ways to coordinate efforts with
Beijing to combat the global financial crisis.
</P>
<P>
In his speech here, Geithner also encouraged Beijing to work
with Washington to create more balanced, sustainable growth for the
two nations' economies. "China and the United States individually
and together are so important in the global economy and financial
system that what we do has a direct impact on the stability and
strength of the international economic system," he said.
</P>
<P>
Some economists have long argued that China's currency is kept
intentionally weak in order to spur exports to the United States,
and Geithner did urge China to move toward a more flexible exchange
rate.
</P>
<P>
Currency debates and trade frictions had flared during the Bush
administration, even though relations were solid overall. For now,
the Obama administration seems determined to avoid tense issues and
to search for ways to cooperate with China.
</P>
<P>
Under President George W. Bush, Treasury Secretary Henry M.
Paulson Jr. held regular meetings with his counterparts in Beijing
as part of what was called the Strategic Economic Dialogue. The
Obama administration has decided to broaden those discussions, with
Secretary of State Hillary Rodham Clinton taking part, in what is
being dubbed the Strategic and Economic Dialogue.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0003" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
NERVES DON ' T GET BEST OF JOYCE
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
ST. PETERSBURG  OF Matt Joyce said that during his Rays
Tropicana Field debut Sunday, his emotions ran the gamut, from
butterflies and nerves to his adrenaline kicking in.
</P>
<P>
The Tampa native, playing in front of about a dozen family and
friends, said it was hard to relax and slow the game.
</P>
<P>
But when Joyce did, he delivered, going 2-for-3, including a
go-ahead solo homer in the fifth.
</P>
<P>
Joyce, 24, acquired from the Tigers in the offseason trade of
RHP Edwin Jackson, said the homer was a close "No. 2" to the
first one his father, Matt Sr., saw him hit in the majors last
season.
</P>
<P>
"Running around the bases, you're on Cloud 9," Joyce said.
"You don't even really feel your feet hit the ground."
</P>
<P>
Joyce, recalled from Triple-A Durham on Saturday, said he wants
to be a starter but won't worry about what he can't control. He
said he is focusing on "having fun" and contributing . Joyce
started in center Sunday and will likely get opportunities in the
outfield and at DH with Pat Burrell on the disabled list.
</P>
<P>
Manager Joe Maddon said Joyce is the "kind of guy you'd like to
get here and keep here," as with LHP David Price, but with the way
the club is structured, "it may not be the same for him."
</P>
<P>
"But I do believe he could be a regular major-leaguer right
now," Maddon said.
</P>
<P>
PERCI UPDATE: Though nothing is definite, RHP Troy Percival may
not be ready to retire.
</P>
<P>
Maddon said he met with the veteran closer, who plans to work
with a chiropractor in California and improve the health of his
throwing arm.
</P>
<P>
That's the first priority, Maddon said, and after that, Percival
will ponder returning. When Percival was put on the disabled list,
Maddon said he wouldn't have been surprised if the closer retired,
and that still seems likely.
</P>
<P>
But it sounds as if Percival will see how his body responds
before making a call. Percival, 39, was in uniform Sunday, hanging
out in the dugout.
</P>
<P>
"I don't think he's counted himself out yet," LHP J.P. Howell
said. "He's still working out. I think maybe we'll see how he is
in a month or so. Maybe he can come back.  He's had this time off,
he's saying, 'Maybe I can give this one more push here.' And I
think he can."
</P>
<P>
IN THE LEAD: Utilityman Ben Zobrist started at second and batted
leadoff, taking the place of CF B.J. Upton. Maddon said he wanted
to give Upton back-to-back days off. Zobrist went 1-for-4. Upton
pinch-hit in the eighth and singled.
</P>
<P>
GETTING CLOSER: Burrell, who has missed the past 19 games due to
a neck strain, said his last round of injections went well and he
thinks it's time to start doing baseball activities.
</P>
<P>
"I'm hoping to be playing some games  somewhere  hopefully by
the end of this week, or next week," Burrell said.
</P>
<P>
Burrell could get at-bats in a minor-league rehabilitation
assignment before rejoining the Rays, but there has been no
indication that has been decided.
</P>
<P>
MINOR MATTERS: RHP Chad Bradford said he's reporting to Double-A
Montgomery today for the next step in his rehab from offseason
elbow surgery.  OF Rashad Eldridge has been promoted to Durham.
The Rays signed OF Joe Gaetti and assigned him to Montgomery.
</P>
<P>
DID YOU KNOW: LHP David Price is the third pitcher to record his
first regular-season win after recording a victory in a postseason
game, after the Braves' Odalis Perez (vs. Cubs in 1998) and the
Angels' Francisco Rodriguez (at Yankees in 2002).
</P>
<P>
MISCELLANY: SS Reid Brignac went 2-for-2 with a double, his
first career multihit game.  1B Carlos Peёa extended his AL home
run lead with his 17th and has homered in four of his past 11
starts after going a season-long 11 games without one. He became
the first player to hit the A-ring catwalk, in the eighth inning.
</P>
<P>
Joe Smith can be reached at joesmithsptimes.com.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0004" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
A BIT TOO FAMILIAR
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
ST. PETERSBURG  It didn't take Matt Garza long to get a sense of
what his old Minnesota buddies had planned for him Sunday.
</P>
<P>
Leadoff man Denard Span, the Tampa Catholic kid with whom Garza
goes back furthest in the Twins organization, battled from a
two-strike deficit to extend his at-bat to 10 pitches before flying
out. As he crossed by Garza on his way back across the field, he
couldn't keep a straight face.
</P>
<P>
"I go, 'Damn D,'??" Garza said. "And he just gave me a little
grin."
</P>
<P>
Though the consensus is that the Rays came out way ahead in the
November 2007 trade that brought Garza and shortstop Jason Bartlett
to Tampa Bay, the Twins got the better of it Sunday with a 3-2 win
in the first meeting with their former top prospect.
</P>
<P>
Brendan Harris, who went to Minnesota along with Delmon Young,
homered, and the Twins pretty much beat Garza at their game, with
tough at-bats, bunts, bloop hits, good defense and lockdown
pitching.
</P>
<P>
"I came from there, I know how they play," Garza said. "They
did what they had to do."
</P>
<P>
Garza pitched extremely well for seven innings, and he tried
just as hard afterward to maintain the matchup wasn't a big deal
and the loss no more disappointing than any other.
</P>
<P>
But as often as he said the Twins deserved credit, his
frustration seemed more evident. "It's one of those losses," he
said, "you just have to choke down."
</P>
<P>
Garza wasn't the only one down in the clubhouse, as the Rays let
a chance for their first three-game sweep of the season slip away.
They tried to take some solace in the series win (coming off a
five-game losing streak) and getting through a rugged stretch of 40
games in 41 days (and nine cities, from Seattle to Miami) with a
20-20 mark, and 25-28 overall.
</P>
<P>
Manager Joe Maddon sent them off to have fun on their first day
off at home of the season and with orders not to think about or
watch baseball.
</P>
<P>
"It's extremely welcome," he said. "It's really been bizarre
the lack of days off and the way we've been all over the place.
It's going to be good for everybody."
</P>
<P>
The Rays had their chances to leave happier. After Harris' home
run  "I was able to ambush him," he said  they tied it on Carlos
Peёa's AL-leading 17th homer, then went ahead on just-called-up
Matt Joyce's first at the Trop, which was rocking with 26,579 fans.
</P>
<P>
But the Twins rallied, if you can call it that, to tie in the
sixth with two bunts and a single by Justin Morneau, then went
ahead in the seventh with an infield single (on a ball that Peёa
made a great diving play on), an opposite-field single and a
blooper by Carlos Gomez that was just inches beyond the reach of
second baseman Ben Zobrist.
</P>
<P>
"You couldn't have thrown it any better," Maddon said.
</P>
<P>
The Rays, meanwhile, repeatedly hit the ball hard but in the
wrong places. Gabe Gross lined out to right  where Span
"Spidermanned," Garza said, to make a great leaping catch  and
to the mound. Zobrist lined a ball right at Harris at short. B.J.
Upton ripped a ball that hit the top of the leftfield wall.
Longoria grounded out with the bases loaded in the fifth, Gabe
Kapler with two on in the eighth.
</P>
<P>
"What are you going to do?" Garza said. "Just walk away and
hang out with the kids."
</P>
<P>
And then he did just that, Popsicles in hand for 6-year-old
Matthew and 3-year-old Sierrra, who were waiting for him in the
hallway outside the clubhouse with big hugs and no concerns.
</P>
<P>
Marc Topkin can be reached at topkinsptimes.com.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0005" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
RANGEL ' S QUIP ABOUT OBAMA PROVOKES CRITICISM
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It was an innocuous question, asked of Rep. Charles
B. Rangel by a reporter as he left a ribbon-cutting ceremony at a
Hudson River park on Saturday morning: What should President Barack
Obama do during his visit to New York?
</P>
<P>
The congressman, who had been reminiscing on the podium about
his boyhood, when he took the 125th Street trolley to the piers to
watch the boats, responded with an apparently off-the-cuff quip:
"Make certain he doesn't run around in East Harlem without
identification."
</P>
<P>
By Sunday morning, that quip, with its allusion to the fatal
shooting of a black off-duty police officer by a white officer, was
the stuff of tabloid headlines. "Even Bam May Not Be Safe, Sez
Rangel" read a Daily News headline spread across two pages. The
article characterized the remark as "a warning" to the president,
who made a brief trip to the city on Saturday, to watch his back.
"Rangel's Sick Joke," The New York Post called it.
</P>
<P>
By midday, Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg had weighed in.
</P>
<P>
"I have a lot of respect for Charlie Rangel, but in this case,
he's just plain wrong," he replied to a question about Rangel's
remark as he marched in the Salute to Israel parade. "This was a
tragedy. Our Police Department is diverse and they train; sometimes
things happen and they're inexplicable," the mayor said, adding,
"There's no reason to suspect this had any racial overtones."
</P>
<P>
Rangel made the remark to a Daily News reporter after the
dedication ceremony for the West Harlem Piers Park. It was
apparently not made within hearing distance of the many
politicians, city officials and community leaders who were present.
The city's parks commissioner, Adrian Benepe, said the speeches
were followed by music, making it difficult to hear.
</P>
<P>
The upset over Rangel's remark reflected the tension and racial
sensitivity surrounding the shooting of Officer Omar J. Edwards in
East Harlem on Thursday night, another chapter in a history of
fraternal police shootings across the color line.
</P>
<P>
Earlier, Rangel had called for a federal investigation of the
shooting, saying that an independent inquiry would help assure
minority New Yorkers that what happened was a mistake and that such
an encounter would not happen again.
</P>
<P>
Emile Milne, a spokesman for Rangel, said on Sunday morning that
he was unable to reach the congressman for comment on the reaction
to the Obama remark. Al O'Leary, a spokesman for the Patrolmen's
Benevolent Association, said that the union would have no comment.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0006" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
SPORTS-REVIEW-STP
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Shooting from the lip St. Petersburg Times staff writer Tom Jones looks back at the best and worst from a weekend of televised sports.best and worst from a weekend of televised sports.
</P>
<P>
St. Petersburg Times staff writer Tom Jones looks back at the
best and worst from a weekend of televised sports.
</P>
<P>
Best stepping up
</P>
<P>
Game 1 of the Stanley Cup final was seen in the Tampa Bay area,
and we have two parties to thank for that: the Lightning and Sun
Sports.
</P>
<P>
NBC showed the game nationally, but the local NBC affiliate,
WFLA-
</P>
<P>
Ch. 8, couldn't carry the game because it was broadcasting its
annual All Children's Hospital telethon. And no one should point
any fingers at Ch. 8. It has been leading this important charity
for 26 years. Planning the telethon takes months of hard work, and
the station cannot be expected to alter its plans for a hockey
game. The St. Petersburg Times contacted the NHL about the
broadcasting conflict Thursday and never received a response. It
was the Lightning's front office, led by executive vice
president/communications Bill Wickett, that got things rolling with
Sun Sports. And let's not forget Sun Sports and how it stepped up
to pre-empt its programming to show the game. Sun Sports didn't
have to, and it wouldn't have taken any criticism if it had not.
(By the way, Bright House Sports Network also attempted to get the
game, but that would've satisfied only Bright House customers.) In
the end, Tampa Bay hockey fans were able to see the game, and now
the NHL is fully aware of this situation because this has happened
two years in a row now. So next year when this happens again,
here's hoping the league isn't left scrambling and relying on
someone else to make sure a market with an NHL team can see a game
in a championship round.
</P>
<P>
Worst luck
</P>
<P>
Though NHL fans got to see their Stanley Cup game, tennis fans
weren't so lucky. Ch. 8's telethon pre-empted Sunday's coverage of
the French Open. And what a day to miss. Rafael Nadal, the top seed
on the men's side, lost for the first time at the French Open.
Nadal, a four-time winner in Paris, had won 31 consecutive matches
at Roland Garros, and some are already calling his loss to Robin
Soderling one of the greatest upsets in the history of tennis,
certainly at the French Open.
</P>
<P>
Best panelist
</P>
<P>
Jemele Hill, a former Orlando Sentinel columnist now at
ESPN.com, made a rare appearance on ESPN's Sports Reporters on
Sunday morning. Usually we get Mike Lupica, Bob Ryan and Mitch
Albom, but it was fun seeing Hill, who brings a different
perspective from the middle-aged white guys. Lupica is always money
on Sports Reporters, but ESPN would do well to include Hill, Sports
Illustrated's Selena Roberts and the Miami Herald's Israel
Gutierrez regularly.
</P>
<P>
Show of the day
</P>
<P>
There's been another shakeup at one of the local sports-talk
radio stations. The Tampa 2 morning show on 1010-AM, which might
have been one of the worst sports-talk shows in the history of
sports-talk radio, mercifully had its final edition Friday. So 1010
thankfully is going back to a show that works. Tom Krasniqi will
host an hour from 6 to 7 a.m., then be joined by Mike Pepper from 7
to 9 a.m.
</P>
<P>
Best feature
</P>
<P>
Any time anyone wants to question whether ESPN will go after a
league partner, it should watch Sunday's Outside the Lines piece on
Broncos wide receiver Brandon Marshall, a former UCF standout and
Pro Bowl player. OTL detailed seven cases of alleged domestic
violence involving Marshall and an ex-girlfriend. John Barr's solid
piece certainly did not portray the NFL in a positive light,
especially after it reminded viewers that the NFL reduced a
Marshall suspension from three games to one because of his
off-field conduct. The piece was followed by OTL host Bob Ley
interviewing Marshall via satellite. Marshall said he never "laid
his hands" on his former girlfriend. Ley did his best to ask the
tough questions, but this is one case where it might have been
better to be in the same room with Marshall instead of interviewing
him via satellite. Perhaps ESPN had no choice, but it made Ley's
job much tougher.
</P>
<P>
Three things that popped into my head
</P>
<P>
1. I love listening to TNT's Marv Albert call a big NBA game.
</P>
<P>
2. They take a lot of criticism, but the NHL referees have done
a good job in these playoffs, much better than the NBA officials
have.
</P>
<P>
3. Is it me, or does it seem like MLB umpires have really
narrowed their strike zones this season?
</P>
<P>
Worst performance
</P>
<P>
Not only did the Cavaliers' LeBron James have his worst game of
the NBA's Eastern Conference final Saturday with 25 points on
8-for-20 shooting, but James had an embarrassing performance
afterward by refusing to meet with the media. If you want to be the
superstar, if you want the commercials and big contracts, if you
want to be considered "the man," you have to talk after the game.
</P>
<P>
You think Michael Jordan would have done that? You think the
Penguins' Sidney Crosby or the Red Wings' Nick Lidstrom will do
that after the Stanley Cup final?
</P>
<P>
Most intriguing question
</P>
<P>
So after another disappointing exit from the postseason, will
LeBron James stay in Cleveland when his contract runs out after
next season, or will he opt for free agency and a place such as New
York? TNT's Reggie Miller asked that question Saturday when the
Cavs were seconds from being bounced by the Magic. "Me, being a
guy in a small market for 18 years in Indiana, I think it would be
fabulous if he stayed in Cleveland," Miller said. "I think it's
great for the game to have superstars in small markets."
</P>
<P>
Best prediction
</P>
<P>
Not only is TNT basketball analyst Charles Barkley entertaining,
he knows his stuff, too. It needs to be pointed out that he was one
of the few people who picked the Magic to beat the Cavaliers in the
Eastern Conference final. "The best team won this series,"
Barkley said after Orlando won Saturday night. "Orlando is the
better team.  Cleveland was the fourth-best team left in the
playoffs." Worst performance
</P>
<P>
Not only did the Cavaliers' LeBron James have his worst game of
the NBA's Eastern Conference final Saturday with 25 points on
8-for-20 shooting, but James had an embarrassing performance
afterward by refusing to meet with the media. If you want to be the
superstar, if you want the commercials and big contracts, if you
want to be considered "the man," you have to talk after the game.
</P>
<P>
You think Michael Jordan would have done that? You think the
Penguins' Sidney Crosby or the Red Wings' Nick Lidstrom will do
that after the Stanley Cup final?
</P>
<P>
Most intriguing question
</P>
<P>
So after another disappointing exit from the postseason, will
LeBron James stay in Cleveland when his contract runs out after
next season, or will he opt for free agency and a place such as New
York? TNT's Reggie Miller asked that question Saturday when the
Cavs were seconds from being bounced by the Magic. "Me, being a
guy in a small market for 18 years in Indiana, I think it would be
fabulous if he stayed in Cleveland," Miller said. "I think it's
great for the game to have superstars in small markets."
</P>
<P>
Best prediction
</P>
<P>
Not only is TNT basketball analyst Charles Barkley entertaining,
he knows his stuff, too. It needs to be pointed out that he was one
of the few people who picked the Magic to beat the Cavaliers in the
Eastern Conference final. "The best team won this series,"
Barkley said after Orlando won Saturday night. "Orlando is the
better team.  Cleveland was the fourth-best team left in the
playoffs."
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0007" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
NO BEEF OVER CHAIN ' S SUCCESS
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Nick Vojnovic , 59, is president of Beef 'O' Brady's, a
Brandon-born chain that grew to 270 locations in 24 states. Beef's
has a reputation for middle-of-the-road pub food (80 million
chicken wings served annually), but with 52 locations in the Tampa
Bay area, it unquestionably reflects local tastes. Brandon sports
eight Beefs and only seven McDonald's. Even Brooksville claims
three. Vojnovic hails from a family of Yugoslavian restaurateurs
whose immigrant mother did not want her kids in food service.
Vojnovic got a hotel management degree from Cornell ("because
their graduates all got jobs") that led him to consultant and
executive-level roles at Chili's, Applebee's and Famous Dave's, a
170-store barbecue chain. His brothers ignored Mom's advice too:
One is a restaurant broker, the other a vice president at Popeye's.
</P>
<P>
There is, of course, no Beef 'O' Brady. What's the story?
</P>
<P>
Jim Mellody , who founded the chain in a onetime Brandon deli,
kind of backed into creating a family sports pub. He started a
steakhouse in 1985, but that didn't work. He had a sign that said
"beef," so he just added his mother's maiden name to get Beef 'O'
Brady's.
</P>
<P>
Your bosses, Chuck Winship and Gene Knippers , once held a
multistate Chili's franchise in a partnership with Tampa
restaurateurs Chris Sullivan and Bob Basham . When Sullivan and
Basham sold their interest to Chili's parent company, they started
the Outback Steakhouse chain. When Winship and Knippers sold to
Chili's, they acquired Beef's and hired you as franchise
development director. What was that like?
</P>
<P>
We only had four people at headquarters when I started. The
franchisees were on handshake deals, so we installed a formal
structure. I was jack-of-all-trades. I would sell a franchise, help
pick the real estate, train the owners and help them open. Chuck
and Gene let me add someone at headquarters for every new franchise
sold. Today we have 270 stores and 40 people at headquarters in
Tampa. And 17 stores are run by the children of the first owner.
</P>
<P>
The economy has hurt all sit-down casual dining chains. Sales in
your average mature store slipped by 10 percent to $886,000 between
2006 and 2008  not quite as bad a decline as your peer group.
You've closed about 18 stores in that period, about twice the
national average. How did you react to that?
</P>
<P>
There is no bank financing for new stores. So we turned on a
dime about six months ago. We're seeking alternative sites that
cost a fraction as much to get in business. We're putting Beefs in
empty spaces like an Applebee's in Bangor, Maine. We're trying to
get in airports and college student unions, like our store in the
Marshall Center at USF. And we've opened two test stores in hotel
restaurants that can be converted for about $100,000. The return on
investment is as quick as a year. The first hotels are a Best
Western in Brandon and the TradeWinds Island Beach Resort in St.
Pete Beach. At the Best Western, 60 percent of the hotel guests now
dine on property vs. a hotel national average of 5 percent.
</P>
<P>
What about the menu?
</P>
<P>
Jim Mellody's chicken wing recipe has served us well. We now
have a steak burger made from trimmings from one of the big steak
house chains that I would put up against anybody's burger. But our
menu needs more wows that make us stand out without adding to the
complexity of a three-person kitchen. We need to showcase our
healthy foods better. We used smaller portions to get some items
down to $4.99. We're filling the gaps around our menu of finger
food. We're testing breakfast items and dinner entrees. We added
liquor in 80 stores after research found women customers wanted a
margarita, daiquiri or mojito. We just have to be careful to
discourage selling shots.
</P>
<P>
The economy also turned as you were about to take Beef's menu to
the next level. You dropped plans to hire a corporate chef in 2008
in favor of more field supervisors to help franchisees cope with
tough times. How do you develop the menu?
</P>
<P>
We bring in 11 franchisees monthly and look for ideas. Vendors
bring in chefs who work with us. It's a balance. Some franchisees
don't want to change a thing. Some think we should be more cutting
edge and create more sides from scratch.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0008" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
LOOKING SMARTER 10 YEARS LATER
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Times Sports Columnist

      ST. PETERSBURG
      Josh Beckett or Josh Hamilton?
</P>
<P>
Once, it was the only question that mattered in Tampa Bay. Two
phenomenal talents, and one chance for the Devil Rays to get it
right. Should they draft the smart-aleck pitcher from Texas, or the
gee-whiz outfielder from North Carolina?
</P>
<P>
Ten years later, it is obvious Tampa Bay put its faith in the
wrong player.
</P>
<P>
But 10 years from now, will that still be true?
</P>
<P>
On the outside, he was noncommittal. Secretly, general manager
Chuck LaMar was leaning toward Beckett.
</P>
<P>
This was early in the process, long before a decision would have
to be made. LaMar wanted to keep it to himself because he did not
want anyone else in the organization to be influenced by what the
boss was thinking.
</P>
<P>
But Beckett had grown up in the Houston suburb of Spring, Texas,
not far from where LaMar's career had begun. So a familiarity was
there. Maybe even an affection. LaMar still knew a lot of the
locals, and they assured him the right-hander was another Kerry
Wood. Maybe even better. They were saying he was a first-round
talent by the time his high school sophomore season had ended. Not
a future first-rounder. Right then. As a sophomore. He was that
good.
</P>
<P>
"Going into that draft, I think Beckett was the guy everyone
was looking at for the No.??1 pick," said R.J. Harrison, then a
national scout and now the Rays' scouting director. "It was going
to be the job of someone else to knock him off the top of the hill.
</P>
<P>
"And Josh Hamilton basically did."
</P>
<P>
The kid was milk and cookies. Like he had stepped off the screen
of a 1950s sitcom.
</P>
<P>
Josh Hamilton was a Sir and Ma'am kind of student. Big grin, big
hands and, my goodness, big talent. He could hit, he could run, he
could throw. If he had never picked up a bat, Hamilton would have
been a first-round pick as a pitcher.
</P>
<P>
As it was, by the time summer rolled around in 1999, people were
talking about Hamilton as a generational type of talent. As good as
Alex Rodriguez in 1993 or Ken Griffey in '87. And, on top of it
all, he was a mother's dream.
</P>
<P>
"This kid was not only a baseball player in every sense but he
carried himself extremely well," said LaMar, now an assistant GM
with the Phillies. "When you're making this kind of investment,
you do the background check. And it showed he was anything but a
problem. There was no hint you would ever have a problem with
him."
</P>
<P>
Beckett, on the other hand, was different. Not a bad kid, just
different.
</P>
<P>
He was cocky to the point of arrogant. He had no trouble
explaining how good he was, and was not shy about tossing his name
around with Roger Clemens or Nolan Ryan or any other hard-throwing
Texan.
</P>
<P>
For years, the word around the Rays' offices was that owner
Vince Naimoli was turned off by Beckett's attitude during a home
visit. The teenager slouched on the couch and acted as if he would
be doing the Rays a favor by allowing them to make him a
millionaire.
</P>
<P>
LaMar insists that account is not true. Nevertheless, a decision
had been made.
</P>
<P>
On this day, 10 years ago, LaMar visited the Hamilton home in
Raleigh. It was the eve of the draft, and he told them he would be
calling 10 a.m. the next day and asking Josh if he wanted to be a
Tampa Bay Devil Ray.
</P>
<P>
You probably know the rest.
</P>
<P>
Beckett was the second pick of the draft and was in the big
leagues two years later. At 23, he won the clinching game of the
2003 World Series for the Marlins. Four years later, he won another
World Series with the Red Sox.
</P>
<P>
As for Hamilton, his career nearly ended before it began. He
hurt his back in an auto accident in the spring of 2001 and later
developed a cocaine addiction. He eventually missed three full
seasons to suspensions and drug abuse. He was plucked off the Rays'
roster by the Reds in the winter of 2006 and didn't reach the big
leagues until nearly eight years after he was drafted.
</P>
<P>
But the thing is, their stories are not over.
</P>
<P>
Beckett has fought his share of minor injuries and has not been
a dominant pitcher for a couple of seasons. Hamilton, meanwhile,
emerged last year as one of the most exciting players in the big
leagues.
</P>
<P>
"I took a lot of heat for a long time because Josh Beckett
turned out to be what we all thought he would be," LaMar said.
"People ask me if I feel vindicated now that Josh Hamilton is an
All-Star. Not at all. I just feel truly happy for Josh and his
family.
</P>
<P>
"You spend a lot of time on the road in this business. A lot of
time away from your family in hotels and airports, just hoping to
get a chance to see a player like Josh Hamilton. To see him on a
baseball field at 18 could literally take your breath away. His
talent was staggering, and I'm glad the world is getting a chance
to see that now."
</P>
<P>
Josh Beckett or Josh Hamilton? For the past 10 years, the answer
should have been Beckett. For the next 10 years, I'm not so sure.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0009" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
NEW FOCUS: DEADLY STORM SURGES
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As Hurricane Ike loomed off Texas in September, thousands along
the coast decided to stay put. It was only a Category 2 storm,
probably not enough to blow off roofs or break windows, they
assumed.
</P>
<P>
But Ike created a storm surge of up to 18 feet, enough to take
down large granite buildings and concrete fuel tanks, and wash away
3,800 homes.
</P>
<P>
The water rose gradually, but the streets flooded before those
hunkering down could flee. Texas emergency officials risked their
lives to rescue more than 600 people trapped in the rushing water.
They couldn't save a woman who tied herself to a bridge that
failed, along with about 20 others killed by Ike.
</P>
<P>
"Make no mistake," said John Simsen, Galveston County's
emergency management coordinator, "the power of a wall of water is
devastating. You just can't imagine it until you live it."
</P>
<P>
The experience has prompted the National Hurricane Center to put
more emphasis on storm surge this hurricane season, which starts
today and ends Nov. 30. Too many people in Texas didn't realize how
deadly and destructive storm surge could be.
</P>
<P>
The same scenario could easily happen in the Tampa Bay area,
Simsen warned. In fact, it could be worse.
</P>
<P>
Storm surge is the single greatest hurricane threat facing Tampa
Bay, emergency officials say.
</P>
<P>
"Seems like I remember you guys have a hospital right near the
water, right?" Simsen said, referring to Tampa General Hospital.
"Yeah  that's not good."
</P>
<P>
Emergency officials have long used the battle cry "run from the
water, hide from the wind" to drive home dire warnings of storm
surge.
</P>
<P>
Too many people still don't get it.
</P>
<P>
Many have become conditioned, and at times comforted, by the
Saffir-Simpson Hurricane Scale, which predicts potential damage
based on wind levels. Emergency officials have devised charts
showing shingles blowing off roofs and palm trees bending as winds
increase.
</P>
<P>
But that's not enough, hurricane experts now say. People need to
worry about storm surge first, storm category second  especially in
the Tampa Bay area, which hasn't had a direct hit by a hurricane
since 1921.
</P>
<P>
So this year, the National Hurricane Center is removing all
storm surge and flooding values from its Saffir-Simpson scale.
Researchers are working to create a separate storm surge warning
that's easy for the public to digest.
</P>
<P>
Forecasters will start using words like "inundation" and
"probabilistic storm surge" in their advisories.
</P>
<P>
All you really need to know, said Hillsborough County emergency
management director Larry Gispert, is that if a hurricane comes
here, "we're all going to be in the same bathtub."
</P>
<P>
Like Galveston, much of the Tampa Bay area is surrounded by a
low continental shelf. That's why you can go to the beach and walk
out into the water for quite a ways before your head is underwater.
</P>
<P>
That kind of shallow graduation makes it a lot easier for gulf
waters to slosh right up onto land  and over homes, cars,
buildings, highways, animals and people. Experts predict that a
worst-case scenario  a Category 5 storm with a large radius, slowly
moving south to north and hitting landfall somewhere between north
Pinellas and Pasco counties  could create up to 30 feet of storm
surge.
</P>
<P>
In that scenario, throw out everything you've always thought
about flood zones and elevation levels. It's not just the beach and
coastal areas that would disappear.
</P>
<P>
Miles of homes and businesses would be washed away, said
Pinellas County emergency management's Tom Iovino. Areas such as
Oldsmar, Snell Isle, downtown St. Petersburg, Ybor City and all of
South Tampa would be underwater.
</P>
<P>
Even those areas not generally prone to flooding could get
"inundation," National Hurricane Center spokesman Dennis Feltgen
said. That word will be used a lot in hurricane advisories and will
help people understand exactly how much water they'll get in their
neighborhood if and when a storm makes landfall.
</P>
<P>
For example, if a 20-foot storm surge is predicted and your
home's elevation is 11 feet above sea level, you will get 9 feet of
water inundation.
</P>
<P>
Hurricane Center officials are also working on a special storm
surge warning that will complement the Saffir-Simpson scale. It's
being developed and tested, and could be implemented in the next
few years, Feltgen said.
</P>
<P>
Gispert and other local emergency officials hope the added
emphasis on storm surge, rather than storm category, will change
attitudes. Hurricanes like Ike and Katrina have already helped
publicize the dangers of water vs. wind.
</P>
<P>
Those who have lived through it, like Galveston's Simsen, are
happy to share their stories and advice.
</P>
<P>
"Pay no attention to storm category," he said. "Leave, and
leave early."
</P>
<P>
But he knows something scary about the Tampa Bay area, or
anywhere else that faces a hurricane threat this season.
</P>
<P>
Some people still won't leave.
</P>
<P>
Emily Nipps can be reached at nippssptimes.com or (727)
893-8452.
</P>
<P>
The "new" Saffir-Simpson wind scale:
</P>
<P>
This season, the National Hurricane Center is removing all
mention of storm surge from the old Saffir-Simpson Hurricane Scale
models. The new scale will focus exclusively on wind damage and
forecasters will estimate storm surge separately, rather than
attach storm surge values to the storm's predicted intensity. Here
are the five categories of hurricanes:
</P>
<P>
Category 1: Sustained winds of 74 to 95 mph. Some damage could
occur to buildings, poorly constructed signs, trees.
</P>
<P>
Category 2: Sustained winds of 96 to 110 mph. Some roofing
material, door and window damage of buildings will occur.
Considerable damage to mobile homes (mainly pre-1994 construction)
and power lines.
</P>
<P>
Category 3: Sustained winds of 111 to 130 mph. Some damage to
houses and buildings will occur with a minor amount of wall
failures. Near total power loss with outages that could last from
several days to weeks.
</P>
<P>
Category 4: Sustained winds of 131 to 155 mph. Damage to
windows, doors and roofs. Windborne debris will cause extensive
damage, and people struck by debris could be injured or killed.
Most trees will be snapped or uprooted.
</P>
<P>
Category 5: Sustained winds greater than 155 mph. Complete roof
failure on many homes and industrial buildings will occur. Small
buildings could be blown over or away. Power outages will last for
weeks to possibly months.
</P>
<P>
Worst case scenario:
</P>
<P>
To see what would happen if a Category 4 hurricane hit the Tampa
Bay area, go to links.tampabay.com.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0010" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
A PROTEST DEFENDING THE BLUEFIN AT TRENDY NOBU
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
To its admirers, buttery, succulent bluefin tuna has
no peer in the sushi world, which may be why those fans do not mind
spending as much as $14 for a single bite of it.
</P>
<P>
But some environmentalists say that passion for bluefin may
cause it to be overfished to the brink of extinction. Those people
are demanding that sushi restaurants stop serving bluefin -- to save
it.
</P>
<P>
On Saturday night, about a dozen members of the environmental
group Greenpeace pressed that point at the upscale Japanese fusion
restaurant Nobu in TriBeCa, with an elaborate if restrained
demonstration in the dining room.
</P>
<P>
Dressed in blazers and billowy dresses like any other patrons on
a weekend night, the demonstrators, who had reservations, carried
fake menus with endangered-species dishes, like "Rack of Mountain
Gorilla Seasoned with Powdered Rhino Horn" ($32).
</P>
<P>
The menus, printed in a font similar to that used by Nobu, were
meant to be slipped among those used by the wait staff, so servers
might unknowingly hand them to diners.
</P>
<P>
Greenpeace members also came with look-alike business cards
bearing the slogan "Specializing in endangered species," which
were to be substituted for the stack on the hostess stand.
</P>
<P>
But the protesters who were asked to leave on Saturday did so
without a fuss. They even tipped the wait staff, they said.
</P>
<P>
The plan hit a snag early on when Casson Trenor, an organizer,
was asked to leave soon after sitting down, when a restaurant
worker spotted the fake menus, Trenor said. Still, other Greenpeace
volunteers who managed to stay undercover for more than an hour
inside plastered a few fake menus on the back of the rest room
doors, said Eva Erbskorn, another organizer, who tried to challenge
her waiter about the bluefin's fate.
</P>
<P>
"But he kept saying 'no comment,"' Erbskorn said afterward.
</P>
<P>
For all the propaganda smuggled into Nobu, few of the patrons
seemed to have noticed it.
</P>
<P>
Joe McCarton, of Oyster Bay, N.Y., said he ordered the bluefin,
as he had many times previously. In fact, he said, all the
questions about it were making him hungry again.
</P>
<P>
"I might go and get another order," he joked. "It was just
great."
</P>
<P>
But Greenpeace, which recently made headlines in London by
testing fish samples at three Nobu restaurants, confirming that
they were bluefin when the restaurants were vague on that point,
might have been heartened by the response on Saturday from Dr. Jane
Brownell, of Omaha, Neb., a Nobu patron who decided not to order
the bluefin based on news stories about it.
</P>
<P>
"I didn't order it out of concern," she said. "I don't want
to eat an endangered fish."
</P>
<P>
Currently, bluefin is not on either the federal
endangered-species list or a global version put out by the
Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild
Fauna and Flora.
</P>
<P>
Still, even if Greenpeace's message did not persuade diners to
ask for their money back, Trenor called the event a success. "I
can't imagine that one of these menus won't find its way up the
food chain," he said.
</P>
<P>
Nobu, which opened in 1994 in TriBeCa and has 24 restaurants
worldwide, says that it is aware of bluefin's depleted numbers but
that it is still on the menu because it is so popular with Japanese
patrons.
</P>
<P>
In 2008, bowing to pressure from Greenpeace, Nobu added a line
at the bottom of its menu stating that bluefin is "environmentally
challenged" and suggested that concerned diners ask their server
for alternatives, like bigeye tuna, said Ming Dhanasarnsilp, a
spokeswoman.
</P>
<P>
Nobu is also considering permanently substituting farm-raised
kindai tuna, from Australia, for bluefin, she added.
</P>
<P>
Dhanasarnsilp said the restaurant would do away with the item
altogether if the U.S. government banned the fish. "We want to
protect the oceans, too," she said. But she criticized
Greenpeace's tactics on Saturday.
</P>
<P>
"They were disruptive to our guests, so I didn't appreciate
it," she said.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="NYT_ENG_20090601.0011" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
AFTER-HUBBLE-STP
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Scoping out space Kepler Mission Launched: March 2009 Cost: $520 million. Claim to fame: It will search the skies for distant planets, especially Earth-sized planets thought to be capable of supporting life. Astronomers have currently found more than 300 planets outside our solar system, but none has a size or orbit similar to Earth's. Factoid: Kepler looks for tiny changes in a star's brightness to see if planets are crossing in front of it. James Webb Space Telescope Launched: Scheduled for 2014 Cost: $4.4 billion Claim to fame: Billed as NASA's successor to Hubble, the Webb will search for some of the first galaxies ever formed and examine the atmospheres of planets outside the solar system. The telescope uses infrared light to see objects even farther away than a telescope that uses visible light.telescopes in space. Curtis Krueger,
</P>
<P>
Kepler Mission
</P>
<P>
Launched: March 2009
</P>
<P>
Cost: $520 million.
</P>
<P>
Claim to fame: It will search the skies for distant planets,
especially Earth-sized planets thought to be capable of supporting
life. Astronomers have currently found more than 300 planets
outside our solar system, but none has a size or orbit similar to
Earth's.
</P>
<P>
Factoid: Kepler looks for tiny changes in a star's brightness to
see if planets are crossing in front of it.
</P>
<P>
James Webb Space Telescope
</P>
<P>
Launched: Scheduled for 2014
</P>
<P>
Cost: $4.4 billion
</P>
<P>
Claim to fame: Billed as NASA's successor to Hubble, the Webb
will search for some of the first galaxies ever formed and examine
the atmospheres of planets outside the solar system. The telescope
uses infrared light to see objects even farther away than a
telescope that uses visible light.
</P>
<P>
Factoid: It will orbit more than 1 million miles away from
Earth, in a position called the second Lagrange point.
</P>
<P>
Herschel Space Telescope
</P>
<P>
Launched: May 2009
</P>
<P>
Cost: $1-5 billion (including some operational costs)
</P>
<P>
Claim to fame: Like the coming Webb telescope, this European
Space Agency telescope seeks to use infrared to look at the
earliest galaxies in the universe. It will also look at clouds and
dust where new stars form.
</P>
<P>
Factoid: The mirror on the telescope is billed as the largest
ever launched. It's headed to the second Lagrange point in the
Earth-sun system.
</P>
<P>
Chandra X-ray Observatory
</P>
<P>
Launched: July 1999
</P>
<P>
Cost: $1.5 billion
</P>
<P>
Claim to fame: It looks at the X-rays emitted from exploding
stars, the matter around black holes and other locations.
</P>
<P>
Factoid: It has studied a massive black hole in the center of
the Milky Way galaxy.
</P>
<P>
Fermi Gamma-ray Space Telescope
</P>
<P>
Launched: June 2008
</P>
<P>
Cost: $510 million
</P>
<P>
Claim to fame: It searches for powerful gamma rays that burst
out from supermassive black holes, merging neutron stars and other
sources.
</P>
<P>
Factoid: High-energy gamma rays pass right through mirrors and
lenses, so conventional telescopes would not see them. A different
technology is used.
</P>
<P>
Hubble Space Telescope
      Launched: April 1990
</P>
<P>
Cost: $1.5 billion
</P>
<P>
Claim to fame: Hubble has taken sparklingly clear images of
distant galaxies and helped scientists discover the unseen force
known as "dark energy." It has taken "deep field" pictures
showing thousands of galaxies in small portions of the sky.
</P>
<P>
Factoid: After this last and final repair mission, Hubble will
probably be allowed to fall back to Earth within a decade.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0001" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
Erectile Dysfunction Linked to Sleep Disorder
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
By Simeon Bennett
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1103ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Erection problems are more common among men with a disorder that causes
sufferers to have an irresistible urge to move their legs than those without the
condition, a Harvard Medical School study found.
</P>
<P>
Erectile dysfunction was 78 percent more likely in men with symptoms of restless
legs syndrome than those without them, and was most common in sufferers with the
most severe symptoms, the researchers said Friday in the journal Sleep. It's
likely both disorders are caused by a common mechanism, they said.
</P>
<P>
The study is the first to probe the connection between erectile dysfunction and
restless legs syndrome, or RLS, two conditions that have been linked to
abnormally low levels of dopamine, a chemical that relays signals in the brain.
RLS, a brain disorder that afflicts about 10 percent of Americans, can cause
problems falling or staying asleep, according to the Rochester, Minn.-based
Restless Legs Syndrome Foundation.
</P>
<P>
"This finding indirectly supports a role of dopamine" in restless legs syndrome,
Xiang Gao, a research scientist at the Boston-based Harvard School of Public
Health, said in the study. More research is needed to clarify the relationship
between the disorder and erection problems, and explore the biological
mechanisms of the association, he said.
</P>
<P>
Erectile dysfunction affects as many as 30 million men in the U.S., according to
the National Institutes of Health, which funded the study.
</P>
<P>
Gao and colleagues studied data from 23,119 men between 56 and 91 years old.
About 4 percent had restless legs syndrome and 41 percent had erectile
dysfunction. Those who had symptoms of RLS between 5 and 14 times a month were
16 percent more likely to have erectile dysfunction. The men with symptoms
occurring more than 15 times a month were 78 percent more likely to have the
condition, the study showed.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0002" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
Teen Suicidal Thoughts May Be Linked to Late Nights, Study Says
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
By Simeon Bennett
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1120ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Late nights may make teenagers more prone to depression and suicidal thoughts by
depriving them of sleep, according to a study by researchers at Columbia
University.
</P>
<P>
Teens whose parents let them go to bed past midnight were 24 percent more likely
to be depressed and 20 percent more likely to have contemplated suicide than
peers whose parents set bedtimes at or before 10 p.m., the researchers said
today in the journal Sleep. Earlier set bedtimes may be protective because they
increase the likelihood of getting enough sleep, they said.
</P>
<P>
The study is the first to show that sleep deprivation may cause depression and
suicidal thoughts in adolescents. Previous research has shown a link, though the
relationship wasn't clear because insomnia can be a symptom of depression.
</P>
<P>
"Our results strengthen the argument that lack of sleep can cause depression as
opposed to simply being a symptom of depression," James Gangwisch, the study's
lead author and an assistant professor at the university's medical center, said
in an e-mail. "Adequate quality sleep could therefore be a preventative measure
against depression and a treatment for depression."
</P>
<P>
About 4,400 Americans between the ages of 10 and 24 commit suicide each year,
making it the third-most common cause of death in the age group, according to
the Atlanta-based Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.
</P>
<P>
Gangwisch and colleagues studied data from 15,659 U.S. students, who were in
grades seven to 12 between 1994 and 1996, and their parents. Seven percent of
the teens were found to have depression and 13 percent said they seriously
contemplated suicide during the preceding 12 months. The association was
stronger for girls and older children, according to the study.
</P>
<P>
Teenagers whose parents said they should go to bed at 10 p.m. or earlier slept
for 8 hours 10 minutes on average, 40 minutes more than those with bedtimes set
at midnight or later, the researchers found. That's less than the nine or more
hours of sleep for adolescents recommended by the American Academy of Sleep
Medicine, a joint publisher of the journal.
</P>
<P>
Those who typically slept for five hours or less each night were 71 percent more
likely to have depression and 48 percent more likely to have thought about
taking their own lives than those who got eight hours of sleep, according to the
study funded by Columbia University.
</P>
<P>
Lack of sleep may affect brain responses to negative stimuli, hinder a person's
ability to cope with stress and impair relationships with peers and adults, the
researchers said. It may also affect judgment, concentration and impulse
control.
</P>
<P>
Almost 70 percent of teenagers reported going to bed at the time set by their
parents, and two-thirds of the rest said they usually went to bed within an hour
after the limit, the study found. More than half of parents surveyed said they
sent their children to bed by 10 p.m. or earlier on weeknights, and 25 percent
said they allowed their kids to stay up until midnight or later.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0003" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
Group Slams Chertoff on Scanners
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
WASHINGTON
By Kimberly Kindy
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1126ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Since the attempted bombing of a U.S. airliner on Christmas Day, former Homeland
Security secretary Michael Chertoff has given dozens of media interviews touting
the need for the federal government to buy more full-body scanners for airports.
</P>
<P>
What he has made little mention of is that the Chertoff Group, his security
consulting agency, includes a client that manufactures the machines. Chertoff
disclosed the relationship on a CNN program Wednesday, in response to a
question.
</P>
<P>
An airport passengers' rights group on Thursday criticized Chertoff's use of his
former government credentials to advocate for a product that benefits his
clients.
</P>
<P>
"Mr. Chertoff should not be allowed to abuse the trust the public has placed in
him as a former public servant to privately gain from the sale of full-body
scanners under the pretense that the scanners would have detected this
particular type of explosive," said Kate Hanni, founder of FlyersRights.org,
which opposes the use of the scanners.
</P>
<P>
Chertoff's advocacy for the technology dates back to his time in the Bush
administration In 2005, Homeland Security ordered the government's first batch
of the scanners _ five from California-based Rapiscan Systems.
</P>
<P>
Rapiscan is one of only two companies that make full-body scanners in accordance
with current contract specifications required by the federal government.
</P>
<P>
Currently 40 body scanners are in use among 19 U.S. airports. The number is
expected to skyrocket, at least in part because of the Christmas Day incident.
The Transportation Security Administration has said it will order another 300
machines.
</P>
<P>
In the summer, TSA purchased another 150 machines from Rapiscan with $25 million
in American Recovery and Reinvestment Act funds. Rapiscan was the only company
that qualified for the contract because it had developed technology that
performs the screening using a less-graphic body imaging system, which is also
less controversial. (Since then, another company, L-3 Communications, has
qualified for future contracts, , but no new contracts have been awarded.)
</P>
<P>
Over the past week, Chertoff has repeatedly talked about the need for expanding
the use of the technology in airports, saying it could detect bombs like the one
federal authorities say Umar Farouk Abdulmutallab, a 23-year-old Nigerian,
carried onto the Detroit-bound aircraft.
</P>
<P>
"We could deploy the scanning machines that we currently are beginning to deploy
in the U.S. that will give us the ability to see what someone has concealed
underneath their clothing," Chertoff said Wednesday in an interview on CNN The
incident on the Detroit-bound plane provided "a very vivid lesson in the value
of that machinery," he said.
</P>
<P>
Researcher Julie Tate contributed to this report.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0004" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
Economist, IMF Historian deVries Dead at 87
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
WASHINGTON
By Patricia Sullivan
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1138ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Margaret Garritsen deVries, an economist and historian at the International
Monetary Fund, died of pneumonia Dec. 18. She was 87.
</P>
<P>
DeVries was among the first employees hired by the IMF, joining it as an
economist in 1946. She represented the agency on missions to Mexico, Thailand,
India, Sri Lanka, Burma, Turkey, Israel, Yugoslavia, Costa Rica and Nicaragua.
</P>
<P>
She was appointed assistant chief of the multiple exchange rate division in 1953
and chief of the Far East division in 1957. She resigned in 1959 to care for her
two young children, but she rejoined the IMF in 1963 to help write the history
of the agency's first 20 years. In 1973, she was appointed the IMF's official
historian, a post she held until retiring in 1987.
</P>
<P>
She wrote a number of books, including "International Monetary Fund , 1966-71,"
(two volumes), "International Monetary Fund, 1972-1978" (three volumes),
"Balance of Payments Adjustment, 1945 to 1986: The IMF Experience" and "The IMF
in a Changing World, 1945-85." She also co-wrote "The International Monetary
Fund, 1945-1965" (three volumes) and "Foreign Economic Problems of the United
States."
</P>
<P>
DeVries taught economics at George Washington University in the late 1940s and
early 1960s. She continued to write in retirement, including a regular column in
the IMF retirees' association newsletter.
</P>
<P>
Margaret Garritsen was born in Detroit and graduated from the University of
Michigan as an American Association of University Women scholar, and she was
elected to Phi Beta Kappa. She received a doctorate in economics from the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1946.
</P>
<P>
She was named Outstanding Washington Woman Economist by Washington Women
Economists in 1987, and she received the 2003 Carolyn Shaw Bell Award of the
American Economics Association. Survivors include her husband of 57 years,
Barend deVries, and two children.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0005" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
NIH Stimulus Money Adds Jobs, Research
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
NEW YORK
By Meg Tirrell
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1146ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
National Institutes of Health has created or saved 50,000 jobs with its $10
billion in federal stimulus funds, boosting medical research and returning $2.25
on the dollar in goods and services, the agency's director Francis Collins said.
</P>
<P>
Collins, appointed by President Barack Obama in August, said the NIH aims to
accelerate drug development, promote research on rare, neglected diseases and
cut health-care costs. In a Dec. 30 interview, he outlined areas for investment
and research released in an article in the jornal Science.
</P>
<P>
Science is an important investment in the economy's recovery as budgeting
decisions are being made for the 2011 fiscal year, Collins said. The 50,000 jobs
the agency created in the first year with stimulus money "are high-paying,
quality jobs that are employing people with considerable skills that we'd hate
to see migrating overseas."
</P>
<P>
"After five years of flat funding between 2003 and 2008, where NIH effectively
lost about 15 percent of its buying power, the community has been exhilarated,"
Collins said. "We're going to see acceleration in both the basic and the
clinical aspects of biomedical research."
</P>
<P>
The agency is investing $400 million of stimulus money in studies comparing the
efficacy of treatments for ailments including dementia, gastro-esophageal reflux
disease, or GERD, and the staph infection MRSA, according to the agency's Web
site. MRSA, or methicillin-resistant staphylococcus aureas, has become
increasingly resistant to standard treatments and affects about 2 million
Americans. Germs such as MRSA cost about $20 billion annually to treat,
according to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.
</P>
<P>
Comparative effectiveness studies can help lower health- care costs and benefit
patients by identifying the best treatments with the fewest side effects.
</P>
<P>
Previous such studies have shown that exercise and life-style changes prevent
the onset of diabetes better than medication, and that older, less expensive
antipsychotics work as well as newer drugs, with fewer side effects, Collins
wrote in his article.
</P>
<P>
The NIH also plans to start a grant program encouraging development of new
models for health economics, Collins said. Incentives for doctors should be
based on patient outcomes rather than the number of tests or procedures
performed, he said.
</P>
<P>
"Our health-care system is currently loaded with incentives that may be counter
to cost savings," Collins said. "We would like to perhaps study that more
carefully in a research environment."
</P>
<P>
In a frenzy to access the stimulus funds, researchers submitted thousands of
grant applications, with some institutions such as the University of California
in Irvine preparing more than 200, according to an April article in Science. Not
all applicants concluded the program would help boost the economy.
</P>
<P>
"I am one of the 21,000 applicants for the NIH Challenge Grant, which will fund
roughly 200 grants at a success rate of 1 percent," Sailen Barik, of the
University of South Alabama College of Medicine in Mobile, wrote in a July 7
letter to Science. "This unprecedented low rate makes me wonder whether this
feeding frenzy is actually stimulating American recovery."
</P>
<P>
Barik wasn't immediately available for comment.
</P>
<P>
The U.S. has a responsibility to use its resources to help solve some health
problems in developing areas of the world, going beyond the "big three" of AIDS,
tuberculosis and malaria, Collins said.
</P>
<P>
Some diseases are rare or affect patients in areas with few resources, making
them unappealing to drug companies that need cover the cost of research through
revenue, Collins said. The NIH plans to forge more partnerships with drugmakers
in which academic investigators perform initial studies. That may help remove
some of the risk of drug development so companies can enter in the later stages
and take a more mature treatment through human trials.
</P>
<P>
Collins cited as a candidate for this model a treatment for a disease called
schistosomiasis, found primarily in sub-Saharan Africa and the Middle East,
that's carried by water snails and affects about 250 million people. Parasites
on the snails can transfer to humans and cause damage to the liver, intestines,
lungs and bladder, according to the CDC.
</P>
<P>
"There hasn't been a new drug for this in 50 years," Collins said. "Through
academic efforts, as a consequence of NIH investing in the front-end of the drug
development pipeline, a very promising compound has emerged that cures this
disease in the mouse model, and can now be moved toward the clinical trial
potential."
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0006" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
Bidder for Volvo Doesn't Want to Emulate Toyota
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
By William Mellor
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1157ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In a sprawling factory south of Shanghai, Li Shufu, the self-made Chinese
billionaire who is poised to buy Volvo Car Corp. from Ford Motor Co., is
presiding over a new-model launch party. If he has any concerns that his Geely
Automobile Holdings rising sales and surging stock price could falter, he's not
showing them on that summer day.
</P>
<P>
Geely, the publicly traded automaker that Goldman Sachs Group Inc. is backing to
the tune of $334 million, is unveiling its first homegrown model specifically
designed for Western markets, Bloomberg Markets reported in its February 2010
issue.
</P>
<P>
The gleaming-white four-door compact, which retails for $11,700 to $17,600 in
China, is called the Emgrand, a name made up to conjure grandeur.
</P>
<P>
To the strains of the company song, willowy models in split- to-the-thigh
cheongsams pin bouquets on pudgy Communist Party VIPs. Policemen salute as the
first Emgrands leave this plant in the port city of Ningbo through clouds of
theatrical smoke.
</P>
<P>
Li, Geely's chairman, already has an international auto business. Since 2006,
Geely Automobile has been a 23 percent shareholder in the company that's the
biggest maker of London's iconic black cabs. In October, Ford named Geely
Holding Group Co., Geely Automobile's closely held parent, as the preferred
bidder for Volvo. On Dec. 23, Ford said the companies had agreed on most terms
of the sale, which would be completed in the second quarter.
</P>
<P>
As Li, 46, answers questions at the factory, a reporter asks whether he wants to
emulate Japan's Toyota Motor Corp. Toyota, the planet's No. 1 carmaker, lost
$4.85 billion in the year that ended on March 31, 2009.
</P>
<P>
"Why should I want to be Toyota?" Li deadpans. "They're losing billions."
</P>
<P>
If any product illustrates China's place in the new economic order, it's the
automobile. The country has averaged annual 10 percent increases in gross
domestic product since 1978 -- growth that has helped turn a nation of
bicyclists into a land of car- craving consumers.
</P>
<P>
China, with its 1.37 billion people, overtook the U.S. in 2009 to become the
world's largest vehicle market by sales. The government projected that auto
sales for the full year would soar 39 percent to more than 13 million vehicles.
In November alone, they shot up 96 percent.
</P>
<P>
While U.S. manufacturers shrink, China had 117 automakers at the end of 2008,
according to the China Association of Automobile Manufacturers.
</P>
<P>
Amid a global recession, the collapse of Detroit and trouble at Toyota,
investors are wild about China's prospects. Geely, in which a Goldman-managed
fund holds bonds and warrants that can be converted into 15 percent of the
company, saw its shares jump 573 percent on the Hong Kong stock exchange in 2009
through Dec. 28. That's more than 10 times the rise in the benchmark Hang Seng
Index.
</P>
<P>
BYD Co., maker of the world's first commercially available plug-in hybrid, an
electric-powered car with a small gasoline engine for backup, attracted Warren
Buffett. He bought a 10 percent stake for $232 million in September 2008. BYD
shares surged more than fivefold in 2009 through Dec. 28.
</P>
<P>
Shares of six other Chinese car companies, including SAIC Motor Corp., China's
biggest domestic manufacturer, have at least tripled. Goldman's September 2009
investment in Geely increased in value by 50 percent in the first two months.
</P>
<P>
"Geely's track record of growth, profitability and innovation has impressed us,"
says Andrew Wolff, Hong Kong-based head of Goldman's merchant-banking division
in Asia outside Japan.
</P>
<P>
Charles Munger, vice chairman of Buffett's Berkshire Hathaway Inc., is equally
bullish on Berkshire's investment.
</P>
<P>
"BYD is one of the most-interesting small companies in the world," Munger, 85,
told Bloomberg Television in May.
</P>
<P>
Now, spurred by the government, Chinese automobile companies are challenging
Western, Japanese and Korean rivals on the global stage. By 2015, China is
aiming for 10 percent, or an $85 billion share, of the world's vehicle and auto
parts sales, the Ministry of Commerce said in November.
</P>
<P>
"There's no doubt that 2009 marked the year that China became king of the
automotive hill," says Michael Dunne, president of Beijing-based Dunne &amp; Co.,
which advises fund managers on buying shares in Chinese automakers.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0007" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
Netflix Pitches Online Film Plan to Wary Studios
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
SAN FRANCISCO
By Adam Satariano, Ari Levy and Ronald Grover
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1212ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Netflix Inc. Chief Content Officer Ted Sarandos bypassed Hollywood to jumpstart
the company's online film-rental business last year. Now he has to convince the
studios the company is a friend and not a foe.
</P>
<P>
Chief Executive Officer Reed Hastings is counting on Sarandos to cut deals with
studios giving Netflix rights to show more films over the Web. Sarandos, 45,
says he is willing to write big checks and negotiate directly with studios after
Netflix earlier went around Walt Disney Co. and Sony Corp. to gain access to
their titles from the Starz cable channel.
</P>
<P>
"We have to fight against their fear that we'll destroy the ecosystem,"
Sarandos, a former video-store clerk, said at a Dec. 16 panel discussion. "We're
not destroying anything. We're creating a new opportunity."
</P>
<P>
Sarandos's success is critical to Netflix as viewers move to the Web,
endangering the mail-order DVD rental business that helped the company upend
brick-and-mortar stores such as Blockbuster Inc. His challenge is to convince
studios to provide content as they explore their own digital options, including
offering movies online themselves.
</P>
<P>
"The challenge for Netflix is what to do when the world migrates to digital
distribution and whether it can obtain product from all the studios as that's
happening," said Warren Lieberfarb, the former head of Warner Bros. DVD
operations.
</P>
<P>
Netflix, the largest mail-order film-rental service, offers Web-based movie-
viewing that's used by 42 percent of its 11.1 million subscribers, according to
the company. It has an online library of 17,000 films and TV shows.
</P>
<P>
The studios, coping with a decline in DVD sales, are trying to avoid the fate of
newspapers and music labels, which lost sales when their content went online.
Hollywood executives view digital distribution as a threat to the traditional
way money is made from movies.
</P>
<P>
"Everybody views it as a terminal career decision if you get it wrong," said
Frank Biondi, who has led Universal Studios, Time Warner Inc.'s HBO cable
network and Viacom Inc., owner of Paramount Pictures.
</P>
<P>
Acquiring DVDs has rarely been a problem for Netflix, which charges $8.99 a
month and up for unlimited mail-order service. The company needs additional
rights from the studios to stream films to PCs, game consoles and Web-linked
TVs.
</P>
<P>
Netflix gained streaming rights to Disney and Sony movies including
"Ratatouille" and "Spider-Man 3" last year by allying with Starz, the pay-TV
network controlled by Liberty Media Corp. In the future, permission will have to
come from the studios, Netflix said in its annual report.
</P>
<P>
The Starz partnership created "animosity" in Hollywood, according to Tony Wible,
an analyst at Janney Montgomery Scott in Philadelphia, who recommends selling
Netflix shares. The retailer will probably need to pay studios more or risk
losing content, he said.
</P>
<P>
Paramount, based in Los Angeles, supplies older titles to Netflix for streaming,
Thomas Lesinski, head of home entertainment, said in an e-mail. "But not new
releases."
</P>
<P>
Home entertainment executives at the other major studios declined to be
interviewed.
</P>
<P>
DVDs rank as the most-profitable part of Hollywood's film business, with studios
keeping about 80 percent of each purchase, according to Tom Adams, president of
Monterey, California-based Adams Media Research. Sales will fall about 10
percent to $13 billion this year, according to Adams, who tracks the market.
Rentals will total $8 billion, unchanged from 2008. Studios also will get about
$2 billion from premium cable in the U.S. and $1 billion from basic cable and
broadcast TV.
</P>
<P>
Sarandos and Hastings pledge to pay studios more as online viewing replaces the
mail-order business. The company estimates it will spend $600 million next year
shipping DVDs.
</P>
<P>
"We'll become one of the networks' and studios' largest revenue generators,"
Hastings said. He expects to be mailing DVDs until 2030.
</P>
<P>
Netflix's DVD subscription service is projected by analysts to drive profit of
$110.8 million this year on sales of $1.67 billion, a 22 percent gain from 2008.
The shares, which have almost doubled this year, added 26 cents to $57.60 at
10:21 a.m. New York time in Nasdaq Stock Market trading.
</P>
<P>
Through the first half of 2009, Netflix accounted for $803 million of the $4.14
billion U.S. rental market, trailing Blockbuster Inc.'s $986 million, according
to Janney Montgomery.
</P>
<P>
The big studios -- Warner Bros., Disney, News Corp.'s Fox, Paramount, Sony and
General Electric Co.'s Universal -- sell films in separate windows and times.
Movies go from theaters to stores, for purchase or rental, to cable and
satellite pay-per- view, to premium channels like HBO, then basic cable and
broadcast, with studios collecting money at every step.
</P>
<P>
Hastings's aim is to find a niche for streaming.
</P>
<P>
Netflix's goal of streaming films to rental customers when DVDs arrive in stores
or air on pay TV would violate studio agreements with cable networks, said
Biondi who's now senior managing director of WaterView Advisors LLC, a New York-
based private-equity firm.
</P>
<P>
"Not that those can't be reset," Biondi said in an interview. "But you're going
to have big customer sets that are going to be very unhappy."
</P>
<P>
Sarandos says Netflix is creating a business that didn't exist before,
partnering with Tokyo-based Sony, Microsoft Corp. and TiVo Inc. to stream films
to game consoles and set-top boxes. It is also vying with cable operators such
as Comcast Corp., which is introducing an online service, studios including New
York-based Time Warner and Burbank, California-based Disney, as well as Apple
Inc. and retailer Best Buy Co.
</P>
<P>
Researcher iSuppli Corp. in El Segundo, California, estimates consumers
worldwide will have 376.5 million devices that can receive Web video content by
2013, up from 94.8 million now. Netflix plans to expand internationally with a
streaming- only service next year, Hastings said in October.
</P>
<P>
The studios have seen rental chains buckle under competition from Netflix and
Coinstar Inc., operator of Redbox kiosks that rent movies for $1 a day. Time
Warner is seeking more money from Netflix, whose Web site no longer features the
studio's DVDs -- a possible "sign of strain," Janney's Wible said in a Dec. 17
research note.
</P>
<P>
To alleviate fears that its online service won't cannibalize existing revenue,
Netflix has suggested it may agree to a new sales-only window in which movies
can't be rented.
</P>
<P>
Grover reported from Los Angeles.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0008" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
December Casualty-Free for Americans in Iraq
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
BAGHDAD
By Michael Hastings
Special to The Washington Post
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1225ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
No Americans died in combat in Iraq in December, a milestone for the U.S.
military, the top U.S. commander in the country said Friday.
</P>
<P>
"December was the first month that the U.S. had zero battle casualties in Iraq,"
Gen. Ray Odierno announced at a news conference after a ceremony to mark the
change of the Baghdad command's name from Multi-National Force-Iraq (MNF-1) to
United States Forces-Iraq (USF-1) .
</P>
<P>
The ceremony, held at Camp Victory, on Baghdad's outskirts, represented a
turning point in the almost seven-year-long war, symbolizing the transition from
a U.S.-led force that was primarily engaged in combat operations to an all-U.S.
contingent that will focus on "advising and assisting" Iraqi security forces in
preparation for the drastic drawdown of U.S. troops from roughly 110,000 to
50,000 by August 2010.
</P>
<P>
"In 2006, when I flew over Baghdad, I remember looking down on a city cloaked by
darkness and gripped in fear," Odierno said at the ceremony. "Today, when I fly
over Baghdad, I see hope, with bright lights and busy traffic."
</P>
<P>
Over the past two years, he said, there has been a 92 percent decrease in
security incidents, a 90 percent decrease in high-profile attacks, a 94 percent
decrease in civilian casualties and a 90 percent decrease in U.S. casualties.
</P>
<P>
Attacks have dropped from more than 200 a day two years ago to approximately 15
a day now, according to the head of the U.S. Central Command, Gen. David H.
Petraeus, who also attended the ceremony.
</P>
<P>
The official name change took place in the headquarters of the multinational
force, a former palace of Saddam Hussein's overlooking a series of artificial
lakes near the Baghdad airport. The hall was filled with hundreds of U.S.
servicemen and women, U.S. diplomats, and a handful of Iraqi dignitaries and
military officials.
</P>
<P>
In his speech, Petraeus said that the ceremony reflected "the continued
transition of security responsibilities in Iraq as we enter a year during which
the United States mission here will be changed and the U.S. forces will be drawn
down." He added, "It's a time for reflection on past achievements and on the
hard work that clearly still lies ahead."
</P>
<P>
"Today is about the military," said Robert Ford, a U.S. deputy ambassador in
Baghdad. "The ceremony marks an important evolution in the role the Americans
are playing in Iraq."
</P>
<P>
For the U.S. military, the multinational force, which was established May 15,
2004, will be remembered as one that made a series of near-catastrophic missteps
early in the war but overcame them after adopting a counterinsurgency strategy
under Petraeus and Odierno in 2007 that focused on protecting the civilian
population, paying off insurgents and helping the central government in Baghdad
consolidate power.
</P>
<P>
About 3,600 Americans were killed in combat under MNF-I, out of a total 4,371
U.S. military deaths in the war, according to the Iraq Coalition Casualty Count.
</P>
<P>
For many Iraqis, however, MNF-I will be remembered as an American occupation
force that unleashed a civil war that claimed the lives of at least 130,000
civilians, forced 2 million people to flee their homes and detained tens of
thousands before restoring a semblance of stability last year.
</P>
<P>
In part, changing the name of the force from MNF-I to USF-I was also a belated
reflection of reality.
</P>
<P>
The mission in Iraq ceased being multinational after the last Australian troops
left the country in July 2009, and the U.S. military's claim that it commanded
significant international support was always somewhat thin, especially as its
allies dwindled after the war became increasingly unpopular.
</P>
<P>
Although the United States claimed a coalition of about 30 countries,
approximately 85 percent of the troops in Iraq have been American, including the
vast majority of combat troops and casualties.
</P>
<P>
The name change also reflects a move to unify and streamline U.S. forces in Iraq
under one command to facilitate what U.S. military officials call "a responsible
drawdown" to meet the Dec. 31, 2011, withdrawal date stipulated in the Status of
Forces Agreement, according to a U.S. military spokesperson.
</P>
<P>
Soldiers in the audience at Camp Victory on Friday did not appear to think the
change would affect their day-to-day lives in the country.
</P>
<P>
"Doesn't impact our mission really _ we just respond to a different
headquarters," said 22-year-old Sgt. Nick Anderson, of Indiana. "I think it's
great we're in Iraq, it's finally drawing down, and the Iraqis are able to take
over their own security."
</P>
<P>
Michael Hastings is a special correspondent for The Washington Post.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0009" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
Deploy the Scanners
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
By Michael Chertoff
Special to The Washington Post
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1227ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Since the uncomfortably close attempted attack on Northwest Flight 253 last
week, many have focused on why the alleged terrorist, Umar Farouk Abdulmutallab,
was not placed on a watch list that would have prevented him from flying, even
though the government had received information that he was a potential
extremist. We should focus on a more fundamental question: How can we keep
explosive materials off planes?
</P>
<P>
Most airport security checkpoints use metal detectors. Al-Qaida has shown that
it knows how to avoid detection by using an explosive device that contains
little or no metal, such as PETN, or pentaerythritol tetranitrate, used by
Abdulmutallab and "shoe bomber" Richard Reid in 2001.
</P>
<P>
During my time as secretary of homeland security, the Transportation Security
Administration began working to replace the 1970s-era metal detectors used at
airports across America with modern technology able to detect non-metal weapons
concealed by terrorists on their bodies _ even in their underwear, where
Abdulmutallab allegedly hid his bomb. The latest versions of these machines _
sometimes called whole-body imagers _ are deployed at 19 airports, and the TSA
is attempting to place them throughout the nation.
</P>
<P>
From the onset, deployment of the machines has been vigorously opposed by some
groups. In June, the House of Representatives passed a bill that would prevent
the TSA from using the new systems in most cases. If the House bill were to
become law, the TSA would be limited to using the new technology only after a
passenger had been selected for additional scrutiny. The vast majority of
passengers would still pass only through metal detectors. So, under the
standards set by the House bill, a terrorist not on a "no-fly" list or a watch
list mandating closer scrutiny _ like Abdulmutallab _ could probably carry a
concealed non-metal weapon onto a plane undetected.
</P>
<P>
Congress should reject this restrictive bill and instead fund a large-scale
deployment of next-generation systems.
</P>
<P>
Opposition to whole-body imagers essentially relies on three arguments. First,
the American Civil Liberties Union and privacy advocates have complained that
the machines subject passengers to a "virtual strip search." Second, they claim
that the machines are unsafe because they expose passengers to dangerous amounts
of radiation in screening. Third, some critics argue that the only correct
approach to airline security lies in better intelligence.
</P>
<P>
All of these objections lack merit. The "safety" concern is particularly
specious, because the technologies expose people to no more radiation than is
experienced in daily life.
</P>
<P>
The case of Abdulmutallab shows that we cannot simply "rely on intelligence."
Abdulmutallab was not on a watch list that required closer scrutiny. Even if the
review President Obama has ordered closes a gap that would have put
Abdulmutallab or others on more select watch lists, there are plenty of
terrorists out there about whom we know nothing. Too many potentially dangerous
people simply would not appear on any watch list. We cannot put all our eggs in
the "intelligence basket." That's why, since Sept. 11, 2001, we have worked to
establish multiple layers of defense to protect the American people. Watch lists
surely are an important layer, as is intelligence-sharing, but others, such as
the deployment of advanced detection technology, are just as important.
</P>
<P>
Claims that the screening amounts to "virtual strip searches" is calculated to
alarm the public. As if screening is meant to reveal people's private parts to
TSA officers. But the agency has nonetheless taken privacy concerns seriously in
creating procedures for using this technology. In deploying the machines, the
TSA has strictly limited the number of officers who see the images; separates
the officers looking at images from the passengers being screened (so the
officers do not know which passengers the images belong to); and uses software
to blur the faces on the images _ further protecting the anonymity of
passengers. Moreover, the machines are configured to prevent TSA officers from
storing or retaining any images. As an additional measure, passengers can choose
not to walk through one of the machines and receive a physical examination
instead.
</P>
<P>
In short, the TSA has listened to the reasonable concerns of privacy advocates
and incorporated numerous suggestions into its protocols to draw the right
balance between security and privacy. The administration must stand firm against
privacy ideologues, for whom every security measure is unacceptable. Failing to
use all available tools to plug a gap in security puts the lives of airline
travelers needlessly at risk.
</P>
<P>
The writer was secretary of homeland security from 2005 to 2009 and is co-
founder of the Chertoff Group, a security and risk-management firm whose clients
include a manufacturer of body-imaging screening machines.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0010" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
Information Sharing Key in Terror Prevention
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
By Thomas E. McNamara
Special to The Washington Post
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1242ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The partisan finger-pointing that followed last week's attempted airplane
bombing is the wrong response to governmental failures to share information.
Since Congress enacted the recommendations of the Sept. 11 commission five years
ago, administrations of both parties have worked to fundamentally change the way
federal agencies and offices manage information. These efforts have received
bipartisan support but have unfortunately been marked by limited success.
</P>
<P>
Neither the George W. Bush nor the Obama administrations nor Congress has
followed its pronouncements of strong support for change with the high-priority
attention required to reform how national security information is processed. I
served in both administrations as program manager for the Information Sharing
Environment _ an office created by the Intelligence Reform and Terrorism
Prevention Act of 2004 _ and I received enough support to avoid failure, but not
enough to ensure success.
</P>
<P>
After the Sept. 11 attacks, the Bush administration, with bipartisan support,
built a solid foundation for an Information Sharing Environment (ISE) _ as
called for by the 2004 act, which required the president to name a program
manager for the ISE and to establish a council to advise the president and the
program manager on the development of information-sharing procedures and
coordination among federal agencies. But fostering an environment in which
timely information moves to those who need it to do their jobs requires
consistent, high-level attention. That is what forces the bureaucracy to
transform its traditional "need to know" restrictions into "responsibility to
provide" practices. We built the base for a new system but lacked high-level
support to institutionalize new practices.
</P>
<P>
The White House failed to push for full implementation or funding of its own
directives. Most agencies, for example, never established required privacy
guidelines for information-sharing, and the Office of Management and Budget
provided no new funding for agency reform efforts. Meanwhile, other priorities
pushed aside information-sharing. In its final year, the Bush White House
focused on its "legacy victory," asserting that reform had been accomplished.
But change was only beginning, and the momentum of the first years was lost.
</P>
<P>
The Obama administration announced a new impetus for information-sharing, but
here, too, reality has not matched rhetoric. After nearly a year in office, the
administration has yet to fill key information management positions. The program
manager position is vacant and has been downgraded in status. The White House
pledged to stand up the Privacy and Civil Liberties Oversight Board, a panel
required in the 2004 legislation, yet it remains dormant.
</P>
<P>
While work continues at a modest pace, the bureaucracy knows how to respond to
signals that this is not a priority _ keep on the old course. The administration
and Congress agree that we cannot return to old ways of managing information.
But without sustained, prioritized attention and allocation of new resources,
true change will remain merely an objective.
</P>
<P>
The major challenges to improving information-sharing are changing the cultures,
policies and business processes of the agencies. These challenges are
exemplified in the differing agency missions; overlapping "turf"; resource
shortfalls; and bureaucratic inertia. For five years, the leadership has been
inconsistent and insufficient. To make substantial progress, three initiatives
are needed:
</P>
<P>
First, integrating divergent efforts requires top-down management by a single
national executive. The administration should consolidate within the Executive
Office of the President a single "Information Management Executive" with budget
certification authority to require agencies to build the infrastructure for a
fully functioning, coordinated system. That individual should coordinate
activity in all information arenas (health, transportation, national security
and law enforcement) at the federal, state, local and private levels.
</P>
<P>
Second, Congress should put aside its jurisdictional rigidities (and territorial
"rice bowl" attitudes) and take a holistic view of information management. So
far, both houses have left these matters to their Homeland Security committees,
which have done good work but are restricted to one department. Congress needs a
special committee or task force in each chamber with oversight across committee
and agency lines to deal with these government-wide issues.
</P>
<P>
Third, the president must stress that sporadic Cabinet-level involvement is
unacceptable. All agency heads must drive the bureaucracy forward. Requiring
periodic reports of progress and failings to the president should actually
produce change.
</P>
<P>
Progress has been made, but inadequate support has been given to this essential
reform. While the rest of the nation marches into 21st-century information
management, the federal government cannot remain mired in 20th-century
practices.
</P>
<P>
The writer served as program manager for the Information Sharing Environment
from 2006 until August 2009. Previously he was an assistant secretary of state
in the Clinton administration and a special assistant to President George H.W.
Bush.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0011" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
 PG&amp;E Customer Revolt May Threaten Rollout of `Smart Grid'
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
SAN FRANCISCO
By Mark Chediak
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1254ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Consumer backlash and cost concerns may cause delays in the nationwide rollout
of "smart" utility meters at the center of the Obama administration's $8 billion
push to update the U.S. electricity grid.
</P>
<P>
PG&amp;E Corp., owner of California's largest utility, halted meter installations in
Bakersfield, north of Los Angeles, after hundreds of customers complained that
readings weren't accurate. The meters, part of a so-called smart-grid initiative
billed as clearing the way for more renewable-energy use, are designed to help
consumers conserve power during periods of peak demand.
</P>
<P>
Martha Johnson, pastor of a church in Bakersfield, said her utility bill almost
doubled from a year earlier to $874 in July after her new meter was installed.
"That caught my eye because I've never had a bill that high," said Johnson, 64.
</P>
<P>
San Francisco-based PG&amp;E, which faces a lawsuit from a Bakersfield customer
who's seeking class-action status, says its meters are accurate and hot weather
and increased rates led to higher bills than consumers expected. The state
Utilities Commission ordered an independent study of billing accuracy.
</P>
<P>
Whether PG&amp;E's complaints stem from perception or defects, they may slow
installations of the meters, a cornerstone of President Barack Obama's plan to
spur grid upgrades with $8 billion in public-private funding. Consumer groups
question whether benefits of the meters justify costs passed on when regulators
allow utilities to increase rates to pay for them.
</P>
<P>
"If customers lose confidence in smart meters, I would expect regulators would
be more reluctant to grant rate increases to install new meters across the
system," said Travis Miller, a utility analyst at Morningstar Inc. in Chicago.
"Any kind of adverse impact from these projects could impact long- term growth
of the meters."
</P>
<P>
The devices allow utilities to check energy use remotely, eliminating the need
for employing meter readers. They can be connected to equipment that shows
customers when rates are highest, allowing households and other consumers to
shift power use to less costly periods. Smart meters also give utilities more
control of demand, helping them match usage with renewable electricity flows,
such as from wind and solar power.
</P>
<P>
There are about 8 million smart electric meters in the U.S., and that count will
jump sevenfold by 2019, according to the Institute for Electric Efficiency in
Washington.
</P>
<P>
"Other states are looking very closely at what is happening in California," said
Mindy Spatt, a spokeswoman for the Utility Reform Network, a consumer group in
San Francisco. "What we know for sure about the meters is they are job killers
and they are very expensive. The rest is just pie in the sky."
</P>
<P>
Utility-consumer groups across the country have raised cost concerns about meter
projects, said Charles Acquard, executive director of the National Association
of State Utility Consumer Advocates.
</P>
<P>
Ben Schuman, an analyst who covers meter makers for Pacific Crest Securities in
Portland, Ore., said the devices installed so far have proved accurate. The
unknown is whether consumers will use the technology to cut power costs, he
said.
</P>
<P>
Liberty Lake, Washington-based Itron has risen 7.3 percent this year on the
Nasdaq Stock Market, trailing a 45 percent jump by the Regulators in states such
as Connecticut and Texas are pressing utilities to show how smart meters will
benefit consumers. In November, Indiana regulators rejected a proposal by Duke
Energy Corp. to install about 800,000 smart meters after concluding the company
didn't show the plan's long-term rewards.
</P>
<P>
Charlotte, N.C.-based Duke, which got $200 million in federal funding to deploy
smart meters and other equipment in three states, will reapply in January for
approval in Indiana, company spokesman Dave Scanzoni said.
</P>
<P>
Bakersfield resident Pete Flores filed suit in October, alleging that his bills
almost tripled after a smart meter was put in. Lawyer Michael Kelly, who
represents Flores, said he plans to file an updated suit with more plaintiffs in
January.
</P>
<P>
"The allegations in the lawsuit are untrue," PG&amp;E spokesman Paul Moreno said.
</P>
<P>
PG&amp;E tested meters in Bakersfield and found they were working properly, Moreno
said. The company is installing 12,000 to 15,000 meters a day in central
California and the San Francisco area.
</P>
<P>
PG&amp;E has investigated more than 400 customer complaints, mostly from Bakersfield
and other areas where hot weather and rate increases as high as 22 percent
caused power bills to surge, Moreno said. Bakersfield had 17 days above 100
degrees Fahrenheit in July, up from six days a year earlier, according to the
National Weather Service.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="WPB_ENG_20100101.0012" type="story">
<HEADLINE>
Restore Protection for Wolves
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
By Jamie Rappaport Clark
Special to The Washington Post
LA TIMES-WASHINGTON POST--01-01-10 1256ET
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
"(T)oday, I've signed a memorandum that will help restore the scientific process
to its rightful place at the heart of the Endangered Species Act, a process
undermined by past administrations. ... For more than three decades, the
Endangered Species Act has successfully protected our nation's most threatened
wildlife, and we should be looking for ways to improve it _ not weaken it."
</P>
<P>
_ President Obama, March 3
</P>
<P>
WASHINGTON _ I felt distinct relief upon hearing those words. I was at the
Interior Department in March when President Obama made this promise to an
audience of conservationists on the 160th anniversary of the agency's founding.
Interior Secretary Ken Salazar was by his side.
</P>
<P>
After eight years of conservation groups fighting tooth and nail to protect
America's imperiled wildlife against the plans and rulings of the Bush
administration, it looked as though the Obama administration would renew our
commitment to conserving endangered species and biodiversity for future
generations.
</P>
<P>
But this relief was short-lived.
</P>
<P>
Just three days after the president pledged to strengthen and restore scientific
integrity to implementation of the Endangered Species Act, Secretary Salazar
removed federal protection from gray wolves in the Northern Rockies. In making
this decision, he adopted the plan developed by the Bush administration, relying
on a flawed legal opinion crafted by that administration. His decision has
undermined the protection of the gray wolf and countless other threatened and
endangered species.
</P>
<P>
This misguided action places wolves squarely in the cross hairs of their
opponents across the Northern Rockies, allowing as many as 1,050 of Idaho and
Montana's estimated 1,350 wolves to be legally killed and jeopardizing the
30-year recovery effort to restore wild wolves to the region. As a result of
Secretary Salazar's action, wolves in the Northern Rockies are being hunted
prematurely. Already, 210 have been killed, and there are still three months
left in the Idaho hunting season.
</P>
<P>
I work with an organization that is among the 13 conservation groups that have
taken this issue to court. In September, a federal judge indicated our case is
likely to succeed on its merits, although a final ruling will not come until
later this year.
</P>
<P>
As a former director of the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, I find it hard to
understand why the Obama administration made this decision and why it justified
it by relying on a legal opinion that has been criticized by a range of people,
including academics and members of Congress. Worse, this decision affects more
than the Northern Rockies wolf population. It also sets an alarming precedent
for future listing and delisting decisions.
</P>
<P>
The Bush administration's legal opinion overturned more than 30 years of
interpretation of the Endangered Species Act. By this reasoning, protection of
species can now be determined by political boundaries and manipulation, not
biology. Adjusting populations in this unscientific way _ carving out areas
along state lines, as Salazar did in exempting Wyoming from the areas in which
wolves were no longer to be considered endangered _ makes the act subject to
political manipulation. This legal sleight of hand is in direct contrast to
Obama's pledge to restore scientific integrity to decisions about endangered-
species conservation.
</P>
<P>
Salazar should not have allowed the gray wolf to be delisted without first
engaging in a clear and transparent public process and without exploring the
ramifications of relying on this flawed legal opinion. Defenders of Wildlife
reached out several times to work with the Interior Department to craft a plan
that would ensure continued wolf recovery while returning management of wolves
to state fish and wildlife agencies. Our efforts were ignored.
</P>
<P>
Because of my intimate involvement with the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service's
reintroduction of wolves to Yellowstone, I was very much looking forward to the
day when the wolf population would no longer need federal protections. But
wolves and endangered-species conservation now face an uncertain future. If the
president's pledge to restore scientific integrity to the Endangered Species
Act, and to improve the law, is to be fulfilled, action must be taken
immediately. The interior secretary should withdraw the flawed legal opinion on
which his delisting relied, restore federal protection to gray wolves in the
Northern Rockies and engage all stakeholders in developing a plan to ensure that
one of our nation's greatest conservation successes, the restoration of gray
wolves to Yellowstone and the Northern Rockies, will not be lost.
</P>
<P>
The writer is executive vice president for Defenders of Wildlife, which has
worked on wolf conservation for more than three decades. She directed the U.S.
Fish and Wildlife Service from 1997 to 2001.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0001" type="multi" >
<HEADLINE>
Xinhua Middle East news advisory -- June 1
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
CAIRO, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The following are some of major Middle
East news stories due to be covered or pursued by Xinhua News
Agency on Monday.
-- Monitoring developments of influenza A/H1N1 cases in the
Mideast region after three additional A/H1N1 flu cases were
diagnosed on Sunday in Israel.
-- Israel started on Sunday a five-day civil defense exercise,
simulating an attack on the Jewish state. Expect coverage.
-- A UN mission is scheduled to arrive in the Gaza Strip to
gather information for its inquiry on Israel's offensive there.
Expect coverage.
-- Israel will not freeze settlement construction for natural
growth, despite intense pressure from the U.S. Obama
administration to do so. Tracking responses from the Arab world.
-- Continue to follow security developments in Palestinian
territories as rivals Fatah and Hamas movements traded
accusations over armed clashes in the West Bank city of Qalqilya
that killed six people.
-- Monitoring campaigns for Lebanon's June 7 parliamentary
election.
-- Tracking campaigns for Iran's 10th presidential election
slated for June 12.
-- Keep watching security situation over Iraq.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0002" type="multi" >
<HEADLINE>
Major news items in leading Israeli newspapers
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
JERUSALEM, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The following are major news items
in leading Israeli newspapers on Monday.
Ha'aretz:
-- Israel's ministerial committee on legislation Sunday rejected
a bill that would have conditioned Israeli citizenship on a
declaration of loyalty to Israel as a Jewish state.
-- Egypt rejected a U.S. proposal for gradual normalization
between the Arab world and Israel that would have allowed Israeli
planes to fly freely through Arab air space.
The Jerusalem Post:
-- Israel will not freeze settlement construction for natural
growth, despite intense pressure from the U.S. Obama
administration to do so, according to the source of the
newspaper.
-- Israeli Defense Minister Ehud Barak left Sunday night for the
United States, where he is expected to run into stiff U.S.
resistance not only over Israel's settlement policy, but also
over its policy regarding the Gaza border crossings and the
reconstruction of the Gaza Strip.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0003" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Bomb explosion kills 4 at Baghdad wholesale market
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
BAGHDAD, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A bomb explosion at a wholesale vegetable market in southern Baghdad early
Monday killed four people and wounded 13 others, an Interior Ministry source
said.
</P>
<P>
An explosive charge detonated early in the morning at the al- Rasheed wholesale
market in Baghdad's southern district of Doura, the source told Xinhua on
condition of anonymity.
</P>
<P>
The bomb was hidden in a shop in the busy market, where dozens of merchants and
grocers gather to buy and sell vegetables that usually brought in the early
morning from countryside, the source said.
</P>
<P>
The blast destroyed the shop and caused damages to several nearby stalls and
civilian vehicles, while Iraqi security forces sealed off the area to secure the
scene, the source added.
</P>
<P>
It was the second such deadly attack that struck al-Rasheed wholesale market in
less than a month when a truck bomb exploded on May 6, killing 11 people and
injuring 37 others.
</P>
<P>
Despite dramatic drop in violence over the last two years, Baghdad are among
some Iraqi cities that sporadically witness deadly attacks.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0004" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Suicide car bomb kills Iraqi policeman in northeast Baghdad
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
BAQUBA, Iraq, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A suicide car bomb struck a police checkpoint in a town in the volatile province
of Diyala on Monday, killing a policeman and wounding nine people, a provincial
police source said.
</P>
<P>
A suicide bomber tried to drive his explosion-laden car into a police checkpoint
in the town of Jalawla, some 130 km northeast of Baghdad, the source told Xinhua
on condition of anonymity.
</P>
<P>
The policemen manning the checkpoint opened heavy fire on the car and blew it up
just before reaching the bomber's target, the source said.
</P>
<P>
The attack resulted in the killing of a policeman and the wounding of seven
others along with two civilians who were close to the scene, he said.
</P>
<P>
The attack in the province came as Iraqi security forces backed by U.S. troops
are conducting a major offensive dubbed "Glad Tidings" against militant groups
and criminal gangs.
</P>
<P>
Diyala province, stretching from the eastern edges of Baghdad to the Iranian
border east of the country, has long been a stronghold for al-Qaida militants
and other insurgent groups since the U.S.-led invasion of Iraq in 2003.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0005" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Yemeni president visits Saudi Arabia
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
RIYADH, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Yemeni President Ali Abdullah Saleh arrived in Riyadh Sunday on a short visit to
Saudi Arabia, Saudi Press Agency (SPA) reported Monday.
</P>
<P>
The Yemeni president said during his talks with the Saudi King Abdullah bin
Abdul-Aziz that "the strength and stability of Yemen is a strength for the
kingdom and its brothers in the Gulf Cooperation Council (GCC)."
</P>
<P>
The two also talked about the necessary measures against the Yemeni pro-
separatists working in the kingdom and means to curb the remittances they afford
for the protesters in Yemen, according to a Yemeni government source.
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, Saleh called on Saudi investors to do more investment projects in
Yemen.
</P>
<P>
The Yemeni president's visit is also for performing the Omra ( lesser
pilgrimage) in Jeddah.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0006" type="multi" >
<HEADLINE>
Major news items in leading Iranian newspapers
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
TEHRAN, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The following are major news items in
leading Iranian newspapers on Monday.
Tehran Times:
-- Iranian Defense Minister Mostafa-Mohammad Najjar announced
Sunday Iran will uncover on Monday a new generation of speedboat,
submarine and drone in the port city of Bandar Abbas, the capital
of Hormozgan Province.
Iran Daily:
-- Addressing a public gathering in Savojbolagh in Tehran
Province on Sunday, Iranian President Mahmoud Ahmadinejad said
that on televised talk shows in the near future he might expose
the names of those who are economically corrupt so that the
people would realize what they have done.
Kayhan:
-- In order to commemorate the 20th anniversary of the death of
the father of Iran's Islamic Revolution Ayatollah Ruholla
Khomeini, the third international conference of Imam Khomeini and
foreign policy with the title of "Manner in International
Relations" will be held in Tehran on June 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0007" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
26th case of A/H1N1 flu diagnosed in Israel: report
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
JERUSALEM, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Another A/H1N1 flu case was diagnosed on Monday in Israel, bringing the total
number in the Jewish state to 26, local news service Ynet reported.
</P>
<P>
The patient, a 19-year-old youth, was hospitalized at Sheba Medical Center at
Tel Hashomer after being diagnosed with the virus, said the report, adding that
doctors said the youth is in good condition.
</P>
<P>
The youth contracted the virus in Israel from a friend who returned from the
United States, added the report.
</P>
<P>
Over the past few days, Israeli health authority diagnosed several influenza
A/H1N1 cases since the outbreak of the influenza.
</P>
<P>
According to the World Health Organization, 53 countries had officially reported
15,510 cases of A/H1N1 infection, including 99 deaths, as of Friday.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0008" type="multi" >
<HEADLINE>
Major news items in leading Egyptian newspapers
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
CAIRO, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The following are major news items in
leading Egyptian newspapers on Monday.
Al Ahram:
-- Egypt's Minister of Water Resources and Irrigation Nasreddin
Allam said Sunday Egypt's stake of the River Nile water are
nonnegotiable.
Al Akhbar:
-- Zahi Hawas, the Secretary General of the Supreme Council of
Antiquities, denied on Sunday he has given up bids to restore
antiquities sent outside Egypt illegally.
The Egyptian Gazette:
-- Egypt sees Middle East peace as the region's top priority
rather than Iran's nuclear program, president spokesman Suleiman
Awad said on Sunday.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0009" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Urgent:UN investigation panel arrives in Gaza
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
GAZA, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A UN inquiry team arrived in the Gaza Strip on Monday to investigate the
performance of Israel and Hamas during a three-week offensive Israel launched in
the Hamas- controlled territory at the end of 2008.
</P>
<P>
South African persecutor Richard Goldstone leads the mission which the UN Human
Rights Council appointed. Mr. Goldstone and the 14 legal experts entered Gaza
through Rafah crossing point, coming from Egypt.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0010" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Israel warns Iran could have nuclear bomb by year-end
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
JERUSALEM, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iran could have enough fissile material for its first nuclear bomb by the end of
this year, an Israeli intelligence official warned Monday.
</P>
<P>
Brigadier General Yossi Baidatz, head of the research division of Israel's
Military Intelligence, made the remarks to the Foreign Affairs and Defense
Committee of Israel's Knesset (parliament).
</P>
<P>
"Iran is extremely troubling because of its speed. It has missiles which could
reach Israel. The Iranian clock precedes the international dialogue clock,"
Baidatz was quoted by local news service Ynet as saying.
</P>
<P>
The United States and Israel have accused Iran of trying to develop nuclear
weapons under the cover of a civilian nuclear program, but Iran has repeatedly
denied the allegations, insisting that its nuclear program is for peaceful
purposes only.
</P>
<P>
Since taking office in January, U.S. President Barack Obama has made some
diplomatic overtures to Iran that have so far been rebuffed. Obama said in May
he would not pursue this policy indefinitely and would like to see some progress
on the nuclear issue by the end of this year.
</P>
<P>
On May 25, Israeli Defense Minister Ehud Barak said that new diplomatic
overtures made by the United States to Iran were unlikely to halt the Islamic
Republic's nuclear program.
</P>
<P>
"I believe that the chance the dialogue has of stopping Iran's nuclear efforts
is very low," Barak was quoted by Israel Radio as saying.
</P>
<P>
He added that Iran posed one of the most "serious potential threats" against
Israel, reiterating that the Jewish state would not take any option off the
table regarding Iran's nuclear program.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20090601.0011" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Palestinians fire mortar at southern Israel: army
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
GAZA, June 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A mortar shell fired from the Gaza Strip landed on Monday morning in southern
Israel, an Israeli army spokesman said.
</P>
<P>
The shell hit an open space in the Western Negev area, the spokesman told
Israel's radio.
</P>
<P>
On the other side, Israeli gunboats opened fire at Palestinian fishing boats off
the southern Gaza Strip coast, local sources said.
</P>
<P>
There were no reports of casualties in the two incidents, according to the
Israeli and the Palestinian sources.
</P>
<P>
Israel and Islamic Hamas movement, which controls Gaza, do not observe a
ceasefire though both of them maintain a sort of self- control after Israel
ended its major offensive in Gaza in January 2009.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0001" type="multi" >
<HEADLINE>
Xinhua Middle East news advisory -- Dec. 1
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
CAIRO, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The following are some of the major
Middle East news stories due to be covered or pursued by Xinhua
News Agency on Wednesday.
-- The 34th Cairo International Film Festival is held in Cairo
till Dec. 9.
-- Monitoring as the Egyptian government delayed the announcement
of parliamentary elections' results on Tuesday.
-- Monitoring the formation of new Iraqi government.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0002" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
1st LD: Club wall collapse kills five in Egypt
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
CAIRO, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Five people died and six others were injured Wednesday after a wall of a club
collapsed in a district of Egypt's Helwan governorate, witnesses said.
</P>
<P>
The wall in the Arab Gohom area of Helwan, south of Cairo, fell at around 6:30
p.m. , according to nearby residents.
</P>
<P>
Workers were still using bulldozers to clear rock debris to search possible
missing persons late Wednesday night.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0003" type="multi" >
<HEADLINE>
Major news items in leading Turkish newspapers
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
ANKARA, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The following are major news items in
leading Turkish newspapers on Wednesday.
CUMHURIYET (Republic):
-- According to figures of TurkStat released on Tuesday, Turkey
's export increased 11.4 percent year-on-year and reached 92.71
billion U.S. dollars in the January-October period while foreign
trade deficit rose 83 percent year-on-year to 55.11 billion U.S.
dollars.
SABAH (Morning):
-- The outlawed Kurdish Workers' Party (PKK) sentenced its member
Ferhat Felat to 24 years of imprisonment and Fikri Bermal to 20
years of imprisonment for planting the bomb that killed four
civilians in the southeastern province of Batman four months ago,
the pro-Kurdish Firat news agency reported Tuesday.
-- Thirty people were detained in an investigation launched by a
prosecutor in Ankara with a special authority into corruption
allegations in the companies Kayseri Sugar Factor and Sugar Beet
Cooperative on Tuesday and the head of Kayseri Seker, Vedat Ali
Ozisik, his son, the director general of the company and two
executive board members were among the detainees.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0004" type="multi" >
<HEADLINE>
Major news items in leading Israeli newspapers
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
JERUSALEM, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
The following are major news items
in leading Israeli newspapers on Wednesday.
Ha'aretz:
-- The United States and Jewish leaders on Tuesday condemned
claims by a senior Palestinian official that the Western Wall of
Jerusalem's Temple Mount bears no significance for Jews.
-- Israeli Foreign Minister Avigdor Lieberman on Tuesday directed
his ministry to draft plans for a permanent "situation room" at
Ben-Gurion International Airport to assist innocent tourists or
senior officials who are harassed by border control or security
officials at Israel's national gateway.
The Jerusalem Post:
-- The Israel Defense Forces (IDF) Northern Command Chief Maj.-
Gen. Gadi Eizenkot Tuesday raised a storm by saying that active
rocket protection systems currently deployed are designated to
protect the IDF's offensive capabilities, and not necessarily
civilians, in case a war breaks out.
-- The number of completed homes in West Bank Jewish settlements
dropped by 21 percent in the first three quarters of 2010,
according to new data released Tuesday by the Central Bureau of
Statistics (CBS).
Yediot Ahronot:
-- Turkish Foreign Minister Ahmet Davutoglu on Tuesday denied
reports according to which Turkey labeled Israel as a threat in a
document that outlines Turkey's policies. Davutoglu, addressing
reporters during a U.S. visit, also refuted reports that he
personally claimed that the Jewish state will not be able to
remain independent in the long term.
Ma'ariv:
-- Israel's defense industries are eyeing contracts worth
billions of dollars with Brazil in the coming years, following
the signing of a security cooperation agreement between the two
countries a few days ago. The Israel Aerospace Industries is
slated to provide Brazil's Federal Police with unmanned aerial
vehicles (UAVs), ground radars, sensors, electronic fences and
satellite technology.
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0005" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Israel arrests Hamas lawmaker in West Bank
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
RAMALLAH, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Israeli army arrested eight Palestinians in the West Bank on Wednesday,
including a Hamas lawmaker, witnesses and security sources said.
</P>
<P>
The lawmaker, Nayef al-Rojoub, was arrested from his house in the southern city
of Hebron, said the witnesses, the other seven were detained in other cities in
the West Bank.
</P>
<P>
In addition to his position at the disabled Hamas-dominated parliament, al-
Rojoub had served as the religious affairs minister in 2006.
</P>
<P>
On June 20, Israel released al-Rojoub after holding him for nearly four years.
Al-Rojoub was among tens of West Bank-based Hamas leaders whom Israel arrested
in response to the capturing of an Israeli soldier by Hamas in Gaza.
</P>
<P>
Hamas parliamentary bloc said in a statement that it fears the arresting of the
lawmaker was a prelude to another campaign to crack down on Hamas officials
there.
</P>
<P>
In recent months, Israel freed most of the lawmakers. By Wednesday's detention,
the number of detained Hamas legislators rises to seven.
</P>
<P>
The West Bank has been controlled by the Palestinian National Authority (PNA),
which is dominated by President Mahmoud Abbas' Fatah party. In June 2007, Hamas
routed pro-Abbas forces and took over the Gaza Strip.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0006" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Kuwait donates 500 mln USD to east Sudan
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
KUWAIT CITY, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Oil-rich Kuwait on Wednesday decided to donate 500 million U.S. dollars in aid
to east Sudan, the first batch of donations at an international donors
conference held in Kuwait city.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's Deputy Prime Minister and Foreign Minister Sheikh Mohammad Sabah Al-
Salem Al-Sabah announced financial aid at the International Donors and Investors
Conference for East Sudan that opened here Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
He said 450 million dollars will be used for the execution of infrastructure and
the rest will go to social ventures.
</P>
<P>
Representatives from 39 countries, 28 institutions, as well as 73 nongovernment
organizations were present at the two-day event to back up the development of
east Sudan.
</P>
<P>
More pledges of aid are expected at the conference.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0007" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Donors, investors conference for East Sudan opens in Kuwait
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
KUWAIT CITY, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
An international donors and investors conference for east Sudan opened on
Wednesday in Kuwait City to promote the development in the region.
</P>
<P>
Kuwait's Deputy Prime Minister and Foreign Minister Sheikh Mohammad Sabah Al-
Salem Al-Sabah said oil-rich Kuwait decided to donate 500 million U.S. dollars
in aid to east Sudan, the first batch of donations at the two-day event.
</P>
<P>
He said 450 million dollars will be used for the development of infrastructure
and the rest will be grants for social ventures.
</P>
<P>
Mousa Mohammad Ahmad, assistant to the Sudanese President, said east Sudan sits
on a strategic location and has substantial natural resources, but the region
suffers from economic weakness, drought, desertification, diseases, and shortage
of services including education and health services and water.
</P>
<P>
He said the Sudanese government pledged 1.572 billion dollars for education,
health, water, electricity, transportation, agriculture, and irrigation projects
in east Sudan.
</P>
<P>
Representatives from 39 countries, 28 institutions, as well as 73 nongovernment
organizations were present at the two-day event to back up the development of
east Sudan.
</P>
<P>
More pledges of aid are expected at the conference.
</P>
<P>
East Sudan that groups three states namely Kassala, Al-Gadarif and Red Sea is
believed to be rich in agricultural and mining resources.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0008" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Iran hangs "temporary" wife of former football star for murder
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
TEHRAN, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iran hanged the temporary wife of a former football star on Wednesday for
committing murder after she spent more than eight years in prison, the local
satellite Press TV reported.
</P>
<P>
Khadijeh Shahla Jahed was found guilty in 2002 of stabbing Laleh Saharkhizan,
the wife of former Iranian football star Nasser Mohammadkhani, said the report.
</P>
<P>
Jahed had been living with the football player in the 1980s in the Iranian
capital of Tehran under a contract of temporary marriage arrangement, according
to the report.
</P>
<P>
Temporary marriage in Iran is a legal way of outside marriage for men.
</P>
<P>
Jahed was hanged at Evin prison at local time 5:00 a.m. (0130 GMT) on Wednesday
after the verdict was confirmed by Iran's Supreme Court and Judiciary Chief
Ayatollah Sadeq Amoli Larijani, her lawyer Abdolsamad Khoramshahi was quoted as
saying.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0009" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Roundup: Haneya says to respect any outcome of Palestinian
referendum on peace
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
by Fares Akram
</P>
<P>
GAZA, Dec. 1 (Xinhua) -- Hamas will respect any Palestinian referendum on a
peaceful settlement with Israel even if the agreement was against its agenda,
deposed Prime Minister of the Hamas government Ismail Haneya said Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
"The (Hamas) government's program includes the creation of a Palestinian
statehood within the borders of lands that Israel occupied in 1967," Haneya said
at a press conference held at his office in Gaza city.
</P>
<P>
However, if another solution was reached through peace talks between Israel and
the Palestinian National Authority (PNA), whose chances of success was
questioned by Haneya, "there would be a referendum and Hamas will respect its
results, even if it contradicts its policies," Haneya said.
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, Haneya said his government will maintain an undeclared ceasefire
between Israel and the Palestinian factions in the Hamas-controlled Gaza Strip
through 2011, which, he noted was one of his government's "priorities in the
coming year."
</P>
<P>
However, he said if Israel attacks Gaza, Hamas "will resist and will not
surrender."
</P>
<P>
Haneya noted that Israel "asked its allies in Europe" to launch a campaign to
show Gaza as the source of threat to the Jewish state. He said the campaign was
based on allegations that militants from Gaza had fired rockets laden with white
phosphorus warheads into Israel, and that al-Qaida has managed to have cells in
the Israeli-besieged coastal enclave.
</P>
<P>
"There is no al-Qaida in Gaza," Haneya said, adding that the killing of three
militants, members of an al-Qaida inspired group, by Israel last month, was "a
dangerous assassinations."
</P>
<P>
The Hamas government "has made sure that there are only Palestinian resistance
factions working only inside Palestine," Haneya said, adding Israeli reports
that activists of the Army of Islam had planned to kidnap Israelis in the nearby
Sinai Peninsula were false.
</P>
<P>
Besides, Haneya underlined the effects of an international isolation on his
administration which refuses to recognize Israel or renounce violence.
</P>
<P>
"There is a problem in the visits of European delegations to Gaza," and that
official delegations, which mostly involve foreign ministers, don't coordinate
their visits with his government, he said.
</P>
<P>
"We don't understand why they don't meet the elected government. " As a result,
the Hamas government started contacting the UN Relief and Works Agency (UNRWA),
which arranges Gaza tours for Western diplomats, to resolve the problem. "The
visitors must knock the door before they enter."
</P>
<P>
He also called Europe to reconsider its position that bans official talks with
Hamas. The United States led the international campaign to boycott Hamas when it
won parliamentary elections in 2006.
</P>
<P>
Talking about the Israeli blockade on the Gaza Strip, Haneya said the relaxation
the blockade that the Western diplomats come to inspect is not exist.
</P>
<P>
"Israel is lying in its claims that it has eased the blockade," he said, noting
"there is a political, social economical siege and Israel has only done marginal
changes."
</P>
<P>
Israel imposed the blockade when Hamas captured an Israeli soldier from his base
near Gaza in June 2006, but tightened it a year later when Hamas routed
Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas's forces and took over Gaza.
</P>
<P>
Haneya called on Germany, which mediates between Hamas and Israel, to fasten the
discussions to exchange Gilad Shalit, the captive soldier, for Arab and
Palestinian prisoners, saying "we need an honorable swap."
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, Haneya said Hamas "is ready to make the needed concessions" to
reconcile with Abbas's Fatah party, which is now holding sway in the West Bank.
</P>
<P>
But he said the reconciliation should not include "a political price at the
expense of the Palestinians" and it must secure political partnership between
Hamas and Fatah, and the rest of the factions in the political life.
</P>
<P>
Asked if he talks to Abbas, Haneya said he tried to contact Abbas over the phone
on several occasions, but Abbas rejected the calls.
</P>
<P>
Abbas fired a Hamas-led government when the Islamic movement seized Gaza in
2007, but Hamas continued ruling Gaza. Recently, Abbas said that the PNA's
security services should remain outside the frame of any future deal with Hamas.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0010" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Jordan's stock market index closes lower
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
AMMAN, Dec. 1 (Xinhua) - The shares price index of Jordan's Amman stock market
closed at 2,345 points on Wednesday, 9 points lower from Tuesday's finish.
</P>
<P>
A total of 17 million shares were traded through 6,342 transactions. The
turnover was 11.2 million Jordanian dinars (about 16 million U.S. dollars).
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0011" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Iran says foreign investment up 95 pct: minister
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
TEHRAN, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iranian Economy Minister Shamseddin Hosseini said that there has been a
95-percent leap in foreign investments in Iran from last year, local satellite
Press TV reported on Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
Foreign investment in the Islamic Republic topped three billion U.S. dollars
currently and is expected to grow, the minister said on Tuesday, attributing the
rise to the overall security and abundant investment opportunities in Iran,
according to the report.
</P>
<P>
"Iran's economic appeal and its overall security is suitable for investment," he
was quoted as saying.
</P>
<P>
The minister's remarks came amid successive sanctions of the UN Security
Council, the United States and its Western allies against Iran in the past years
over the country's refusal to halt its sensitive nuclear program.
</P>
<P>
The United States, European Union and some other western allies believe Iran's
nuclear program is moving to the atomic weaponry developments. However, Tehran
denied the allegations, claiming that its nuclear program is aimed at civilian
and peaceful purpose.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0012" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Sudanese gov't vows to protect oil field workers regardless of
referendum result
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
KHARTOUM, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Sudanese government on Wednesday vowed to ensure security and safety of all
the workers in the country's oil fields whatever the result of south Sudan
referendum is.
</P>
<P>
"The Sudanese government reiterates its commitment to provide security, safety
and suitable work environment for all the workers at the different oil fields in
the country," said Sudanese Vice- President Ali Osman Mohamed Taha on a
celebration of increasing Al- Fula oil field production in Kordofan State
Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
He added that a package of security arrangements to sustain security at the oil
areas will be adopted regardless of the referendum results.
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, Taha hailed that the productivity increase of Al- Fula oil field for
extra 30,000 barrels a day was a real addition to the country's financial
resources, saying "this is an accomplishment with which Sudan responses to those
who question the promising future of the country in both cases of unity or
separation. The Sudanese people are determined to abort all conspiracies of the
enemies."
</P>
<P>
Besides, Taha said his country appreciates the partners from friendly countries
to invest in agriculture, livestock raising, and infrastructure construction.
</P>
<P>
Oil income consists 90 percent of Sudan's foreign revenues and 45 percent of its
general budget, and it tends to further increase its oil productivity in the
coming years.
</P>
<P>
A referendum on self-determination for southern Sudan is scheduled to be
conducted on Jan. 9, 2011 as it was stipulated by the Comprehensive Peace
Agreement (CPA) inked between north and south Sudan in 2005, which ended a two-
decade civil war between the two sides.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0013" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Turkish deputy PM calls for international cooperation against
corruption
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
ANKARA, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Turkish Deputy Prime Minister Cemil Cicek on Wednesday called for international
cooperation to fight corruption.
</P>
<P>
"Corruption is a cross-border crime today," Cicek told the International
Conference on Anti-corruption Measures in Turkey and Around the Globe jointly
organized by the government and the UN Development Program (UNDP) here.
</P>
<P>
There was a noticeable connection between terrorism and corruption, as terrorist
organizations earned a significant part of their money from corruption crimes,
he said.
</P>
<P>
The anti-corruption conference, to last till Thursday, aims to share anti-
corruption knowledge and experience and help Turkey intensify efforts to fight
corruption.
</P>
<P>
The conference marked the beginning of a project launched by the UNDP Turkey and
the Turkish government to lay the ground for a long-term partnership in the
design and implementation of effective anti-corruption activities.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0014" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Israeli FM acts to prevent airport security humiliation of VIPs
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
JERUSALEM, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Concerned by recent incidents in which VIPs visiting Israel were harassed, at
times humiliated, by airport security checks, Israeli Foreign Minister Avigdor
Lieberman Tuesday directed his ministry to draw a plan meant to assist innocent
tourists or senior officials in case of need.
</P>
<P>
The plan calls for the establishment of a permanent situation room at the Ben-
Gurion International Airport that would be staffed by officials from several
government ministries, local daily Ha' aretz reported on Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
In cases in which a foreign tourist or official would be delayed for
particularly lengthy questioning by airport security personnel, or when harsher
security measures, including deportation, are considered, the situation room
would intervene and possibly prevent faulty judgment.
</P>
<P>
Incidents of this kind "cause serious diplomatic and image damage to Israel," a
Foreign Ministry official, who spoke with Ha 'aretz, quoted Lieberman as saying
at Tuesday's meeting.
</P>
<P>
Security measures at Ben-Gurion, Israel's national gateway, are considered to be
among the most stringent in the world, and are determined and supervised by the
Shin Bet security agency.
</P>
<P>
But good intentions at times result in innocent travelers mistakenly marked as
posing risk. Several high-profile incidents in which prominent visitors were
wrongfully humiliated, occurred over the past year.
</P>
<P>
In May, Ivan Prado, a professional clown hailing from Spain, who had planned to
participate in a festival in Ramallah, was denied entry to Israel after being
wrongfully accused by Shin Bet of having ties to terrorist elements. Two months
later, University of Miami President Donna Shalala went through a degrading
security check prior to her return flight, solely because of her Lebanese
origin.
</P>
<P>
According to official data published recently by the Tourism Ministry, a record
number of tourists arrived in Israel during 2010, exactly three million by mid-
November.
</P>
<P>
Lieberman reportedly told participants at the meeting that in order to maintain
the flow of tourists, Israel has to ensure that they don't leave back home with
"a bad taste in their mouths," the Foreign Ministry official said.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0015" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Two policemen killed in bomb attack in western Iraq
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
RAMADI, Iraq, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Two policemen were killed and two others wounded in a roadside bomb explosion
targeted a police convoy in Iraq's Anbar province on Wednesday, a provincial
police source said.
</P>
<P>
The attack took place in the afternoon near the al-Qaim city to the Iraqi-Syrian
border when a roadside bomb struck the convoy of Mohammed Abdul-Majeed, the
police chief of the city, the source told Xinhua on condition of anonymity.
</P>
<P>
Two of Majeed's guards were killed and two others wounded by the powerful blast
which destroyed two of the convoy's vehicles, the source said.
</P>
<P>
However, Majeed himself survived the attack without injury, the source added.
</P>
<P>
Insurgent attacks continue in the once volatile Sunni Arab area in west of
Baghdad that stretches through Anbar province to Iraq's western borders with
Syria, Jordan and Saudi Arabia. The vast desert area has been relatively calm
for more than three years after Sunni tribes and anti-U.S. insurgent groups
turned to cooperate with the U.S. troops and Iraqi security forces against al-
Qaida network in Iraq.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0016" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Urgent: Egypt's Wafd party withdraws from election
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
CAIRO, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The liberal Wafd opposition party announced on Wednesday its withdrawal from
Egypt's parliamentary election amid accusations that the vote was rigged,
according its official website.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0017" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Iran says "basic questions" should be addressed in talks with
G5+1
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
TEHRAN, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Iran's chief nuclear negotiator Saeed Jalili said Wednesday Iran's essential
questions should be answered in the upcoming talks with the five UN Security
Council permanent members and Germany (G5+1), the official IRNA news agency
reported.
</P>
<P>
Speaking to reporters on the sidelines of the funeral procession for an
assassinated academic, Jalili said the West should respond to Tehran's basic
questions in the talks.
</P>
<P>
He was quoted as saying that "they (Westerners) used all possible ploys,
including resolution, sanctions and political pressures, against us, and getting
assured of their futility, have now resorted to assassination. This is sign of
their desperation and failure."
</P>
<P>
These are Iran's questions and "we look forward to hearing responses to such
questions in the talks," said Jalili according to IRNA.
</P>
<P>
Iranian officials have accused the West and Israel for assassination attempts on
two Iranian nuclear scientists. In two separate terrorist acts in northern
Tehran early Monday, Iranian nuclear scientist Majid Shahriari was killed and
Fereidoon Abbasi was wounded when they were driving to work.
</P>
<P>
The European Union (EU) and Iran are expected to hold talks on Dec. 6 and 7 in
Geneva, Switzerland.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0018" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Hamas court sentences policeman to death
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
GAZA, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A Hamas military court on Wednesday sentenced a Hamas policeman to death for
killing a Palestinian man in a Gaza City market last month.
</P>
<P>
The verdict, which would be carried out by a firing squad, can be appealed to
the higher court, a statement by the Hamas interior ministry said.
</P>
<P>
The murderer was not in his official duty when he shot dead a person and wounded
the second in the market, the statement said.
</P>
<P>
Over the past months, Hamas has carried out the execution of three people
convicted of murder crimes and two accused of collaborating with Israel.
</P>
<P>
By carrying out the executions, Hamas bypass a key article in the Palestinian
law that the president of the Palestinian National Authority (PNA) must ratify
the death sentences. The sentences also provoked human rights groups in Gaza and
officials in the PNA.
</P>
<P>
Jamil Sarhan, director of the Independent Commission for Human Rights (ICHR) in
Gaza, said that the Hamas courts in Gaza "lack the standards of fair trial."
</P>
<P>
Hamas is locked in a power struggle with Palestinian President Mahmoud Abbas,
since it routed his forces and took over Gaza in 2007.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0019" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Turkish police seizes 174 kg hashish
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
ANKARA, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Turkish police Wednesday seized 174 kg of hashish in four separate
operations in Turkey's southeastern province of Diyarbakir, the semi-official
Anatolia news agency reported.
</P>
<P>
Three people, who had been detained in the operations, were later arrested,
according to the report.
</P>
<P>
On Tuesday, Turkish police stopped a car on Tarsus-Gaziantep highway in
southeastern Gaziantep province and searched out 61.4 kg of heroin stashed in
the vehicle, said the report, adding five suspects were detained in the
operation.
</P>
<P>
Turkey is a key transit route for smuggling drugs from Asia and the Middle East
to markets in western Europe.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0020" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Feature: Olive: Syria's ancient green old
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
DAMASCUS, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Legend claims that olive trees appeared first in ancient Syria, nearly 6,000
years ago, before expanding to the rest of the Mediterranean basin.
</P>
<P>
Nowadays, 6,000 years after the spread of olive cultivation from Syria to the
Mediterranean region, Syria is still among the leading producers of olive oil
around the world with over 640,000 hectares of olive orchards and some 100
million olive trees.
</P>
<P>
Do you know that the normal life span of olive tree is 500 to 900 years? There
are even trees alive in the Mediterranean basin that are over 1,000 years, said
Mohamad al-Ahmad, 47 years old, an olive farm owner In Idlib, 350 km north to
Syria's capital of Damascus.
</P>
<P>
"I have this olive farm estimated at 27 acres, planted with olive trees since
1996. Each tree produces 20 kg to 30 kg of olive annually, and every 5 kg of
olive extracts 1 kg of oil," al- Ahamad said, "This olive farm provides me some
4,000 U.S. dollars a year, " he added.
</P>
<P>
"Thousands of Syrian families depend on olive fruits and olive oil products to
live, olive trees are considered as treasure as many of Syrian families grew,
educated and covered their costs through olives and olive oil industry," Firas
Sweid, the Syrian chairman of olive chamber, told Xinhua.
</P>
<P>
Olive oil has many valuable uses beyond cooking, from personal care to home
improvement and natural remedies, but olive oil often goes bad under the best
storage conditions in a few years. Light and heat are its enemies. Storage in a
dark cool cupboard or in dark glass or tin is preferable.
</P>
<P>
Storage in a refrigerator is fine but the oil will turn almost solid so you must
warm it before using. Keep only a small amount next to the range where you need
it for cooking as the heat from cooking degrades it.
</P>
<P>
Olive oil is known to be gentle on the digestive system, and even may help
prevent gallstones and soothe ulcers. Good quality olive oil contains valuable
vitamins and nutrients, and it is loaded with antioxidants, which many believe
help protect the body from cancer.
</P>
<P>
However, Syrian farmers now worry about the future of their olive farms
especially after Syrian agriculture ministry decided that allow only big
companies to export olive products, as well as the severe competitions from
Spain and Italy.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>
<DOC id="XIN_ENG_20101201.0021" type="story" >
<HEADLINE>
Turkey's export growth slow to 7.3 pct in November
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
ANKARA, Dec. 1 (Xinhua)
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Turkey's exports increased by 7.3 percent to 9.4 billion U.S. dollars year-on-
year in November, a slower growth than last month, local media reported
Wednesday.
</P>
<P>
The rate was lower than the 8.8 percent rise in exports in October, according to
figures cited by the semi-official Anatolia news agency from the Turkish
Exporters Assembly (TIM).
</P>
<P>
In the January to November period, exports rose 10.9 percent year-on-year to
102.1 billion dollars, the report said.
</P>
<P>
Automotive industry outpaced other sectors with an export volume of 1.3 billion
dollars in November, followed by textile and chemical, it said.
</P>
<P>
Most of the exports went to Germany, followed by Britain, Iraq, Italy, France
and Russia, data showed.
</P>
<P>
Turkish State Minister for Foreign Trade Zafer Caglayan said Iran, United Arab
Emirates, Egypt, Syria, Israel, Germany, Russia, Iraq and China were among the
countries to which Turkish exports saw a significant rise, Anatolia reported.
</P>
<P>
Turkey targets 111.7 billion dollars of exports for 2010 and 127 billion dollars
for 2011, according to the report.
</P>
</TEXT>
</DOC>